okay so we started recording everything
is fine I
hope
chat no okay good so if there's any
problem you guys if you see in the chat
there's a problem just let me know okay
so now we're going to start our slides
oh why is that not working it just
worked
right
somehow what happened
there
I didn't do anything in work last time
so I didn't do anything special last
time check table and store this to
sleep that
hey all right it's
not same level
with2 that's
4.11 I'm sure the number have being
higher without the occasional presses in
the f
1.1.9
which was distributed on the delivery
start dat as well as small
non-waterproof batch from the
first
I I'm trying to who is talking this guy
let's
mute no size fits the majority of
respondents which is lifting the number
increased by 4.
8% hello somebody who's talking please
mute yourself I know that I can ask to M
oh see this guy I cannot
mute I cannot mute him there is no
option well I think that guy is not
connected to voice anyway oh that he is
connecting so somebody else is talking
okay I think they muted okay is it time
to start no not yet so let me hide this
thing it's too big I don't have much
space here just have extra windows and
let's start
with oh
that's that's in the
way so we'll start with
this and we're going to do slider.com
okay you remember to record I'm
recording already okay thank you that's
very
important and how many people do you
have online 20 and well hey it's not
full room so we're
good oh yeah I need annotation as
well I need
annotation and now I need to present
with speaker notes because
otherwise it gohost
okay I think it's there
there you
go where can I get the zoom
link I sent M
email it's the same one as I usually use
it's my personal can you find it
somewhere
else in some
chats this is a very
small
[Music]
okay okay
okay so I gave you this handouts this is
for the actual lecture so we'll start
with just introduction to the course
then we'll use this and I realized that
my version is so bad last night it felt
like I just don't see
because but now in bright I
see but the idea is that you'll pill out
whatever you can okay so we will have to
understand everything that slide and
it's first lecture that's our goal if
you don't see something and don't
understand what you're discussing just
ask and let me see
here okay so let's start we'll start
with some introductions so my name is
Anna laala I've seen many familiar faces
so many of you have taken course with me
before probably was virtual reality
course of some sort but this is
something new and yet old so I'm going
to be teaching this term the course and
um why I'm going to teach it so let's
see my background I got PhD in 2008 from
un of Illinois at champ and uh my PG
topics were in robotics motion training
and lat VR but I also taught for two
years this c+1 over there um and I had a
great mentor who developed this course
and helped me start there and um it was
a great it was a very good very popular
later on I also was a research stist at
Oculus VR so I had a chance to actually
write code in C++ so I would say
throughout my academic
years industry experience it was more
than a decade that I used C++ on daily
basis um since then then I
have um but nevertheless this is some
picture from my PD years I worked on um
uniform distributions of quan that was
useful for uh VR as well writing had
tracking code for virtual reality at
Oculus it was very useful in C++ so I
will not be doing it alone we will have
here El Ando helping they our teaching
assistants and uh I want you guys to
introduce yourself as well as usual the
same thing so what like why are you here
why do you want to
C++ uh yeah hey and uh yeah I'm I'm
working at the University teacher here I
I was teaching the mobile Computing
course last year and I've been working
on this C++ course as well developing
the like Auto graders for the exercises
uh you're going to be working on as well
as like developing like a new exercise
entirely and yeah I've always like liked
C++ I it was actually the first
programming language I started with
so yeah I'm looking forward
to working here on this course yeah so
these guys are uh going to be more help
for you with debugging your homework
because I'll be probably more
concentrated on preparing the lectures
each lecture is kind of a nice story and
it's very important to remember where to
turn otherwise it will the story will
break so that takes some time and I
really encourage you to come to lectures
because they are fun they they are these
nice stories um but then there is a lot
of work that you guys will have to do in
teams for your lab assignments and
individually for your machine problems
and uh we'll have a lot of support for
you with debugging and El Ando that's
their main job to help
you the t
is uh also going to be on board as our
TA
[Music]
so yeah hello everyone my name is I'm
Bachelor student here and I will be
helping you mainly during the lab
any questions you might have about
General
I I am part of CA because I helped with
debugging the exercise last fall and
otherwise I just and I just asked me to
be here so now yes so so these guys are
experienced
Tas and um they have been helping me
with other courses for many years now El
how many years has it been
five since
2019 and like two already two years yeah
so so they know what they're doing uh
but this is all new to all of us in some
way in some sense so let's see how it
goes this is supposed to be a pilot
course and I'll explain uh later in more
details why
now something exciting is
happening um this course seem to be
important not only because hey we
decided to teach it actually we didn't
decide to teach it we kind of were
pushed in some way because there's a big
need in loc in our community here for
you guys to learn sequence plus so these
companies were all over us for the last
year um kind of encouraging us to start
as course so we talking about fute
mainly but also C no and El so we are in
communication with them and even more
excitingly five members of cute will be
helping you guys on this score they're
already there with deing your homeworks
as well not only us but also those
person and moreover one person from
cute right did I say it right v l he is
largest Ser programmer um but he's also
a member of the C++ senate committee um
so he knows C++ in and out and you know
he goes to those meetings and decides
what should be the next um release of
C++ so he'll be there so that's really
exciting he also will come as an invited
lecturer for one of our lectures in
April sometime I already put it as an
enlighted lecture by him so please mark
the date and come because I think I'm
sure that will be very interesting so
here's full disclosure I think I already
mentioned that I cannot say that I'm an
expert on c i don't practice C++ every
day
anymore which means so what is the
implication for this course I may just
not know really and that's why it's so
important for us to have those guys
because if there's any question that you
can have that we can figure out we have
to have a list of questions for those
guys because I want to learn those
things too and most importantly we are
starting this course with core C++
Notions that are very important so all
of this material is important and um
secret some of it is going to be
pointers that need some stats that's
something that is on interviews at HUD
as well so we we'll start with pointers
already next Thursday it's important
it's core uh core C++ so we'll teach
that but some later things in C++ some
later editions is something that we
don't have in this course yet so in the
future installments we run this course
and see how it goes maybe the last
lectures would have to be changed
somewhere else according to the industry
needs
model that's the dis for that and
actually very exciting things um so
everybody is excited these guys from
those companies they want you to join
them and work there essentially there's
so much code that they have in C++ that
needs to be maintained and they just
don't have qualified people to maintain
it so you could be
them okay um so okay now U many of you
know the drill so you see the white
slide that all the slides are white so
when you see slider.com slide that's
where you take your phones you put that
number ins slide and you go
to um
you see that you can ask me
questions or I can ask you questions
well now I want to learn a little bit
about you let's do what done Exercise
with slide.com so if you there you put
the number let me go back so that you
know the number I don't know why it
doesn't show the number here it should
be it should always show the number
right I hope it works
sometimes like it was not
loading yeah it was us up so do you see
which country you're from is that
something that you can answer is it
answerable no no no no okay let me see
what's going on I'll have to exit the
slideshow and see what's going
on
yeah it should be fine
right ah there you go somehow it didn't
load properly
right okay
so so now what's very exciting about it
is that you guys they
online ah they asked me to be close to
the microphone okay I'll be
I'll try not to walk then
sorry do you know which microphone we're
using this one okay
oh I don't know I I believe I didn't
connect this one would this be the
connection is the camera could be the
microphone difficult yep I'll just try
to be here sorry sorry okay is this
better so you guys can now answer too
the guys who are online can also do the
same thing and they can
[Music]
um they can answer and we see where you
from Russia Finland Finland Finland
India Finland Sri Lanka Vietnam Libya
Egypt Iraq Iran Algeria all over the
world what is BD
Bangladesh yes okay
cool okay so that's kind of how we do it
so now I want to learn about you not
only where you from but where you from
in terms of you know professionally so
what programming languages are you
already comfortable with BB python C and
Java good I imagine that you will have
Java Python
and and C
mhm and not so much C++ do you see
that and mainly python because I know
that python is taught really well here
at University of Olo and Java too but we
are missing as you can see we are
missing C++ and it turns out there was
no C++ course here at University of Alla
for years now for some reason for some
unknown
reason so it's really good to start it
okay let's do it now how would you rate
your understanding of basic C++ Concepts
and already I see that probably one yeah
okay so two some
twos some fours that's good so those who
are at four level or three level you can
actually contribute a lot to this course
by going ahead and then helping
everybody debug in this course just like
you know just like the rest of us on the
staff I I hope to see a lot of Comm uh
communication going on on Discord okay
so what do you like in ter in terms of
software engineering so what do you what
are you passionate about mostly in terms
of
programming embedded systems
cool
web fast programs cool that's C right
then C++ can do that too full St testing
game development okay VR yeah we do VR
and game so so as you can see this is
something that's already been taught
here at University of Olo robotics cool
best so numerical methods or something
like that or financial say
um applications that's something that
needs then understanding how to make
your programs fast and that's what C++
is more about rather than Python and
Java that's why we need to do that to
learn it okay so now pick all the
programming languages Technologies you
already know so actually I wanted to
change I forgot which land is it and I
think I kind of know that okay so you're
coming from Python and c and Java in
that distribution good
good good to
know now what about the rest that's just
for fun like do you like any of those
and how much do you know
including python C and
Java but what about the other things
that you might have experienced
with and I know that you know game
development because we teach it you know
python because we teach it you know
mobile de web development and mobile
Computing because we teach a
train okay look at that c now is number
one and it used to be python hey what's
going on there
now see
maybe
H okay that's interesting so what's good
what's good about c.com is that I can go
back and look at all of the questions
and all of the answers so if there are
any questions that are left unanswered
in Q&A and you probably see that there's
a Q&A there on slider.com you can always
put your question there and you'll get
to
it like uh here see this is Q&A and I
think students just added something they
didn't have a chance to uh didn't have
time to answer but this is Q&A slide and
I have them this Q&A slides every two
slides so that if you have any questions
I make sure that we answer them but here
of course you are welcome
just ient for mon that's the way we do
it so what's the communication I know
that already on love L that's the main
um way for us to communicate what's the
materials right all the materials of the
course are there all of the homework oh
yeah all of the homework all of the
materials uh links to lectures all of
that stuff is there policies it Discord
is for us talk right so that's
um somebody please mute yourself because
I hear
feedback um okay so it Discord you're
there hopefully we don't see as many
people signed up to Discord as on Lovely
so please do that now it's very
important please do not send us
individual DMS or emails we will not be
able to process it so I said 230
students here now it's
270 I don't know today is still a day
where students register and there's no
way for me to put a cap on it so we
wanted to have 40 students in this
course and two weeks ago there was one
student registered so that's when I made
a mistake of sending an mass
email and then we have almost
300 so let's see how it goes um actually
no DMS no uh direct messages it's it uh
wide Discord policy so I I think I was
answering DMS until I learned from the
administrators that it's actually no
really frowned upon like that's the
policy no DMs if you absolutely have to
do something it's something personal
then it's the email because that's the
policy for for Discord but please other
than that if you have a question about
homework just ask everybody because I'm
sure there will be somebody else or
maybe 10 students or maybe even 50 who
have the same
question now course resources so let's
list what's
there this point sign up info oh it's
not actually on the no no no no no it's
not on Lovely because we don't want to
have Bots there so I sent you it's it's
here it's on on this slides right so if
you have yeah on slides you'll have this
link that's it there you go that's your
sign up inform schedule homework exam
materials grading lecture slides YouTube
channel Zoom link I also sent you in
mass email so if you don't have a zoom
link I guess everybody on Zoom has a
zoom link but if you don't have a zoom
link then put on Discord question we'll
put it
there um I think I did maybe now
computer lab is going to be
ts35 so the first lab is going to be
today right after the SE 12 there's only
20 stations there how many people do you
have you might actually fit because if
you make a te then you'll be fine Prett
good surprisingly how how did it work
out have 270 students we have only 4ish
here so no problem no stress I was
really stressed about the situation but
seems like maybe it'll sort of resolve
itself
somehow hello world I have not been
accepted to the course Pepe uh that's
okay so please
send that's a personal question so send
an email I'll get you on Pepe okay
that's an email question see that's
personal because that's personal
information everything else about the
course no personal uh
emails okay course at a glance let's
look at the course schedule so that's
your main page maybe where I really want
you to be familiar with so we'll go
there okay how do you like
it course and deadlines at a glance do
you see this thing is in the way I don't
know how to minimize it it's going to be
in the way and I want to exit this so
that I have control of my windows and
this thing is in the way okay so let's
look at our course here if you go to C++
programming this course schedule at a at
a glance link is your uh very important
link so a goto link that's the schedule
of our lectures schedule of our labs and
also schedule and deadlines for our
homework work so you will have to get
started with setting up your laptop so
start with that wherever you are in the
lab if you have a laptop if you're
planning to work on machines in the lab
go through that process
there um but I think it's preferable
that you'll be working on your laptops
even my little tablet here can run the
virtual machine so that's what we will
guide you through doing and um you can
complete your exercises even on very
small kind of laptop tablet
whatever um however we still have the
machines there so you're welcome to work
there as well uh look how many Labs we
have seven right and we have four MPS I
would say on average for me completing
this exercises was 1.5 hours or two
hours yeah some of them I compl in one
hour when I was repeating and even
second time and the reason is just
because they're long you have to go
through it and read it and understand
what it is that is asking and there are
puzzles there so that means if you don't
know how to resolve the puzzle it may it
longer one I think setting up your
laptop to 5 hours one of the tablets for
no reason that I don't remember but it
took me five hours something didn't work
I don't all of that is which means that
don't leave it until the last
and think of this course as a boot point
this is serious stuff this is how univ
of Illinois like you will spend time
learning this language you cannot learn
a language you cannot use language you
canot communicate in language if you
don't practice it every day so that's
kind of a goal you'll be practicing
every day if you leave it until the last
hours before the deadline you may not be
able to complete it sorry I left my
station here so you will not be able to
complete it right just because you know
your your system will decide to update
and it takes hours
right um so so those things like just
start now just do it okay and I've
noticed that some of you have there's
one student who completed everything
already and we want to talk to you
whoever that is like really really you
can help us help
us okay so that's really cool so which
means that you know you can like you can
if you just do it it's not unheard of to
spend 20 hours a week on the
course how it is and you know what since
it's a pilot we'll run it the way it was
at the University of Illinois why not
that's that course was a legend we want
to repeat the same experience because it
was also known that if you go through
this you get a job if if you go through
it successfully you get a job so full
stop okay um some MPS take longer on
average because that's individual
assignment and it it is kind of
scheduled to take two weeks versus one
week um you should do this individually
you should do this in a group
of you know what is it three people can
I
look I forgot what I said oh no groups
yet okay I think it's three
people I wasn't sure I was
yeah I think it's three whatever it says
here actually Let's see we have forming
groups didn't say it there okay let's
let's figure it out because you'll be
forming groups right now and I know that
it's this information is right
here three people so okay very helpful
because then you can interact and solve
those problems so three people per
group
okay let's go back to our slides let's
see what else I wanted to say here so
course schedule is is is
tough now how do you complete your
homework your own laptop as I said is
preferable there's PCS in ts1 35 which
is fine but they just not many of them
and however if you have to use them the
good news is that after 400 p.m. and on
weekends they yours for you so you just
do it um but the first option is
preferable because um because of the
size of the class okay let's go through
the questions I have not been accepted
to the course in Pepe many other people
have this problem also I noticed that
because we have 270 on Lovel
and 230 on pepy so I think there's 30
people that are missing somewhere I
wanted I even have a slide about it like
where are you people why are you not on
pey okay that means I'll get 30 idual
emails and that's fine because I'll get
you in then that's important hello
world we do we need to register both in
love less and tudo I don't know what
tudo is instructors don't have tudo I
have no idea maybe who are more close to
you guys in terms of like they I think
by T they mean py then yeah once you're
in py you'll get your tudo schedule
right it's for
schedules what is recommended group size
three you can do it alone by the way
you're welcome to do all of the labs
alone or two people that's fine but you
can have up to three and the system will
not let you have more so that's um is it
possible no it's not possible because
it's set up to three we don't want four
people four people groups are known to
be
less less use less they don't work out
as well as three or two two are not as
well three is a really good size for
groups in terms of who does what work
okay is it possible to do lab
assignments alone yes yes yes yes okay
so that's how the Q&A works so very
useful do you guys have any questions so
far just raise your hand do you get
feedback even if you get full marks and
levels maybe the solution is not
perfect
um that's where I think I really expect
you to go to ask these questions on this
Discord and we'll discuss your solution
whether it's perfect or not whether it's
elegant or not whether it's good writing
style or not coding style or not so
that's that's a perfect question and
please ask these kind of questions on um
on
Discord I cannot guarantee that we'll
answer all of them depending on the size
but we'll try that that's what we really
want to do guide you through this yeah
so how do we ask this kind of question I
mean we are not uh we shouldn't reveal
our code yeah be careful of
course
um first of all after the deadline you
could so this is a if it's a coding
style question then after afterwards
it's fine um although some students may
be still submitting later so I'll talk
about late submission policy we do have
late submission policy but I think it's
fair game to to do that you be able to
like link answer to the submission on so
us can that's true that's another that's
an elegant
solution you can say hey can you look up
at my yeah that's a that's a better
solution I'm not sure cute guys will
have access to that yeah I guess we're
gonna talk
with yeah we can add them Grant
MTA
l so yeah yeah little for m
is there many no there's no restriction
how many times you can try to submit on
love La so love La is essentially a web
compiler so you submit your solution you
submit your files it'll compile it spit
out whatever it is if it doesn't compile
it will tell you
why and if it doesn't run if there's
memory it will tell you that as well so
you'll have feedback and you can
continue submitting
it um as long as many as many times as
you want do we get feedback even if we
get oh yeah yes I answered that okay
cool grading so let's look at the
distribution for individual assignments
there are four of them 40 points Labs 37
points because one of them is a little
longer seven points every other lab is
Five
Points exam will be 30 points so it'll
take a big chunk of your grade because
well it's important then will be
something unpredictable unknown
something that's harder to find on web
uh MPS and Labs you may find some
similar solution somewhere and I'll have
the the slide about academic
Integrity um but you know just or you
may ask your friend you know we we just
really want to make sure that exam will
correct for that that will be just you
having an enormous amount of work to do
in two
hours that is really hard to find
Solutions any anywhere or ask CH GPT you
know those kind of things so exam will
correct for any kind of problems like
that we'll really want to make sure you
you know what you're talking about there
so total points you can see that they
add up more to to more than 100 which
means that there's extra credit right so
if you miss one assignment you may still
compensate later and you pass if it's
more than 65 points so you need to do
all of the homework if you want to pass
right uh at least
and that's that's a good thing and this
is the grade distribution so you get a
five if you are really fluent in C++
which is more than
95 but remember there's extra credit
right okay there's chat
question oh yeah please ask on on um
these kind of questions now on
slider.com
okay so now late submission policy so if
you submit after the deadline you get
80% % for assignment no
exceptions oh if you have an official
document yeah yes sure but but it's a
small
enough it's a small enough
um what's the right
word penalty penalty yeah that's small
enough penalty so no problem right um
take your time with it but we just don't
we don't encourage it
because if
you if you start being late with your
submissions then what you'll be late
right okay and so so this means that
roughly you lose one or two points per
late submission and there are many
submissions are seven labs and four and
P so you can lose a lot of points if you
do it late so what's the point
right don't do it late it's very
important to keep deadlines so some St
people are much more productive if
there's a deadline so that's why we have
very straight deadlines but the penalty
is not so
bad now a little bit about the history
of the course so it's modeled after the
C++ course at U as I said and I taught
it personally for two years there were
700 more than 700 students there so we
are prepared this course is the
infrastructure is ready to take a lot of
students it's just that we didn't want
to do it in the pilot run here so we
don't have physical space so the
physical space is the bottleneck but hey
maybe it's not
so we'll see and um yeah as I said be
prepared to work really hard and um
maybe spend 20 hours of work of work a
week but in the end of the day
hopefully you know you you Le a job if
you do really well and that's our goal
our goal is to connect you with the
local industry needs so what the scores
is
like for some of you it may feel like
you're a surfer and there's big wave and
there may be weeks where the wave is
just you feel like that's it and that's
when you go on Discord and ask us
questions okay there may be sharks there
not just friendly Dolphins maybe really
really bad stuff you know maybe it will
feel
overwhelming and you have to work hard
and keep going right so that's that's
the goal that's kind of the idea that's
the metaphor here that's the what the
course is
like guys can you please mute
again because I I hear myself if you're
stuck Discord just Discord please ask we
really want to
help and uh don't wait until the last
minute I think I went through this again
because there may be so many problems
that unpredictable things that will take
time and you lose your points academic
Integrity don't
plagiarize don't just don't uh it's
disservice right it's disservice like if
I ask Google translate I don't learn the
language so if you ask chat GPT maybe I
try to run all of the assignments chat
GPT uh I think you really need to know
C++ in order to use the answers so so I
think it may slow you down significantly
on some assignments and introduce bugs
that you'll be like you know it's longer
to solve them then just write it
yourself so so just don't do it it's a
disservice to yourself right it is it
just robbing you off uh from this
experience of understanding things there
are really nice puzzles there that if
you do it you'll have a good feeling
about yourself so just do it that way
however we will run the plagerism check
in the end so if you find
you similar code with your friends on
individual assignments you know we'll
will follow whatever the GU guidelines
for that so just don't do it it's not
worth it
and also the exams are tough so if you
don't do the work yourself um then it
will be really really hard to do it
quickly on the
exam oh I forgot to mention that you can
complete any work from anywhere not only
from home from airplane anywhere I've
had students who are flying back home
and were submitting uh exams on from
airplane as long as you have a good
connection and you have your laptop it
just works you can do it from anywhere
so we really excited actually about uh
lovely and US putting our courses there
because you can be anywhere that's cool
so this is the numbers again uh oh okay
so there's
274 students and Lovel and only 240
students and Peppe I already hear you
that you guys could not get on Pepe I'll
help you with that but there's some
students who are registered in love not
with University email so here's the
trick if you didn't use your University
email please raise your hand if you
didn't use your University email anybody
here so if it's not all P the fee on uh
love L you do not get a credit for the
course because I we just for for all we
know we don't know who you are we don't
know how to locate you in our system
some students are here from om and
you're welcome you just cannot get a
grade if you're not registered through
University email and if you're not on
Pepe so there are some students who want
to take this course just because just
because it is a needed course right and
you're welcome I'm just saying that if
you want a grade you have to be enrolled
on Pepe with University email and I've
seen I think at least 10 people not with
University email you don't get a grade
if you don't do if you don't change
it
okay can I ask yes
so so if I have enrolled with the
University email but I have not been
able to find this course so on yeah so
I'm just wondering like how it happens
you send me an email and I'll enoll you
on but there four cases when I did that
for students in the past and still their
program managers complain that they
didn't go through them like maybe
depending where you are maybe you have
to make sure that they'll let you sign
up on
pep and that's only for getting credit
again you're welcome to just go through
assignments and do it yourself but if
you need credit for it then you I may
help you get an Pepe but it may not be
enough your program might
complain okay does that make
sense uh yes I will check so it's just
good to know that this class should be
in pep so it should be
yeah okay okay but send me an email
then okay so those are the only
individual emails about uh getting
on are the exercise sessions so that we
can only ask help for exercises or is
there like extra info that we need in
order to complete the exercises I think
we'll see how it goes what what do you
think guys will there be extra
information or will it be just ask
questions
probably just questions just questions
yeah unless it seems like there like a
big problem that everyone is if
everybody has the same problem then we
will then Tas during the El Maran during
the lab sessions they'll explain things
but then we'll make sure that we repeat
the same explanation say on Discord
right so if there was if there will be
the same question over and over then
we'll just posted on Discord that
discussion okay what is the email to
send to the Pepe query uh on
laal so like everybody has first name
last name first name. last name
at what is the course go I don't know
sorry
okay um but again please send me the
email about that and we'll I'll find
that number I just don't know it off the
top of my head and pep is way too slow
for me to load it now if you have the
answer to that question please post it
by the way if you if you can find the
number on Pepe for other students okay
or post it on Discord that
you now to-do list for today so go to
the lab and now the exercises so you
should start on this three exercises
today laptop set up instructions right
away lab GDB and make file tutorial
because the deadlines for these two
assignments is in one week so you
probably feel like okay let's get to
work let's get to work I think I'm done
with all of the infrastructure questions
we'll get to work okay everybody on
board we'll get to work inro that's in
one
week oh did I say l GB ha yeah it's
l yeah sorry well it's on yeah okay good
correction okay I see more
questions are
questions will this year's lectures yes
I'm recording the lectur so all lectures
I'll be recorded this is the number on
py so I hope it's useful you can see it
take a screenshot because I'm going to
switch to our work so let's start
on keep annotations okay let's start on
our
next
lecture and I'm going to start slideshow
with presenter view
because otherwise it'll kick me out from
this mode okay cool let's put this here
let's put this here out of the way we're
going to start talking about Hello World
classes and a little bit about
encapsulation if you notice why slider
it's it's doing it again right is it
doing it
again there is no
number how did I just try again right
try again yep maybe I should start with
slide though yeah exit slideshow maybe I
should re before it wasn't like this ah
yeah okay sorry slider is changing it's
a very useful thing to have because I
can have feedback like this
but they constantly update and I have to
get used to like the new
things and it's
slow okay so we are switching to another
presentation and it's another slide.
come because of that here so if you have
any questions put it there now we'll
have to do this so let's follow your
print out and you know some people
really learn well if they write so
you're welcome to do that please raise
your hand if
you um please your hand if you learn by
writing
[Music]
always upload slides on Google Drive and
work on your computer write over those
slides online and many of you I see have
tablets do that but if you appreciate
this just give me feedback if you
appreciate this slide print outs then
we'll keep going with
those
okay or Nina raised hand
you
uh I don't know what it means
okay so this is our first
slide we can do anything without
variables so many of you probably know
about variables in C++ already but let's
just go through it let's see what we
have
to do what what what is the deal with
variables in C++ so every variable will
have a
name a
type
value and location in memory okay so
here's one variable I'm going to declare
and this is going to be my declaration
so I'm going to declare a variable in
C++ so it's going to be
declaration I'm going to say
buan is here and let's see if it has all
four so what's the name is here type
bullan what's the
location it's implicit
yeah some address right some address but
you don't know it it's implicit the
system will give it will provide that
location for that variable and what's
the
value the system will most likely just
recycle whatever was at that location
because you didn't provide any value you
just declared a variable so we call it
garbage so let's draw garbage bin here
we call it a garbage because it's
recycled stuff cool now this there's a
so we covered this there's another
variable
declaration so these are going to be
declarations my favorite int has name my
favorite int type
integer location implicitly provided by
the system value garbage okay so I could
actually
Define can you mute please because I
hear myself again I could actually have
definition definitions
here and I could actually Define or
prescribe the value that I want to be
stored in that location for is sphere
and I say true and I put
semicolon because in C++ it will not
understand that it's the end of the
statement unless you put semicolon so
that's a delimeter of
statements and um and then I put that
value true
in that location okay and in C++ there
will be a way to
control which location for the variable
will be assigned by the system or
sometimes you can just allow the system
to pick yourself for itself so you can
combine declaration and definition in
one line like this so for this um type
character CH rating name rating you can
give value e
to be in that implicit location and
W uh half
37.0 value okay so these are both
declarations and definitions so what's
interesting about it is that these are
primitive types right and you can Google
C++ has lots of primitive types but
they're not very interesting right
they're primitive so what's really good
about C++ is that it allows you to
Define your own types and the user
defined types are called classes you
probably heard the word class from java
but this is slightly different here
because in C++ classes or user defined
types are meant to be treated exactly as
if they were primitive types so the
syntax is going to be the same so here
is a
declaration of a variable with the name
my favorite sphere type sphere and that
is a user defined type a class class
sphere which you know will spend some
lectures defining in many different ways
including today how we would Define this
class sphere but so far we declare a
variable of that type right and what its
location again just like with primitive
types it's whatever system will choose
and the value is garbage so far because
we didn't Define it right so to
summarize let's write down what a class
is so
definition a
class is a group
of so here's what what is that do you
know primitive types
yeah or a group of we call it variables
variables yeah
variables very good a group of variables
so you can think of dat data associated
with
that user type and
functionalities the functions
functions because let's think about what
this instance of a sphere should be it
should be something we want to do with
spheres right and something that it
stores so um the the way we'll decide
design the class will be defining this
group of variables and functions of what
can be done and what these spheres are
and let's look at the next slide to
start doing exactly
that the C++ variables doesn't have any
default values yeah yeah some sometimes
it'll have the it depends on the
compiler so you should never let the
rely on default
values that's good practice to have full
control of what is initialized if you
leave it up to the system it could be
some default vales or it could be really
truly
garbage depending on the
compiler uh what if we compare variables
to Define value yeah yeah I think I
answered the question
right okay so now let's start designing
the class and on your printouts I
realize that the cop here didn't see
those colors but you can draw on top
that we have this oh that one shows it
okay sometimes projectors don't show
Colors either so let's look at this
possible spheres and see what kind of
variables do we want to have associated
with this class and what kind of
functionalities so what would you want
the Spheres be or how would you want
them to be different right so what could
be the data associated with the sphere
or representing the sphere what would be
the variables
representing radius yeah very good so
let's see so data or variables
variables could be radius very
good but then this purple sphere or
magenta sphere and this green sphere
they are like twins right they're not
different if that's your design so this
is a design Choice as a software
engineer you'll always have these
choices what do I want to uh the sphere
class or user defined class to represent
and um you want maybe you want the
Spheres to be twins but maybe not and
then you would pick another variable say
color
right and then based on color these
little guys here they're all tuplets
right eight identical spheres because
they have the same radius and the same
color and if you want them to be
different you would maybe introduce
something else
right like U what
Center coordinate
the center right so
location then then it would make all of
and if that's what you want that's what
you do now functionalities what would
you want the Spheres to
do I don't know we don't know yet right
we don't have any code in mind but I
want to write my first class and I have
my
uh
um yes I have my Ubuntu here so I can
actually go to lectures and I want to
start writing let me remove my program
CPP and remove okay maybe out okay so I
want to start writing my first program
so I'm going to say program
CPP and we are going to write this
class and I think you have it
on but I'm going to start with the
keyword class so this keyword says that
it's going to be the definition of the
user type with the name whatever follows
after the keyword class
sphere and then I put curly brackets
here and put semicolon right there for
the compiler to know that that's the end
of my user find user type
definition hey that's it I wrote my
first program I wrote my first
class now I can show you how to compile
this little program so we call the G the
C++ compiler we will use
g++ there may be better compilers out
there but that's what we use for now
maybe in the future itations will change
depending on how it goes but all you do
is you compile this program CPP
and what the compiler will do it will
first check the syntax if everything is
correct and second it will create an
executable to run the code so first
check the syntax then create this
machine code into the
executable and then so that you can run
it and in fact make pile tutorial walks
you through the process very well it's a
very well written tutorial about how to
compile many files together and how then
these uh build-in blocks for machine
code are linked together but this is
just one file so there's no linking much
so let's see what they what it does H it
bared so
so and this means that something went
wrong either with syntax or with the
building so in this
case and kind of guess what's going
wrong so I don't know if you can
look hey guys please mute yourself um
the sentence says something complaining
about main so do you know what went
wrong I have a question here maybe some
of you already know why doesn't it
compile huh
you can
answer you can answer on
slider need the main function that's
true okay so it will never if you don't
have a main function so main function is
this magical control station that's
where everything starts it's really nice
to know that you know you can always
untangle
starting with the main function I wish I
could mute you know my
whole you should be able to but it's
mute do you see that like it's somewhere
in Zoom where I should mute participants
and if I mute myself yeah oh
participants yeah like open the
participants and
then
no no please guys
ask please ask on
slidec sorry they're like it's so mean
to make fun of them you know they online
really sorry that's how it goes you guys
you don't have physical self to to stand
by yourself okay so need the main right
so the main function is the control and
you can untangle the whole logic of your
program just looking at what main does
and then going inside see what they do
so there's no main program program it
will not uh compile it it actually in
terms of syntax it's it's okay it just
doesn't want to build an executable
because there's no main function there's
nothing to build so let's fix it I'm
going to do the bare minimum and that
will be your next slide already so I'm
going to say okay you need a main
function let's write a main function so
I'm going to say int main it's a
function so
um so it will have it may have some
parameters but in this case it's a bare
minimum and I don't put a semicolon here
don't ask me why I forget I always
prepare and I forget and this time I
even forgot to prepare like I don't know
why there's no semicolon here but it's
important for the syntax to have
semicolon your classes anyway if it
doesn't compile try a semicolon
sometimes and it will one of this deals
but I'm sure there is a more
sophisticated explanation that we
should uh we should send it to
V okay
so is it good now any questions any
surprises
here yeah question related to my
previous question that I asked that so
you said that the compiler defines the
uh default values for the very
right so if we use some kind of
comparison operation that will not
return an error right it will just maybe
return some garbage because yeah and
different garbage
depending no error always need oh no no
no right right it will be runtime error
versus compile error yeah if if if
you're relying oh the if you're relying
on some default behavior of the system
sometimes it can be Insidious bugs
errors those are really really hard to
find and that's why the good practice is
to never rely on
this
stuff one question about that so I
remember there was something related to
this like when you define main they
always use this
void void that's C right so here in C++
it has to be integer so that's the
convention it has to be integer so you
have to return some integer and this is
also controlled for you so you can say I
I return zero and then I'll know that if
the return value is zero then the
function executed to that line so you
can put something like control blocks
and depending on what's returned you'll
know where it's sto and didn't work but
that's the convention so you might want
to put void here you might and then some
compilers will complain I mean the
compiler will have to figure out what
did you mean and some of them will
figure it out and some of them will not
I know C++ it will not it will just not
compile it'll say Hey you have to return
an integer value for me but you can uh
try it on different compil and see how
it works okay are we are we what's the
time
11 oh so we still have half an hour yes
okay good okay so so far so good
right so the logic it's very important
for me to follow what what is the story
so we're building this little program
from bare minimum our main function is
now very boring and the class is boring
does nothing but I hope it'll compile
now what do you think
yay all clean no complaining and what is
going to happen do you see what happened
in my directory I'm listing all of the
files so this is my program CPP and new
green file an executable has been
created and by default an executable is
called called a out sometimes it's a as
utable but and you can change that so
main file tutorial will will help you
with that so you can I can say that okay
I want it to be called program as aable
you know like that and then I list the
program the files and I have programable
so you can direct the compiler to do
many things to name files and in fact
you can write a make file script that
will direct the compiler to do things in
different steps and that's what m file
tutorial is about how to write those m
files that will follow the steps of
compilation of different files into the
Final Exit or into several exit if you
want so that's cool but by default so
let's go back to our slide and fill out
this
things um I'll come back so let's let's
not forget to come back back to this
questions but let me just finish this
for for this little simple program
CPP I compile it with this
command I compile a chat synx I created
as a uable a out by default sometimes a
as eable and to run you have to put dot
slash so to running aable from the Comm
from the terminal you put a uh dot slash
a out the name of your utable and then
the output was did we run it we didn't
run it yet so do slash out what do you
think will be the
output nothing nothing it does nothing
it's a very Bor boring program Okay cool
so let's go back to the
questions yeah we I answered this
one we can use signed main instead uh
yeah uh what's the difference we can use
signed main instead of original yeah I
think so signed
integer versus I've never uh tried it so
that's this is an example of a question
that if you really want to know I think
most of our uh Labs will have integer
maybe you can use sign maybe not I could
try to run it like if you had your
laptop you could take that program and
see if it compiles I don't know that's
the question that is a little bit
nuanced and I don't I don't know sorry
but this is the example of a question
that we should keep and maybe like keep
a list for like if if uh our cute guys
would want to answer those or
not please repeat that question I just
deleted the one that was there sorry
sorry didn't mean to I remember it was
like what's the best way to learn C++
this feels difficult this seems
difficult
no
no I don't know
I'm sorry this a yes it's a language you
know Finnish language is difficult d++
is not like I have to tell
you if you speak Finnish then you can do
it if you don't speak finish I you still
can do it because finish is hard C++ it
just practice okay you'll write this
program many times you'll be able to
write a simple hello world problem but
then what is really cool about our
assignments is that we'll never ask you
to write anything from scratch instead
we'll give you a bunch of code and
you'll look at it and it's a
well-written code and you'll have to
just figure some bugs that we planted
okay so the first uh lab it's like only
maybe a couple of lines that you really
will have to
write and those lines can we figure out
from this uh contest here you know and
ask us so like don't be worried it's
it's a language it's a language so it's
new and I get it it's hard but we're
going to write more so now we're going
to write more in our main
function we're going to create a Holo
World okay so I'm going to start writing
it and you guys tell me what's
surprising about
it okay now if you freaked out before
now probably it's time to freak out
what's okay this is um yeah different
keybord okay so I want to say hello
world good
and and S CD blah blah and line
character two lines that I'm going to
add which like look probably very
foreign so I'm going to say hash let me
figure out which one is Hash here hash
or pound include angle bracket I
stream and go
bracket okay oh thank you yeah stream
yep that one work okay so any surprises
pound include what does that
mean well I want to print something
right so
just uh proper C++ has very little
functionality so over time a lot of
developers put together the code that
was useful for their projects for many
many projects and they put it into
libraries and that's the point of the
C++ standards committee they meet very
so often and they release new updates to
this libraries every four years or so
and uh printing is useful so we'll
probably use that pound include I stream
in every assignment because we will
print stuff and that's a bunch of
functions so I stream is input out
Stream So related to printing why do I
use this angle
brackets that says that it's standard
Library so I could use quotes and that
would be my own stuff to include in my
my own local directory but if it's
standard library then the compiler will
know that it's from angle brackets so
that means that whenever the compiler
sees some unusual things like this C out
or end line it look in included stuff in
this case in our stream and we'll try to
find what is this function C out which
is standard
output so to read this line you take
this strain hello world and redirect it
with this operator which is double less
than redirected
to standard out and then you also put
the end of line character and also send
it to standard out standard out is the
line on the ter terminal right so that's
the center output so there you
go that's the sent so what's with this
STD double column so there's a thing
that is a very very bad yeah so is C++
sensitive to SPAC system upad so or did
you no like it's not it's not it's not
you only put that for cl yeah
yeah um so I could put like this I don't
care I could put like this I don't oh it
doesn't let you because it's a you Ed
but example
thisd yeah put here don't put uh a space
between this because it's an operator
yeah but over there it doesn't matter
yep so don't put it between semicolon so
some of them are so say this is the
resolution scope operator so it's
important to not put then um it'll look
directly to the left directly to the
right uh but let me talk about this
SD double colon thing so I could say
using name
space
STD and I would say hey compiler look at
that in standard library look at the Nam
space so standard library has many Nam
spaces many regions associated with
different functionalities so take this
STD and bring all of the functions for
use as if I were to write them myself
that's pretty bad because then the is a
potential for collisions right what if I
what if somebody else will write C out
for I don't know for some other purposes
like this is standard this is standard
output what if I want to use it for some
something else right so there's a a a
possibility for collisions and that's
why this is a bad practice to bring all
of the STD there but if you work then
you could simplify your syntax like this
because then see out and n End of Line
character would be in your scope
immediately from standard Library so
double column is scope resolution
operator and if you need to look at some
user defined Scopes you use it but you
can also using name spaces you can bring
all of those in your
local uh
environment local scope is this clear so
uh let me clean up clean up this things
it just looks bad but okay so let me try
to compile let's
see you have this code by the
way uh in the in
your oh yeah this is where it's really
hard to read
right so but you have your hello world
here yes no typos so I can run it and we
hope to see Hello World right so it does
what we expected it prints hello world
two standard
output okay so we're done with this
right we wrote all of this except that
please don't use like there's entire
threads on Reddit and core core and
stuff like that where um or stack
Overflow where people argue why you
should never use name spaces however if
you know what you're doing it's fine
it just be careful because then you
sometimes there could be even things
where a wrong function is called because
of usern name spaces because of the
collisions and you'll never find out so
so it's better to do STD do semi colum
colum any
questions okay well I think this see out
is
really creepy because after that I think
it'll be easier so if if you if you're
fine with this it'll it'll get easier
now more logical so finish is difficult
I still can do not do it so will this be
hard yes I told you it's a boot camp it
is going to be really really hard but
you'll love
it could you also use using names space
stdc out yes so that's a better practice
bring only what you need to
survive if you know that line uh from
Space Balls Okay so
um see out and then you would also have
to include STD Colin colon and line and
then you're fine you can use those so so
you just Brint only the functions that
you want I understand that stream has
all functions as CNC out yes but why
would they put them inside STD and make
us use the resolution scope I don't know
oh ask V he knows he's part of the guys
who did it so we can ask them so does
STD see out mean that you call a
function called C out from Center
Library class yes yes yes yes yes
yes yes that's a function and then
there's operators that you know just
like bra all sorts of uh brackets that
you could use you could redefine uh
those operators and to do whatever you
want in C++ which is really really
cool okay and we'll show you how to do
that now I'm going to build even more do
you remember that useless class that we
did in my program well it's there it
compiles so it's a type it acts just
like a type so maybe I can declare a
variable of that type right with the
value with the name a type sphere some
location and garbage value right so
let's see should it compile
now let me write a little more according
to to what we have on your um notes here
we'll also write this we'll put
public so we'll Define regions in the
class that will do different things so
each class
in um in C++ can have three regions and
let's talk just about two now public and
private so if you don't do it everything
will be private so if you don't write it
by default it will be private
which means that so if everything is
private that means that only functions
or members of the class can use anything
that's private to that class so no
other
things can access it so for example this
a sphere and therefore main function
cannot have access to private variables
or
functions therefore it's very important
to have control and explicitly design
your class so that you have public
functionalities and private
functionalities private functionalities
are only visible inside of the class to
the members themselves but then public
functionalities can be used by what we
called a client code that is this main
function is in this
case so is this clear let's see is this
surprising let's see what I wanted to uh
to say here on my slide
yeah so we declared uh
sphere a of type sphere and we defined
two regions we didn't put anything there
yet and that's the goal of the next
slide and we are on the next
page so now it's the design
question what do you want this sphere to
be so what will be the representation
that is variable variables associated
with this class
and what should be the functionality do
you remember we had radius as
representations and color and location
right so let's keep radius as
representation and this is the Syntax
for that and we put it in
private and I have a question for you
why do you think radius should be
private so this means that from main
function we can never access radius we
can never change it is that a good
choice let's think about it so what if I
I still want to change radius somehow
maybe right I want to have control but I
want to completely control what the
client will be able to do with my sphere
so maybe if they change radius I will
ask like oh what if it's negative then I
will not let them do that right so I
don't want the client code here directly
access this radi because they may change
it to something that I don't want so I
want instead to provide maybe the
functionality see how I wrot it
here maybe I want to provide the
functionality
instead for doing that oh
yeah
so maybe
instead one of my
functionalities should be being able to
change the sphere
in some way including radius right and
then it's control behavior and that
should go in
public something that clients can do but
my sphere representation or data will be
something that I protect with private
region so that nobody can access it and
change it in unwanted manner right so
what other functionalities do we want
with spheres what would you want to know
about the sphere
Maybe
do you want to know the radius or
something else right maybe you want to
know like volume or something so like
get information about it get
information about the sphere and here we
have this um sample function get
diameter for
example so maybe we want to change this
sphere and that will be the function set
radius we might want just to create cre
here as well so there's many more things
that you might want to do create
sphere many things that you might might
want maybe you want to add spheres maybe
you want to divide them in some way
maybe what color them draw them print
them you know many things that you might
want to do but this is just for
Simplicity let's start with this so I'm
going to go to my code and please now
see maybe I'll make some mistakes so
here's functionality for
creating and this is called a
Constructor so this is going to create
sphere so why do you know and compiler
knows that it's a Constructor well it's
a
function with no return type you see it
doesn't return anything and the name of
the function is the same as the class so
that's how the compiler will know that
it's the Constructor that's something
that will build the object um
okay the object of this type now the
second one was void set radius because
it doesn't have to return anything we're
just going to change the radius
radius and we want to give a parameter
or Double R
right and um the last one was we want to
get the diameter so we want to return
type double and we want to get a
diameter
okay so what do we want to do with this
functions maybe we want to print out get
diameter
instead so how do we do that we created
an object of type sphere a in order to
access its functionalities you put a dot
so it's kind of like scope resolution
operating for types but for objects of
that type in order to access the
functions you need to put dot for types
themselves like spere you need to put
scope resolution double column to access
uh the members but for the objects of
that type you put a dot to access the
members so I can say get diameter and
that way I will print
out the diameter of the
sphere does this look good so we created
functionalities creating a
sphere change sphere change it and get
information get
information about
it so I'm going to compile
[Music]
it doesn't like it I have a question for
you I'm going to this is
the moment for you to answer why does
that H why did that
happen why doesn't it compile yeah we
didn't Define the function for we
actually didn't give the code to run
those functions right we only declared
them right we only declared the
functionalities we didn't give the
provide the code to build that is it
unable yeah that's why it's complain yep
I honestly did not no it only has
functions declarations not
implementation do you see that we
prescribed to set radius of this value
but we didn't tell how there's no code
right H okay good good good good so we
have to write the code right but um
let's do it but I think I want to say
something about this line
though do so so what what does it do
when I
declare a variable of T sphere what is
this here what is the value of it then
we know that it's garbage right but
what's the location how does the
compiler know what to even do do you
have does anybody
know or can take
guess
so we actually have control some control
of what's going to happen upon
Declaration of that sphere and this is
the line when you declare this sphere
here this is where a
Constructor is called so this function
that we just wrote or declared but
didn't Define so this
Constructor is called so before we wrote
this
function a default Constructor was
called and that default Constructor did
nothing right but you have control you
can actually write your own construction
and you can then prescribe what should
happen at that moment okay so that's uh
something to remember we'll talk about
Constructors much more later but that's
something to remember that over here
something important happens and if you
were to actually write the Constructor
and you would um put a print out
statement of some sort sort in your
Constructor here after this line it
would print out whatever you put
whatever you say so let's write these
functions okay let's write them H where
do oh wait sorry we need to
also put the representation ofhere right
with
radius
okay okay so now I'm going to write my
functions so which as we're going to
write let's write set radius and get
diameter and we'll leave out we'll keep
the default Constructor for now so I'm
going to write this function
avoid H
sphere so you already know this scope
resolution operator because otherwise
the compiler will not know which set
radius is it we need to actually say
that this is the sphere set radius that
we're going to define Double R so so far
I wrote the signature of this
function okay so this signature and
let's uh go please actually
yeah or sphere yeah it's outside yeah so
very very good this is something that
can be written in many ways and write it
in one way but there's three ways to
write definitions of the functions so
I'm going to write it outside of the
sphere class
definition and now explain why in a bit
but let's first try it so if it's
outside then it's not clear if I would
not write the sphere double column it
wouldn't be clear which set radius it is
because there may be balls with set
radius and maybe some other things that
will want to set the radius as well so
it's very important out if you're
outside of that class to Define which
scope this radius belongs to and this is
the signature of this function the
return type the parameter type and the
name and the scope right but now we'll
actually write down what it should do so
what should you do if you set the radius
you just say Okay this private member
radius is equal to
R and remember private members can only
be accessed by the
members of the class itself so this is
the m radius function is the member of
the class so it can U access radius and
change it that's good so this is where
you could also put a state if statement
like if radius is greater than zero so
you could control how the client is
going to set this radius and that it's
proper okay and now let's write the
function signature for get diameter so
double
scope scope resolution operator get
diameter and now the actual
implementation so curly braces or curly
brackets and what do you want
return two times radius again we can
access the private member because this
is the member function okay so now
hopefully we should get some diameter to
be printed
out and hopefully there will be no
compilation errors let's
check no compilation errors we run the
program zero why is
that ah because of the Constructor The
Constructor actually does nothing right
we rely on default constructure so
default constructure does nothing it
doesn't assign any radius to the sphere
let's write a
Constructor do you want to write a
Constructor I don't think I have that in
my slides so this is a little bit
of um so let's set radius
to equals 10 that's my that's my
construct it's really silly right it
really doesn't do much nothing
interesting or useful or even meaningful
right but that's what it is so what do
we expect
now what's the
output diameter 20 yay so do you see now
that we defined and sorry in the in the
slides I don't have definition of the
Constructor but it's just another line
for defining the in the same way with
the function signature of the
Constructor and what it has to
do and now it's very clear for you guys
right that in this main function here
the Constructor is called and now it
assigns radius to
10 that's good and then we call get
diameter actually I could even
maybe set the diameter to something else
now so I could say
a or set radius set radius
to
five and let's do a double so that
there's no I don't want to deal with
cast yet we'll talk about it
later and now what should be the
output 10
okay okay so we use all three
functionalities of our
class
object because we Define them so well
right so let's go back to our slides I
think I had some questions so we can
answer them
um let's answer them and then I'll
finish so can and should aliases for
important functions be
used this is let's let's not do this
now
because um we're jumping ahead so we
we'll talk about this kind of syntax
later when it's more appropriate
right
not to be altered by users
directly oh I don't understand wasn't
response to why theid should be private
oh right right right yeah yeah do did I
answer all okay or is there yeah
okay sorry sometimes um it's difficult
to follow the questions and so just ask
again if I didn't answer it right okay
so so I want to conclude because I think
we're running out out of time so now
I'll if you look at your slides I think
it's not very clear at your printouts
that there but it's clear that there are
three cases three cases of writing these
definitions of the functions one was
just the way I just did uh in in my file
so bringing the definitions of functions
outside of the class you like
it or does it feel like this is
weird Okay let me show you the
second the second case is actually doing
the same thing so instead of these two
lines here I brought whatever was in
curly braces and put them right here
after the Declaration so like putting
the Declaration of the functionalities
together with implementation right there
inside the do you like it
better yes yes is more
common the most common is number three
so the number three is
this putl them in three files have your
main function here put the definitions
in what's called sphere
CPP so that's the definitions of member
functionalities and
put your signatures only which is called
an interface to the F in spere
that's what we'll be using all along
that's what everybody
does do you like it like seems like the
worst thing right but it's actually very
important for encapsulation so let me
just give you a hint why and then we'll
start you this later so the thing is
that you can hide your Genius code of
implementation and sell just the
interfaces to the client to
use together with objects that you
pre-compile using your smart code so you
never actually Reveal Your codes but you
can sell your product like that for
people to use and that's called in
capsulation so you really hide your proi
and
stuff uh unfortunately if you use
templates you cannot do that so people
love templates but then you canot hide
stuff so but but if you don't use templ
templates are really useful so they
Implement polymorphism and all of that
but
um but this is a very common thing to do
if you really want to write them your
code here and sell only uh object and uh
interfaces okay next time we'll start
right there so we'll go through this
again oh sorry Pa I have to check on
Zoom I think I just clck the computer no
Zoom is on let's see everything is
on okay you guys all
good okay we'll see
you stop
share and oh it's lab now so you guys
all go to the lab
and yeah can you repeat that stuff you
said about the Q no and so on Boyers
they gonna be now or no they're not
gonna be in the lab but they on our
slack let me see do I slack geez what am
I saying Discord okay let me
see there if you go on Discord y so we
have our staff stuff these guys are
CT don't me yeah that's
wait a second I wonder if I'm
a so go on announcement they should be
here no I mean okay just I guess this is
the
the cute so you can tell them because
they put like
cute and yeah they're right there so go
ahead and ask questions it's really
exciting yeah yeah I'm I can't believe
it's happening
and the attend attendance is not
mandatory not for lectures not for labs
nothing yeah everything can be competed
online if you want that's good have the
lecture at the same
stab that's why we don't have many
students but like here physically but we
want we want you to be able to
completely do it online although we'll
miss nice to have physical lectures too
well thank you for the lecture you you
okay hey I think there might be a
problem with
the I don't think they have the
environments
here they should use their
laptops yeah oh right so they'll have to
go through
setup no we all have to go have to yeah
because you'll they you'll need to log
them in with your Ro password
yeah yep at least I think that is
necessary I think there will be see you
sell anything there that ad
maybe see if I can
likeall yes maybe I can they like ited
for
today I know but hey I think it's going
to be okay because you know the toughest
Will Survive and they can do it on their
laptops and if not like the rest will
take it next year where we are more
prepared because yeah I don't know what
to expect like Steve is like why didn't
you say last week that you want bigger
lectures but last week you only had 100
students and then this is almost fine
right I I mean I I think it's going to
be fine from like how like usually a
small percentage of students actually
attend
way
so you know what what really frustrates
me the most it's 2hour lectures it's
just like impossible to remember that
much material this lectures were one
hour at a time it's so much easier like
one hour you can really remember the
story two hours
oh
[Laughter]
yeah