e
okay so let's
start let's start
um today
is a lecture on um ads and hashing so
adts is abstract data types that um I
will talk about at the level of
abstraction today but El next time we'll
talk about uh implementation of these
data structures in or abstract data
types in C++ uh STL but
today um I will be talking about more
abstractly about these data structures
and specifically about hashing and the
reason why we do this is because uh we
still have homework that is related to
this more uh theoretical uh things like
data structures however this will not be
topics that we cover on the exams so we
give this St this lecture primarily for
you to be able to uh complete your
homework uh specifically lab hash and uh
uh lab hash and what else
is um and dictionary so these
two
okay so today slider.com is
this and uh just please do not forget
that there's going to be a an invited
lecture next week already on Thursday so
exactly in a
week uh by uh V V Line
in okay so let's
start uh last time we talked about lists
and we even talked about the
implementation of lists using linked
memory and I talked about how to
implement such linked memory and you
will go through these exercises in your
lab um uh that lab and MP lists that we
have in this class however I just want
to mention today the
abstract things about about uh lists and
other uh abstract data types that we
will talk about today so uh what does it
mean an abstract data type it's just
when you describe the functionality of
your data so what do you want to do with
your data so what would we want to do
with lists specifically well
examples of list would be grocery lists
or to-do lists right or roster of
student so it's a collection of data
where you know a position so nothing
else really is so special about lists
and um all of the elements are index by
their position so therefore if you were
to implement a list say C+ using C++
language then you would provide an
interface for your list and the only
functionalities that you would provide
would be to the ability to insert and
remove elements in your list in a
specific position maybe you would also
allow to Peak at specific elements of in
in a particular position without
removing so these are the only
functionalities that would be enough to
describe and use this abstract data type
how these are implemented is not a
concern of a client so from the client
point of all we want to do from the
client side is to be able to insert
elements in certain position and remove
elements from certain position and maybe
look what is the element at a particular
position and that's
it the way you the way um you as a
designer or software engineer would
implement this class um is independent
of the user the user should not know or
doesn't even care about how this is
implemented so that's um so as you can
see we are talking about different
levels of abstraction when we talking
about data structures and that is first
the functionality of the data then the
interface so how particularly you're
going to implement and call these
functions and then actually the
implementation so maybe a list will be
implemented using an array or maybe a
linked list that's implementation
details okay so that was list and we did
it last time so now I want to talk about
the next abstract data type that is a
stack okay so what is a
stack here H Pringles is an example of a
stack so what is so special about data
structure or data collection that uh is
similar to Pringles well there's only
two functionalities or two operations
two um principal
operations that you can perform on the
stack that is you can insert an element
in the
stack and then you can remove the top
element from the stack so you cannot
really remove the bottom ele element you
cannot remove a pringle from the middle
without removing first top and first the
the top elements from the stack right so
you can push on top and pop an elephant
the top ele element so you can push an
element on top and pop the top element
and that's it you may want to implement
in your interface maybe a little more
more operations like to Peck at the top
element or ask whether it's an empty
stack or not but these are the two
principal
operations okay so um how if we were to
implement a stack class in
C++ then the interface of this
class would be exactly the functionality
of the stack that uh we would want to
see and of course we we expect to see
push and
Pop um and you can uh also maybe ask
whether you maybe you want to to ask see
what's on top as well the top operation
without changing the stack but push and
pop would change the stack okay and a
couple more maybe like ask for size and
uh whether it's empty or
not okay so here are examp of stats
stats and why do I even talk about stats
because some of the examples are um very
important moreover they are crucial for
programming in general so what are more
examples of stack last time I think I
mentioned that um Pez dispenser is a
stack right you can put the candy on top
and it falls on the bottom here but you
can only pop the the top candy you
cannot really start from the bottom just
like with Pringles
chips I don't know I have a problem
today with this laptop I I hope you
don't see it like blinking
and there's some problem with the screen
that I cannot diagnose some connection
problem anyway so why I wanted to
mention
Stacks uh it's because there's also
Hardware stack and it works on the same
Principle as uh STL stats or data
structure stats that you you heard in
your data structures course or
algorithms course so let's look at the
operation of the main function and what
really happens in Hardware stack or how
is memory going to be arranged on the
stack and there's no surprise that when
we talk about memories um variables on
the stack it is the stack data type
abstract data type that I'm talking
about now so let's see how it works so
imagine that uh we are executing main
function um so in C++ when um the
control goes to a function that
function together with its local
variables and whatever parameters it has
will be pushed on the stack and the
pointer which is which it's a hardware
pointer it's CPU pointer that um
represents what's the top of the stack
is going to be moved to the top of the
that function space so here main is
pushed on the stack together with all of
its local
variables and then main starts executing
so that's when the control goes to main
okay so that's great but when we execute
main we see that the next function that
it calls is called study hard which
means that an entire region associated
with all of the local variables and
parameters whatever par that are sent to
this function will be again pushed on
top of the stack so this is study hard
study hard
function and the control is passed to
this function and the hardware stack top
of the stack pointer is moved to the
corresponding position on top of the
stack therefore again study heart
occupies this portion of the stack and
the pointer is moved and um and study
heart starts uh execution and the first
thing that it does is calls it calls
another function which is MPS and again
MP is with all of its local variables is
pushed on top of the stack and the top
top of the stack pointer is moved and
the execution of MPS starts and plan is
pushed on top of the
stack and the pointer is advanced again
to the corresponding position and all of
the local Vari Ables of the plan that uh
that were allocated in the stack are
there in this region in this bucket that
was just pushed on top of the stack so
what happens once the execution ends so
plan started execution and then it the
the program sees
the right the the the closing curly
braces which means that plan ceases to
exist there is ution should be passed
back to MPS so what happens with the
stack is that this whole region
associated with plan is removed but it's
not really physically removed it's just
that the top of the stack is sent
back two MPS which means that
technically none of these local
variables can ever be reached again
because the top of the stack is not
there anymore and execution as execution
continues some something else can be
pushed on the stack and in this case
it's code right code is going to be put
here on top of the stack because it
starts as execution and the top of the
stack is going to be Advanced and all of
the local variables are going to live
here so what this is this is exactly
what it means that variables go out of
scope that's when they're no longer on
the stack so just like when code ends
its execution the stack
uh pointer will go back to MPS which
means the control is going to be sent uh
given back to the MPS function and all
of the code uh portion of the stack is
not going to be available anymore it
goes out of scope right the control is
passed back to MPS and so on then MPS
Seas to this right the uh pointer goes
back to study heart and all of this
memory is no longer on the stack and it
will be overwritten by whatever is the
next function that's going to be pushed
on top of the stack so this notion of
Stack is very useful to keep in mind
when you think about the order in which
um local variables are on the stack in
order in which they're going to be
deleted in order in which um destructors
are going to be called all of this
matters and all of this re is the result
of Stack
operations just like in abstract data
type stack so push and pop and the order
is determined by that and the order what
we call this order so let me go back um
the order is last in first out right so
whatever was on top of the stat that was
the last element that was in that can be
the first one to be
out last in first out okay so we can
only uh remove the top element which was
the last one to go
in okay so similarly this post fits
notation uh that was implemented in uh
you know calculators long time ago
because the memories was so the memory
was so small so um essentially when you
see that the operation was if you see a
number you push it on the stack if you
see so let's let's put it this way here
if there's another stack for the this uh
postfix notation in a calculator when
you see a number push it when you see
five next number uh push it when you see
an operation pop the last two
numbers and do an operation on them so
that's nine so push the result back
nine then you see a number push it you
see a number push it see an operation
pop the last two numbers or elements
perform the operation minus and push the
result which is
five
five and then what's the next element
that we see multiplication right so you
see an operation you pop the last two
numbers apply operation and push the
result which will be what 45 forever 4
45 and so on and then
continue but um so the stats are very
important they're fundamental data
structures and they're still used in
Hardware um in modern computers and
that's why we talk about stack
variables and
scope okay so now the next fundamental
data structure is uh or abstract data
type is a q so what's the difference
between a q and a stack well this is our
stack right where the principle is last
in first out so Q data abstract data
type is a collection of element where
you can perform slightly different two
principal operations that is n q that
you put an element in the
Q and then you can in q more just a q
okay so then the first element that you
can d DQ was the first one that came in
so the principle is slightly different
it's first in first out just like Q's
any Q in a grocery store or postal
office right so the first in first out
in uh contrast to last in first out for
Stacks so how could I make Pringles into
a
q anybody want to say I want to have a
box of Pringles and I want to make it a
q instead of a stack
how would that look
like I cut the bottom right I just cut
the bottom of here and then I can remove
um my Pringle tips from both sides from
front and from back so it's not really
this cute that I just described but it's
more like a double end Q double end
q and that's exactly what Elmer will be
talking about uh on Tuesday because
that's one of the STL Q's
implementations where you can you can
grab objects not only from the first in
first out but also from the back you can
grab elements from both sides just like
Pringles with the bottom cut
out you Cann grab them from the middle
right you cannot take a middle chip
without rearranging everything or
removing half of the quebe but you can
grab the first one or the last one in
the que okay so this will be STD STD
double Q
okay again we're not talking about
implementation at this point so I'm
talking about different level of
abstraction I'm talking about the
interfaces how to use them but I'm not
talking about how one would implement it
so if I were to write an interface to a
queue I would have all of the the two
principal operations in Q and DQ but
maybe I could also ask if it's an empty
Q or not not or peek at the front of the
que or if it was double-ended Q I could
maybe peek at the at the end as
well okay so that's
good so the last abstract data type that
I want to talk about today is called a
dictionary so what is a
dictionary in in uh real life something
similar to dictionaries would be phone
books or a dictionary dictionary where
you look up the meaning of a word so
essentially a dictionary is a collection
of keys and values where keys are not
necessarily numbers anymore so just like
with the phone book you look up a name
and for that name you'll see the phone
number and there may be multiple same
names and they'll have different phone
number so that is possible or um or it
can be an address book right so you also
look maybe you look at the at the um
well add dress book is not really a good
example a Rost of students you you have
um the ID numbers and you look up their
name or photo so key
value uh Pairs and collection of them so
what is um interesting about the
terminology is again different levels of
abstractions May mean the same thing so
you may say oh it's dictionary when you
talking about abstract data type but
then how are they implemented it's an
ordered Maps or maps at in a standard
templated Library uh in
C++ or if you look under the hood they
implemented using what's called hash
tables that we'll look at today or even
more um precisely those are associative
arrays right so arrays that do not have
integer indices but have um um any kind
of type index whether it's strain or
whatever you want it to be so that's um
terminology here right and this is the
definition so let's think about the
operations that can be allowed in this
um if you were to write an interface
what would be the operations that you
allowed so here's an interface of a
dictionary and C++ so you might want to
insert a key a new key value so uh again
maybe there's a new person in town with
the phone number right you want to
insert uh the key value the the person's
name and their phone number into the
book you might want to remove a specific
um
key together with the value of course
all of that will be removed you may just
want to look at that key value pair
without removing and again um just check
if it's an empty uh dictionary or not so
something else that is fundamental
is uh in C++ is that you can override
operator square
brackets so you can access those
elements or values by the
keys by saying square
bracket and put an apple there because
that's your key and know Apple will give
you the value of the Apple which is
maybe red shiny or whatever juicy or
whatever are they or a picture of an
apple so this is a very abstract way of
then using square brackets which is a
really neat thing so let's see how it's
done I'll give you some examples so
suppose we have the following data and I
really hope that the screen doesn't do
what what I see here so let's let's hope
that the recording is nice but anyway so
um assume that you have the following
pairs lock a number and a name so you
have a school and say it has five story
school and the lockers are numbered by
the first um number is the the floor and
then the rest is um is the number of the
locker and um say uh and then you you
get the name of the student
right so what if I want to retrieve a
name given a Locker number
well then I can say whatever my table
is and put
103 and you get the name of that student
that has that Locker or owns that Locker
right so that's not a big deal because
then you might think I don't know what
why it's happening do you see guys this
blurring of the W of this
screen it's kind of annoying
but
anyway so
um the way to implement it is doesn't
seem like a big deal like why are we
even talking about this associative
arrays or hashing if we have this Locker
number keys and
name uh values it's not a big deal just
to store it all in Array and put um
number this array from zero to whatever
um whatever is the last floor I said
five floors so maybe
599 right and just put all of the
corresponding names like J had away here
uh into the corresponding indices of
elements of the array not a big deal
right then you can just ask for that
corresponding uh element of the array
using square brackets not a big deal
right
but however for this particular example
this is only possible because we have
really specific nice keys that is they
are integers they are positive integers
and moreover they're small positive
integers right so we don't it's not a
100 story floor or um or more right not
100 story
building um so this is something very
specific what if my key values are um
are more complex like a course number
right so what is the course number that
we have I I really don't know I'm going
to just put something like this what is
the course number like this and you want
to look up by course number a schedule
info for or information about the course
or say you have a flight number right
something like American Airlines
7705 right and you look at the arrival
information so so maybe the keys are not
as necessarily nice as in this first
example or you have a URL that's a
string string and you want to look up
the the page so I'll give you more
examples of possible indices and how to
deal then with the rang in this data in
memory so now we'll talk a little bit
about implementation and we talk about
implementation here uh because your
homework has it we are kind of
overlapping this material a little bit
with data structure scor where they
would be talking about hashing is an
implementation um however we do that
because we still have those assignments
okay so what is general vacabulary
though so these are the principal
operations you want to insert a key and
data in the vocabulary if you got new
key data pair you want to remove the
pair by um using the key for searching
or you want to just look at the uh key
value pair using find operation and this
very important part of implementation of
dictionary is to have the square
brackets for you that would look up the
key and give you the value so now in
this example I have my dictionary that
is it stores
names as keys so those are the indices
and the data is the the age of the
person so say if I have col here and I
have 19 that's that my arrangement of
the data and this is what's called an
associative array when indices are no
longer nice small integers they are
anything right in this case strings but
any other
type okay so do you have any
questions if not let's talk very general
now so what is the problem then of
hashing so if we were to implement this
um associative arrays what does it even
mean what does it mean to have indices
that are not integers anymore how do we
do that so you could pose this problem
um mathematically or from theoretical
point of view and you would say well
what is my key space maybe it's a set of
strains maybe it's a set of specific
strains like with the URL starting with
something or with um say flight numbers
or names um
maybe just general strings maybe it's a
dice toss again dice roll so uh but you
can say it's some kind of space K and
then the goal is then to use a function
to map this key space so have have some
hash function we call it h to map this
key space k onto a small set of integers
because ultimately we do want to store
all this data in some kind of small
array so we don't really want to have
these weird indices we want to map them
to some small set of integers so that we
can use array so it's kind of like
hashing is kind of like hashing into an
array hashing all these weird Keys uh
set into an array somehow so that really
we Underneath It All We Have just an
array and um um this is a very fuzzy way
of putting this goal kind of because
nothing is really clear especially let's
let's say what does it mean a small
subset of or small set of integers that
are positive what does it even mean
right 100 a thousand what is small so
that's not really clear a memory is
pretty large now so maybe it's a million
right and what is this space of keys
like is that well defined we don't even
know it could be strings as I said it
could be anything right it's not always
very defined so finding this hash table
because uh hash uh function because of
this very fuzzy description of the
problem is a big challenge that's like a
huge research area and it's a it's it
can be a lot of fun and it's a very
important problem too because here we
are talking really about some lossless
compression of some sort right we really
want to have this really nice bestion
function that will give us a nice
distribution of all keys in the integer
space and that's really difficult to do
um
okay so let's just let's draw a little
picture of what does it all mean so a
basic idea of
hashing is that when you have your
key value
pair you want to treat that key as an
integer so when you get the key again
think of it as an name or whatever or a
URL or a flight information number of a
course number you want to Hash it into
an integer so you want to apply H to K
and have an i at the way like some small
nice integer on the way out so then you
can put find that I and put the value oh
find that I and put the value into that
position of the
array and then you can say okay my table
hash T which is a hash table essentially
my table I equals
value but it's better to say what is I I
is really literally is H of K so I'm
going to write it over it's h of K so I
hashed my key into an integer right
there so table h of k equals to value
and this is exactly how the overridden
square brackets is going to be instead
of saying table I because we don't know
I yet you do table h of K like look
that's that's the override that's how
the implementation of the overwritten
square brackets would look
like
okay so we have this goal so let's
see what kind of hash functions would be
good and which ones would not be good
and this is a little relevant to again
to your homework where you have to think
about actually hashing some um some keys
in some good way or bad way so I have
imagine that I have this set which is my
data and it is key value pairs where the
key is the name of a child and the value
is the Hallow
costume so name and we'll be wearing
black cat as as her C costume for
Halloween so that's my
data I want to have a hash function that
will take
n and we'll put her in some array uh um
in this right finds an array in this to
put ands information into the array and
say my array is little so it only has
eight elements so I have that constraint
of the size of the array so what would
be a perfect hash function here can you
see some kind of way of hashing these
names so that they evenly distributed in
my
array nicely
distributed oh yeah thank you for your
comment that your screen looks nice mine
is like doing some weird things I
sometimes don't see it I have to write
on it without seeing it so it's really
strange but anyway so what would be a
good hash function for this numbers well
if I look at these numbers do you see
something really special about
them H they all start with different
first letter and moreover they
alphabetic look A B C D E F G H H which
means that if I just look so if my hash
function will
take say
name just first element of the name
which is first character of the
name that would be a c d f g for all of
the names and maybe I divided mod
8 right which means that a oh so what it
does it takes the S key
value of your first character of a and
divides it by eight I have a table of s
key values I think a is 49 ID by8 but I
also have the implementation so we can
look at the
implementation
there you go see I have my oh yeah let's
just call it
name um
name here this is better so look I take
name and it say it's N I take the first
character it's cast to the S key value
divides by 8 mod 8 the answer is one
right so if it was
Ben
then then the the result would be two
and then whatever the names if the name
starts with C the the hash value would
be
three which means that all of these guys
so n will go here
and N will be hash to in this one so the
I will be one and the black cat
black cat costume will be put in here
and Ben with the Harry Potter costume
will be put in tat two and cor Cory spy
will be put into three and so on and the
last Harmony will be put into zero
because it will be wrapped around the
array so the B costume will go in
here okay so this is a fabulous or
perfect hash function
because it even evenly distributes the
keys across the
array also it's one to one it's a bje
right it's a bje so there will be no two
names that will map to the same uh
element in the array and there will be
no holes in the array either we'll
populate all of the array
uniformly that's that's the definition
of a perfect function hash function it's
really really hard to find find S such
perfect Hash Hash functions for General
data sets Okay so we lucky now I'm going
to show you other hash functions where
you know it's not so nice anymore so
let's look at the roll of five dice and
I have the applet here so I can run it
let's
look so here is a perfect here's a roll
and we can roll again and we'll get
different values and I will tell you
what's the hash value of each roll is so
the the this first
one
h
of 2
5 three and
four
um the value of this is um let's
see four six six the hash of this um
roll dice roll will be six so let's roll
again oh come
on oh it will it will erase my writing
okay I guess
guess so for this roll dice I'll have 10
as a hash
value for this dice roll I'll have a
zero
value for this one I'll have I have to
do the calculation in my head 10 again
so let me explain what I mean if I have
a
roll come on let's go
back if I have a
roll what I look at is how many padal I
have around the rows what does do it
mean I look only at
the at the dice that has a dot inside so
in this case I only have this three one
and one and I add up only dots that are
around the center so in this case for
this dice roll AG of it would be
two so I put it in here I put this three
one
six and two right here okay so then I
roll again I calculate so the the way
this function works is petals you
calculate number of petals
around
rows okay so if there is a a dot inside
I calculate how many petals are around
so for six there is zero for two there
is zero because there's no no dot inside
right okay so is this a good hash
function and the answer is not so much
because first of all we'll never get odd
hash values so we'll never calculate a
one so never the result of this hash
function will be one or three or five or
7 or 9 11 13 so all of
this indices in the array will never be
values of this has hash function there
will be never values in those positions
in the array which means that the
resulting array will be
sparse most of the rolls will fall under
the I mean all of the all of the rolls
will fall onto the even
indices so we'll only populate half of
the array so what's the point right
maybe we could improve this hash
function but we're talking about this
particular hash function and how it is a
bad
choice okay so um there are many other
reasons why this hash function is bad
and I have them on the next slide let's
see okay so first of all number one
reason is that we only have effectively
11 indices that will be ever be occupied
with different configurations of roll of
five dice of R their roles but the not
the the domain or the key space is huge
because the all of the different numbers
in which we could have or the result of
this five dice rolls would be six to
the^ five right so all possible six
values five times to to the power five
so this is a huge domain with respect to
the very little range of the function
which means that this function will
never be a one to one or onto it's it's
not a bje and it's not onto because
there's wasted space right we don't map
onto the uh odd indices moreover it's
not even uniformly distributed because
for example for the last roll where you
get um let's put it this way so the role
when you have all five
FES which index which Val which hash
value would it be for this
configuration again we compute the
paddles around the rows there four in
each dice so 4 * 5 is 20 so you have to
put it in the last 20th element of this
array there cannot be
more uh elements in the array 21 will
never be a result of this hash function
20 is the maximum and the only
configuration that matches it is this
particular configuration so there will
be only one element right here while
imagine how many different
configurations of five roll dice uh
there will be for zero right so I don't
know 22 2 2 two 4 4 4 4 four and all of
the combinations of the even dice rolls
for all five of them will all be right
here so huge number number of different
rols of five dice will be uh will be all
crowding the zero space of the array and
what does it even mean like we map many
different Keys value pairs to one
element of our hash table what does it
even mean how do we resolve this
Collision so this is what's called a
collision and um if you want to use this
hash function you'll have to have a way
of resolving these collisions right how
do we put all those elements in there
and how we look them up
later so that's a problem which I'll
talk about in a bit and that's what
linear CH uh linear um probing and
separate chaining Collision detections
me Collision detection Collision
resolution strategies will be sorry
okay so let's sum up what is hashing and
what is a hash T table so hash table is
just an array
right just an array which has a hash
function defined so that this hash
function will take the
key and give us the index in the array
right but we have to have a collision
resolution strategy because if our key
space k is kind of the same as the size
of the array so if the key space is the
same in size as the size of the array so
if the number of key value pairs is kind
of equal or similar to the size of the
array that it's not so hard to find a
perfect hash function that will just
evenly distribute all of the key value
chair uh value pairs into this array
that's not such a big problem the
problem arises when we have the key
space much much l larger than the size
of the array that's when the real
problem Rises and that's where there's a
lot of research put into understanding
how to do best um hash functions for
these kind of situations that always
work kind of uniform uh perfect hash
functions um so let's look at this case
when the key size when the number of
these key value pairs are much much
bigger than the available aable space
for the array what do we do well we hope
then that for
any selection or collection of
n key value pairs that this hash
function will be so nice that it will
put all of these key value pairs
uniformly into the array so that's kind
of the hope that whenever I select
n key value pairs so say this is another
selection of n key value pairs they're
all red then the hash function will be
nice and distribute them all nicely so
let me show just one more so say I
select another end sized subset of my
keys uh and all of these key value pairs
then again will be uniformly distributed
in my
array however you cannot prevent this
following situation happen
that I will select the subset of my key
value pairs that all of size n that all
fall into the same index with this hash
function so I'll pick that red one and
red that black uh key value pair and
that green key value pair that all as a
set will map to one Index right it's
it's still possible that you'll be so
unlucky and that's why picking such nice
hash uh functions for General sets of
key values is really difficult okay so
that's the theoretical Foundation of why
this problem is so difficult and and why
is it important at the same time to
solve this so let's look at uh a couple
more motivating
examples so say I have 40 character
strings here they
are first strain second strin so on I
want to Hash them right I want to have a
way of storing them in an
array and I need to find a hash function
that will map each of the 40 character
string to an
integer so I'm going to do the Fallen
hash or hack or whatever I'm going to
select
eight characters or eight character
positions at random somehow I don't know
like maybe like
this and from each strain 40 character
strain I will create then an eight
character
strain based on this position so say the
it's second position and whatever eighth
position so it's o
r
h
comma
space
space is that eight that's not eight I
need one more let's do one more say this
one so I have a uh G okay so that's my
eight character
string compression from a 40 character
string
now the second string will go to what
little O say G I'm not really precise
here so say uh
d
c r
space l right and so on so the idea is
that if I hatch 40 character strings
into the eight character
strings then is it eight maybe it's
still seven oh it's still seven okay
let's do one more sorry so that we
really good at the look that we really
precise so
here
what is
um here e insert e and here is s
before here C before R another C here
okay this is better right okay so we
really really select the
proper characters from those eight
positions that we randomly pet for this
40 character strengths so we compress
the 40 character into eight characters
like that and it seems like a nice thing
to do because look if we know how to
Hash eight character strings which I'll
show you later that's actually not a big
deal so if we have small strings like of
eight characters you just add the ask
key values and do mod whatever the size
of the array that you want to do and
that's a really
nice uh well
distributed uh hash function for this
kind of strings it's a really really
nice hash function so let's assume that
we know how to Hash small strings
hashing large strings in the same way
would be really difficult
because um we would we would run into
all sorts of problems with them um which
I'll show you again later so we really
want to have then a nice way of hashing
largest strings uh but we'll use the
hash of small strings for that okay so
this seems like a nice thing to
do so let's see if we can if this then
applies if this nice hash function can
work for any set of 40 character strings
and the answer is not so much what if my
40 character strings
are
just a bunch of URLs
right and if I select eight positions at
random let's say this one and this one
and it's Wikipedia Pages sorry
specifically wikip Wikipedia pages and
this one and this one and say this one
and how many do I need to have this one
and this one
H is my distribution as nice as in the
with the first set of keys because this
is the same function just different set
of keys right okay so where does this
stram map to T
slash I do slash
slash
ENT and uh
B okay but is that m% I'm blanking is
that the did I say it right whatever
that character is okay now the second
strain MTH to T slash I the same thing
dot SL SL W
slash what about do you see the problem
here right the second the second
character in all of the strings is the
same this character in all of the
strings is the same this character is
the same this character is the same this
character is the same this only the last
two will be different so we will really
differentiate all of the Wikipedia URLs
based on these two characters and it's
just very few numbers very few keys that
we will have for thousands of pages
right so that's not really good there
will be much smaller uh key space uh
hash table range space than the key
space which is the problem we know that
so that's that's not
good um okay do you have any questions
so now let's look into how then to
resolve these issues of um the problem
when the same strains will most likely
end up in the
same IND this of of the hash
table just like in the case of Wikipedia
Pages or earlier we had another example
where there will be just two the the uh
key SPAC is two too large for the size
of the array and too many um key value
pairs will crowd the same indices so I
decided that I will not be showing you
examples because I found this really
amazing page where all of this is
described in great way with the
animation so here I can narrate this
animation but of course you can read it
so what we're talking about is
hashing hashing Str strings in Array
right so we need to find a hash function
so say strings are names here's Randy we
want to put him in the array the array
is small in this case let's say just
seven elements so you could just instead
of Designing any hash function you could
just go one by one and
ask but if the r as the arays get larger
and larger it just so long to do that
right asking every single index oh are
you storing Randy no M okay let's go
next right so this can take a lot of
time each single time you want to insert
an ele element into the hash into the
array so therefore hash tables are used
instead so instead of regular array use
a hash table or this associative array
where for a r or for a key or a name
here you find the index using this hash
function so you give Randy into the hash
function and it spits out the
index okay so if index is say 82 you
just then put Randy in there no problem
right okay so we already covered it but
this is kind of the animation way of
explaining the same thing so that's
great how could we make a hash function
like that for names well one of the Imp
implementation is exactly for short
strains you could add up the ask key
values and divide mod the size of the
array then that strain that that set of
um indices produced by this hash
function will be uniformly distributed
if the original keys are uniformly
distributed so you'll get a nice hash
function for your 100 size
array and that's that's the explanation
how a 2 was obtained for randing you
just add the SQL uh
numbers so that's great for short
strains this will work perfectly so say
for eight size strains the the size of
the strain set and the size of the array
will be roughly matched and it will be
great uh so here they show so the
animation shows how you can put more
strings into this array and how the same
same thing is computer the same hash
function will find the place for um the
element to either be inserted or removed
or just found simply peaked at right so
here for St what do we do for St we
compute the hash value we found it we
report that we found it that's one of
the principal operations to look at the
array Eric we insert it and what else I
guess that's all it says searching for
for stand inserting Eric okay cool but
inevitably there may be situation where
the same
name or the same key will result result
in the same index so Eric uh here has
hash value
four just like what was it uh Randy
Randy and Eric all mapped to four so
they belong to the same place in the
array what do we
do
and that's the lab hash problem so there
are two principal way of doing it open
addressing or closed addressing so open
addressing is also what we call linear
probing here it's explained uh I think
let me show you on my slides that oh I
start with separate chain but the next
slide shows a linear probing or open
hash that's what that animation will be
about so open hash what we do instead of
inserting the key in that place that was
already occupied by something we just
increase the hash by one so let's see
where is the animation so you say oh
Randy is already there so we cannot put
Eric in there well we'll just increment
by one and insert Eric in the next
position and then will flag that place
in the array as hey it's occupied now
you can't really put it in there
like just just remember that you have to
probe next when you're next time okay so
that's uh how open addressing or linear
probing
works now another way of resolving
collisions would be just instead of
keeping one value keep a link list on
values of values associated with that
index or with that hash value so then
Randy Eric or whatever whoever else maps
to for would all live in that link list
of course then you have to manage link
lists and maybe it's also an array under
the hood but maybe it's um if it's a
link list then you have to deal with
those pointers like we talked about last
time so here we go if Randy and Eric are
there then I think he'll show you how
to insert in searching yeah let's see so
if Randy goes into
four and then Eric goes into four then
you have
to you know open up the link list
and and um rearrange the pointers like
here to to maintain the link list
maintain link list can be tricky because
you have to deal with pointers however
once we go through SD or S
um the standard templated Library
implementation and I'll show you later
in this today how you don't really have
to worry about this once you use the
standard templat Library lists for link
list
implementation
okay so that's it that's that's the key
uh you can do analysis but we will not
do this in this class because we're not
really talking about data structures
uh but these are the
two uh different ways of dealing with
collisions so either separate chaining
that is instead of inert if if a bucket
is occupied just move on to the next one
and put it
there that's for uh linear probing right
and for separate chaining you just
attach a link list of all of the key
element pairs that
uh that map to the same IND
this okay so now let me show you an
implementation
of hashing and hash hashing function but
also a hash table for eight character
strings so that's what I promised you a
little
earlier and let's go through the
implementation so what exactly we are
doing
here
so I'm going to declare a hash table and
it will have 100 elements so Underneath
It All I know that there will be an
array of 100 elements for each key right
so now I'm going to
insert an apple that's the key with the
value a
fruit The Strain C++ is the key with the
value a programming language and hash is
a is a um is a key and the value is a
data structure okay so that's from the
client point of view what I can do I can
declare a table and then I can start
populating and then I can look at each
of the um by the key I can look up the
value right so for the key Apple I hope
to look up the value which you can see
that I'm doing it right there right so I
printed out the key and the hash table
value using this overwritten square
bracket operation because for apple
square brackets I should get the value
in that array with this key right so
apple is printed out to be a fruit C++
is printed out a programming language
and hash is printed out a data structure
this is all great but how is this hash
table implemented so here's my class
hash simple hash table privately it has
this key value pairs it also has this
table so it's a private uh member so you
can really access it uh directly but
what you can access directly is only
public principal operations and that is
operator square
brackets and um and just um I can
structure in this case so I don't really
have any other public um operations here
I I did not Implement insert and
delete because it was just for uh just a
simple implementation that I wanted to
show but operator square brackets is
overr so I can always Peak or look up
the element for with the key so how do I
even how can I look up this element with
the key well the operator square
brackets really is Hash calculation
right so it will look up the table with
that hash
value which is Hash value of the key and
um and it's doing something interesting
there as well so what is it doing is
that it's the way my table is really
stored and implemented which is a p
which is done privately but we can look
and see how it's done so table is a
vector which means that it's an
array but each element is is a q which
means that I'm talking about closed
hashing right so it's a it's a chaining
of the key value pairs for each
index but um I'm not really concerned
about it because lists already Implement
all of those insert and delete
operations if I need that so this is
very clever way to do it using C++
standard Library Center templated
Library okay and um so so what else oh
the hash table the hash function the
hash function itself is what we talked
about uh for eight character strings you
you just add up
their each of their character as key
values and then you divide it mod the
table size so mod 100 and then those 80
character strings will be nicely
distributed across that table you can
it's gu to do that so there you go uh
that's the
implementation you can look up at it you
can look it up and uh and see and play
with it and I think I'm done for today
so we are a little
earlier but again this is just think of
it as a bonus lecture because I will not
be asking this material on the exam um
but it's helpful for your
homework okay any questions
so now next week we still have really
cool material uh Elmer will be talking
about the standard library and um V will
be talking about smart
pointers and um principles of
programming in modern C++ so that's very
very crucial he lecture is something
that we'll need to start with in the
next installation of this class so we
are all looking forward to seeing it and
I hope you all will be there so I'll see
you next
Tuesday