e
okay it's quarter past 10 so let's
start uh so I'm going to be holding this
lecture today and I'll talk
about um I'll talk about a standard
Library some data containers and other
things included in it and also
iterators
um and once again uh so this invited
lecture is now this Thursday
so very very soon so may make sure to be
there it's going to
actually kind of bring these topics
together in a way or or I kind of forget
you up to date with modern
C++ B is very uh very experienced in
this
field um
okay I think yeah okay yeah just
checking that there should be audio on
Zoom as well let me know if there's any
problems um okay but let's get to the
topic so talking about data container so
so this is like kind of the the basic
one you you would start with just an
array and uh you
have just in sequence this boxes with
like some kind of data in them like
you can have an array of numbers or you
can have an array of like any kind of
objects you you want and the way it's
stored in the memory is um like that
they're just in sequence so you
basically have a pointer to the first
element and then you know the size of
one object if it's an in then it's
probably four
bytes so then you know that ele
7 is at offset uh 1 C and that's
basically how you can access the
data uh now if we compare that to a
dynamic array so for example STD
Vector uh the idea is the same but the
way vectors
work uh is that they dynamically
reallocate
memory as they grow larger and when that
happens what it has to do is uh copy the
data from the previous array to the next
one it it can't just like
continue
uh like past the current array just like
grow it directly it needs to create a
completely new array and usually the
implementation is like this where it
like doubles the size from the previous
time uh well well I don't know maybe I
shouldn't say usually but but this is
like at least a common way to uh
present the idea there could be more
optimal
ways uh and and when you when you do
this like like I said it creates new
array so another thing that leads
to uh is
that the
um memory locations of these individual
elements change so if you had like a
pointer
to uh see there when it was like a size
of
four
uh you had a pointer to it like stor it
somewhere
else and then you add some more elements
into the array you try to access the
pointer then you'll find that you
can't you might end up finding the C
there but if you do then that would just
be the old data and it's like actually
garbage data that was just left
there
um Al the the term for this
um that that the memory is like have in
in sequence NE next to each other uh in
this consistent way
uh is is called
cones uh and that term will also be
relevant uh
later okay so Anna already talked about
uh lists a little bit I'll just quickly
go over the basic idea so basically you
have the
head uh where there's some kind of data
and then it points to another node which
points to another and uh so on
and then at the end uh you often store
the address for the
tail
and uh you might be able to Traverse
this like forward and back depending on
how it's defined
um so then in this case the memory
locations always remain the same even
when you keep adding new elements so I I
kind of put this uh box all around the
screen just to show that like they kind
of like it can be anywhere and they're
just like you just have these pointers
telling you where the next element
is uh so so how to iterate uh so Anna
probably showed uh that yeah you can
access the next pointer and and then
just kind of go from there uh but we'll
kind of talk about a more robust
uh method for the
iteration
um so yeah this is the still like
basic
uh way to do this but then
uh what it looks like with iterators is
like this so so you
create uh an iterator for this
list and and
and you initialize it with the beginning
of the
list and then you use the
Plus+ operator uh the the the
increment operator uh to kind of move it
forward and and then you can dreference
it to get access to the
um oh I think that's actually U
oh wait minute is that
right so we D reference the iterator
then we get access to this rgba pixel
pointer that we then have to like yeah
yeah okay I think this is this is right
um yeah anyway
so so so so then what what's happening
there we're just like incrementing this
iterator what what does that
mean
um okay well yeah I'll talk about that
in the next slide for first I I'll just
uh mention the auto
keyword uh so you can see here this like
declaration is really long this sdd list
RGB pixel po
iterator so then uh one way to make it
much uh
shorter is
um just to use the auto keyword yeah you
might have seen some discussion about it
uh on
Discord uh basically iterators is one
good use case uh for it so just
basically let the
compiler uh did use what what the type
is so especially like if it's kind of
obvious what it is then uh it's it's
like safe to use this Auto keyword but
you shouldn't really get in the habit of
like uh using it for every type you
declare because then it gets really
confusing and like there might be cases
where uh the compiler would maybe pick a
type that's a little bit different from
what you actually intended
um okay okay so
now uh now let's talk about like what
what the like operator means in the case
federator so basically how it works is
that it's some kind of operator overload
that you're
using and like in the case of list it
could be like that where
it's looking for the
um next item in the in the
list um so so basically the the way that
an already showed how you can uh go
through these
lists but then for the case of array it
could just be like that where it just
has some kind of index and it's just
incrementing that index and then uh
that's all you need to access the
elements you want
uh so the point is that that the data
container can Define the way to iterate
it and create this like clean interface
uh for the user of of that
class uh so so then the user doesn't
need to think okay well what this is a
list so I need to Traverse it like this
or or this is some other kind of
container especially if we consider all
the like different types of containers
that exist
some might make you think like okay I'm
not really sure like what what the like
way to uh iterate this would even
be um so then iterators are this kind of
General uh
concept that the developer of of the
class uh can Define it so then it's easy
to uh iterate through the
container and also
uh also it's just like a kind
of a
general way that can be applied to all
the different kinds of um containers you
can especially see like with with the
standard
library that uh it's very consistent in
the way that you can use uh these
iterators to to access the data
containers
there um
okay so if if
you like let's say you write some kind
of data container and you also write an
iterator for it then it is indeed your
uh job to write the operator overloads
and like technically you could make
these operator overloads do anything uh
anything you want but of course there's
a kind of a standard way that people
expect it um to
work and one thing I want to mention
here is
um post versus pre increment so uh when
you see that it Plus+ there that's
called a post increment
um so maybe maybe you're not sure what
what pre-increment then means well what
that's that means the case where the
plus plus is before uh the it now I have
a little bit of uh
code here to
show Le I think I do
I I get R of that
code um well okay let's just um let's
just kind of WR
it
um WR it
now so let's say
we have this template function that
takes any any kind of container now this
isn't really like a perfect way to uh
Implement things but uh we just going to
let it slide now
um oh didn't try the
name okay so let's just um
do exactly we have
here I'm struggling to type like this
when the screen I'm looking at this over
there
um okay so if we try to
if we do this so so now the the idea is
that we
are uh
iterating
uh at the same time as we're also
accessing uh the data behind the
iterator so then we don't need to have
it on a separate line it's kind of a
small optimization but it's also
something you see uh See pretty often
uh so let's see what
the result looks
like oh clearly I'm we're getting
something here
and this is always what happens if
uh oh it's supposed to be
while whenever you do live coding I
thought I had like all this
code
already written
but
um so this is list Tesla let's get rid
of all the other things for now so it's
clear what's happening
oh I didn't
say
um okay okay
uh wait did I did I do everything
correctly
now just 255 shouldn't there be more in
the
like I this is this is what happens when
the when the code is not not prepared
okay now I'm getting confused well let
me try anyway with the
increment okay
well oh oh it's not list test it's
uh H wait
no yeah it's it's the print function oh
oh that's why it's not looking correct
okay
uh okay there we go so so the list is
supposed
to have this
uh r red then green and then blue and
blue
uh uh and that those have these kinds of
values so then we're always printing the
green value from here uh which only in
the case of G it's
255 so now as the second print we got we
got
255 and then the last one is some kind
of zero none of these have zero so so
this is basically what happens if you
use the pre-increment that it increments
it and then it Returns the
uh Returns the elements that it points
to after the
incrementation and then we if we use to
uh post
increment then it's actually working as
we wanted to so now
it's actually going to give us this as
it is before the increment and after
that it's going to increment it so so
the next time we access it it's going to
be
okay and also when it accesses the last
element then it's going to increment
after that and then here is going to see
like okay we're at the end now so that
way this ends up working just
fine uh so important difference there
between
uh post and and
pre-increment um okay and then something
interesting about them is if you want to
Define these
overloads uh this is actually how you
make the distinction so it's the same
operator but for the post fix you put
this dummy int uh
identifier uh in the kind of arguments
section
and that's how the compiler sees that
okay okay this is supposed to be postfix
it's kind of a like hacky way uh that
that it works
but
uh you know it's it's important to know
if you need to implement these or if
you're looking at code and it'll make it
easier to understand and and
generally uh how you expect the post fix
to work is that it creates some kind of
um
temporary variable
here um and then
it creates or returns an iterator to
this temporary
node uh that was created before
incrementing
okay um so now little bit like recap in
a way of STD vector and STD list I mean
we didn't specifically kind of talk
about the standard library right there
but uh but but we'll talk about it now
and um SD Vector is something that's
very
commonly uh used mainly because it's um
it allows you to access items very
quickly uh and usually that's what you
want and then the benefit of the list
for example is that you can insert and
to move quickly and and it retains all
the memory
locations uh so then maybe you have some
kind of scenario where
uh you really need to like insert
elements all over the place and remove
them and you do much more like
insertions than uh accessing the
elements like you could see
uh here is that like like basically the
way
to you can also see it here so the way
to like access the elements in a list is
that
basically you just have to iterate
through the entire list until you find
the one you need so you you can't like
somehow say like okay I want to access
the fifth element in this list now now
of course you can do that by having like
a loop that uh increments the iterator
five
times
um but but then of course you can see
how that's much less uh efficient
than than uh with vectors where you can
simply just
um access it by by index and and with
vectors uh you also have access to this
at
method and the difference
there is that that that has bounds
checking so if you try to
um so if you try to access
something outside of the bounds of the
vector then it's not going
to segment fault or something that you
would
expect to regular ARR I don't actually
remember exactly what happened so it's
actually a good way to uh
show I'm sorry show a little bit of CPP
reference so if you ever need to to kind
of uh get a better understanding of how
these different things in the standard
Library work uh then CPP reference is is
one good site uh to go
to uh so you get like a basic
description here so it says the elements
are stored continuously so uh you can
access by index and not only iterators
uh and then you can see that is talking
about the automatic memory
allocation and
then for for data containers you can
usually expect it to um tell you the
complexity of of different uh
operations okay but I wanted to look at
um the ATS method so so let's see what
this
does um
if PA is not within the range an
exception of type SD out of range is
thrown now we haven't really talked
about exceptions and that's kind of
another uh topic entirely and we're not
going to get into that but
um yeah if if if you're if you're not
making use of the exceptions then it is
actually faster to uh just use uh this
operator because the the balance
checking does cost some
time um
okay let's move
forward uh but the iterators can indeed
be also used
for vectors but but that'll also be uh
of course um
slower than if you can just access
directly with um with like an
index okay then another
thing uh another data
container uh STD map so if you know
dictionaries from other
languages uh then this probably looks
very very
similar so you can kind of Define this
key and a value and in this case I I
make it that this key is a string and
the value is
in uh and
then you can kind of just
uh insert values with different keys and
it'll kind of automatically create those
elements into the
map and then for for a map you can also
just uh iterate through
it uh if you need to
uh but then there's also unordered
map
and
the pretty much everything works the
same I like on the surface but then the
difference is that in unordered map that
well as the name says they're they're
not in order but what that implies is
that it's actually faster to access
things
uh through the uh
key the implementations are quite
different
um but then yeah you can't expect them
to be in any kind of uh order in the
map okay and again you can use the CPP
reference uh for example to like find
all these details about the
differences um okay so then I have a
question
if if you don't have a key in the
map then what happens but once again I I
should have code for this yeah so okay
now I have the exact code that's that's
PRM here that's good
um okay and I should have a
slido uh question for this as
well U so this the first time I I showed
the slide at all so I'm going to wait
for a while for everybody to
um join so what's the output of C out uh
oh it says my map door but I if ramed it
to inventory but regardless if you if
you try to
access some kind of key in this
map in this map of ins that doesn't
exist what is the
output yeah I I'll wait a little bit
more somebody saying Kina found
exception 100ch of people voting for
zero a segment fault or random garbage
going to get any votes
okay maybe no one else is voting
now okay there we have our answer so we
get the output of
zero and we can kind of find
the uh reason for this from here maybe
some people online uh
looked looked at this and found the
answer so what we can hear what what we
can see here is that uh when
it
um let's see returns of
reference or or performs insertion if
the key doesn't exist if you use this
operator uh at all even if if you're not
trying to like insert some kind of value
to it
in any case it's going to be some kind
of um
insertion and then uh
specifically uh it's going to
be uh value initialized and and for
um for something like in that's going to
mean being zero initialized so it is
actually consistently going to be
initialized as zero
um okay so so that can lead to some kind
of problems if you if you like keep
trying to access these things and then
it just keeps adding more elements that
you didn't necessarily want uh to be
there I mean maybe you did
um maybe you did want them to be there
but if if you didn't then you do have
access to this find function which
actually returns an
iterator
uh and then the iterator is either going
to point at the uh element that it
found or it's going to just point at the
kind of blank space at the
end and then you can check like okay if
it's if it's pointing at something
that's not the end
uh then we
should have our answer here oh actually
this is kind
of this is kind of
naturally
um okay I think I think at least of the
top of myit should be
like should be like this well let's try
it out actually so so let's say we have
that key here then let's make this
iterator inventory
find
key think if I remember correctly that's
the way it
works oh or maybe
okay yeah there we go okay okay that's
the way it works of course uh yeah
that's not it's not a pointer
anymore yeah there we go that that makes
more
sense uh to do so this way we already
have access to it where we wouldn't
really want to need
to find it
again um okay and then
uh I just have this kind of uh don't do
here because uh in one of the
assignments uh you're going to be using
maps and you might need to find some
elements there and if you do it like
this where you iterates through the
whole thing looking for
um looking for the
key that's going to be really slow it's
it's much faster to use the uh find
function or or even like the
uh operator uh for it but of course with
the operator there's some like risks
involved the
way of course sometimes you might have a
reason to operate through or or to
iterate through a map but if you need to
find one thing
then definitely
not I just realized
I reference the uh value different ways
in these now so so yeah yeah you can
just do
like it and then arrow and then the
element and and then with the maps uh
like usually with like any kind
of uh pairs that you have in this
standard Library you'll have the uh
properties first and second
so in this case the first would be the
key and second is is then uh the
value
okay so then again let's consider out of
these containers what to use so so let's
see so with vectors we have fast
access to all the elements we have fast
insert and remove at the end
of it so so we can easily like uh add
things to the end of course if it ends
up having
to
preallocate uh the vector or or I call
the memory then um then that's going to
be
slower having to copy all
those all that data is is really
expensive um but otherwise it's it's
fast
okay with list we have fast insert
anywhere and memory is allocated per
element so so every time we add one
element then it allocates the memory for
just that one but with vectors it's uh
kind of allocating more memory ahead of
time and and then also sometimes it has
to do the copying so so list has an
advantage there now with maps
with maps we can actually find that
uh access by key
and and in inserting is actually
especially in case of unordered map it's
actually constant time
operation um at at least most of the
time uh I think there was like in some
cases it might not be but
uh okay so so if we we can quickly
access anything by key and and we can
quickly insert anywhere then wouldn't
that be like really
amazing so then other things to consider
here is uh the amount of memory
consumption caching so so caching uh
especially kind of uh relates
to
the cont good
continuity I
don't entirely know how to pronounce
that but um basically if the data of the
container is kind of all over the place
and you try to access it like a little
bit here and a little bit there uh then
it's actually going to be much slower
for the uh computer because if it's all
like kind of bunched up together all all
the memory of the
container uh
then it might just like all the memory
be like in this C memory and then super
fast to access but if it's all over the
place then the system constantly needs
to like swap the cach memory
around
uh also something
to uh look into is uh the average versus
worst case complexity so a lot of the
time uh when you look it up
it it tells you what the average
complexity
is uh and then if you see like okay what
what this average complexity looks
amazing but maybe you're dealing with a
case that's more like a worst
case and then of course uh if it's if it
is constant complexity then what is the
speed of that constant complexity
so unordered map accessing by
key or or vector accessing by index uh
there's a big difference in in how fast
it is even if they're both uh
constant uh
complexity so the kind of rule of thumb
that you you can consider is uh that
that simpler is better if
it's if it suffices for you so so
Vector is it's it's very simple actually
if you use STD array that's even simpler
and if you don't need it your array to
be dynamic then of course the simplest
option is to use an
array
um yeah that's kind of how you can you
can think about it so if you can stick
with something simple and make it
work then that's probably a good
idea uh
okay then one more I I want to mention
is
DQ this may be something
that you might not have heard
about it doesn't really come up with
like other languages like okay what what
is this so so basically the idea is that
you access it pretty much the same way
as a vector like from the outside it
looks much the
same uh but the main difference
uh and how it operates is that uh you
can you can insert at either end so you
can insert at the beginning or the end
of the
um
like I don't want to say list but but I
guess it's a kind of a r
internally um and then to the user like
they can just access by uh index
and there's no copying uh of anything
what it does kind of internally is
create these multiple different
arrays and and then when you access
something then it kind of uh has to do
two different D references so first the
spine's like okay this is
the uh array we're looking at and then
this is the index of that
array uh okay so so this sounds pretty
amazing like like which is kind of
getting rid of the uh downsides of of a
vector
right um but again there's downsides to
this so so so it's not
continuous the it has these multiple
different arrays like kind of all over
the place they could be anywhere but
that makes the uh like memory caching
much less
efficient and then index access requires
these two pointer D references so so
it's
not as fast there
either and then another kind of detail
is that if you create like a really
small DQ even then it's going to use a
lot of memory because it kind of uh has
to allocate a lot of memory like by
default um to kind of prepare for all
the data that would be added so if you
have
like just like five elements then you
probably don't want to use DQ is kind of
a
waste
um okay and
then you can find even more uh here as
we talked about lists but then there's
also forward list which uh doesn't let
you go backward words but then that
allows it to usess
memory uh the set and multiset like map
um um yeah with just keys and not not
key value pairs in the stack and Q which
are the
um last in first out first in first out
s talked about
those and yeah here here you can kind of
just find the complete list gives you
like a basic uh description of what it
is and and then you can click on them to
find uh more
details so if if you're thinking okay
what kind of data container should I use
for this then you know where to
go okay then I want to
introduce
um it's kind of just a bunch of code
that you don't really have to worry
about but um a way to
measure what is actually uh
fastest and and what I mean by that is
is fastest in your particular uh
scenario so I have a
this I have this code here where um
I'm using this
um I'm using this uh Chrono Library
that's part of the standard Library as
well so this is a good way to time
things uh so so you can you can see here
we we take the clock at a specific
moment then we do something and then we
take the clock uh at the moment after
doing that operation and then we print
that time
um this Chrono Library tends to like
create this really long line so you
usually might want to do something to
kind
of make it a little easier to look at
and like here I have this print time
function that's kind of doing half the
operations so I can make this like
relatively clean
here um
okay we'll look at the results in a
little
bit because first I have another slido
question so if we have 100,000 pairs of
two in to store in a loop uh what is
fastest so so should we add these s STD
pairs I didn't really talk about that
but STD pair is just like a type that
contains two
values
um so should should we just add these
pairs into a vector would it be faster
to add them to a list or since it's two
values maybe we might as well use a map
or we talked about how DQ is actually
like pretty fast uh
for um for insertion
okay vector and list are are getting VES
so
far and this is by the way um kind
of just using a very very kind of KN
solution where like of course with
vectors if we knew ahead of time that
we're going to be adding
100,000 things to it then we could just
reserve the memory ahead of
time
um
but yeah I mean the point here isn't to
find the best data container that exist
it I just want to kind of showcase these
um differences
see um actually I I don't want to run
that because
um because I have another question after
this okay vector and list are getting
the most votes and then somebody is
voting for
DQ and the answers are here
so uh these are the times that I've
gotten on my machine of course could VAR
there's some variance but it's clear
that in a situation like
this DQ ends up being the fastest and
and that's specifically
because because DQ doesn't need
to copy the elements unlike vector and
then list is
actually it's just not really as as fast
you would think because list has to do
all these operations where it's like uh
attaching these nodes to each other
making sure that all the like previous
and next
pointers uh are correct every time just
one thing is
inserted while with uh DQ or or vector
when we're inserting uh to the end then
it just it can kind of just like slap
the element there and and just make sure
that the reported length of the array is
is
correct and then it's done so so
actually list is slower because it has
to do more of this operations so even
though list insertions are constant
time
um it's still like longer constant time
than than vector or or
DQ um
okay but next now that we have these uh
pairs of two in
in these containers which container is
fastest for accessing all of them once
so so we're going to have a
loop that kind of just
um goes
through
um go goes through the container and
accesses all of them once
so uh so so when it can when it's a
container that can be accessed through
index we're going to do this and
otherwise we're going to use an
iterator okay what do we get
um two volts for
Vector anyone have any other opinions
I mean since we're just going through
the entire thing accessing all of them
once uh
maybe maybe list wouldn't be that bad
because uh it's just like following
the next and it doesn't have to like
like if you try to access an individual
element in list it's really slow but in
the case like this is actually not that
bad
um okay well maybe we're not getting any
more about so let's look at the
results and and we can see quite a a
wild difference between vector and some
of the
others and and yeah actually list
this the second one which might be a
little bit surprising maybe I maybe that
should have been the question because
everybody knew that Vector would be
fastest but uh
yeah the the DQ is quite a bit slower
for the reasons I mentioned it is having
to access this memory all over the place
and then it has to like uh do these 2D
references every
time while while with list it's just
kind of accessing one element and then
uh
just following the pointer to the next
one so so it's actually not that
slow um
and with with
Vector it is
definitely much fast faster to do it
like this we could also like use the
iterator to go through the vector in
which case it would be much closer to
the list in
speed uh or we could use also the
um uh at method
okay let's uh just run this here so you
can kind of see so the above is the um
insert and then below is
AIS so the numbers bar a little bit but
uh you can see I and it's also different
machine than I actually found this on
but yeah I I can show you if I do
like that instead
okay it's actually not that much slower
but even then it's like almost twice as
slow or actually no no it's more than
twice as
slow or just
about
um yeah STD Chrono good good way to do
these kinds of measurements so if you're
ever in a situation where
you have some large amount of operations
with some data container you're
wondering okay what what's the best
thing to do here then it's probably best
to just measure it than to like think
hard about the theory of like which
container has the
like best complexity for the scenario or
something like that because there's a
many factors here like I said there's
the memory
caching there's the algorithms there's
the
um possible
pre-allocation sorry I still have
a still recovering a little bit from
this
cough okay uh one
more Topic at the end before I cover the
lab GDP
um so streams and iterators so first of
all what are streams so so it's actually
whenever you f uh like see out something
to print something then you're throwing
stuff into the standard
outstream and that's going to be shown
in
the
terminal and then also you have the STD
in which is kind of in Reverse
taking uh data from the terminal to your
program and then common cases the file
streams so if you want to free data from
a
file uh then you'll have something like
that um so I a really basic example
here so for these streams we can create
this uh I stream iterator that that like
navigates through the
stream
um and yeah so to be clear stream is
basically like you can consider a
sequence of data so so there's like data
coming in and then we have an iterator
to navigate the data as it comes
in
um so then what happens here what we
kind of bind this iterator to SDC
in and then
as long as it's not at the
end
uh it's going to print out the
like value attached and and then go
forward and this is specifically an INT
iterator which is something you can do
with these I stream iterators is that
you can Define the type that you're kind
of looking
for uh
okay so let's see the way that this
behaves it's looking for INS so I type
any kind of
number and then it's just going to print
the same number that I just wrote If I
put like a letter for
example then it say it's like
okay like if it fails to find a number
then it actually like kind of goes to
the
end and also the way the end is defined
here is that this is called like a Sen
uh we're just going to we just
initialize this and we don't really tell
it
anything so then it just kind of
represents like a kind of null value in
a
way it's kind of weird that it's like
this and not like if while input
iterator is not null or
something um
but that's just kind of the way it works
okay then let's look at this a little
bit more complex situation
where uh we want to read from some kind
of file so we have
this uh text file uh I'll actually show
you I made this text file
that's um
it's a it's quite a large text file that
just has a lot of garbage in it it's
kind of copy the same thing over and
over it has some letters it has some
numbers and
then what what we want to see is if we
can find a two from
here so then what what we can actually
do is we can use this find fun function
in in the standard Library which takes
uh the starting iterator and then the
end so it's going to start iterating
from the start until the end looking
for this value that that that we give to
it okay so let's
see I have that code here
okay and it found number two and then I
made give the distance to us as
well and the way I did that is with the
STD distance
function i s this kind of um oh yeah I
actually have
this text here
[Music]
um so I create the ifstream uh for the
file create the copy to the beginning as
well and then the Sentinel
end uh and then the STD
find um traverses through it until it
finds what we want and then with the
stdd distance we can measure the steps
between two iterators we made this copy
so this is still at the
end uh wait hold on that's not
it's not how it should be though it
should be
uh distance to this
right okay maybe maybe this actually
didn't work the way I I thought it would
um okay okay maybe we we'll scrap that I
actually had
this
U bug there all the all this time
um but at least if you well that that
might have been an inefficient way
anyway um probably if you trly need to
find where it is then
then you could um kind of have your own
function to Traverse through it and and
keep track of where it is uh I'll just
show
that there is indeed uh number
two in
here um okay
well never mind I kind of messed up this
example it was kind of last moment that
I was like uh creating some kind of
example out of this
um okay but that's uh enough of the
actual lecture
content um yeah
I'll go over the lab
GDB uh next if you
oh actually I I do see one question in
in slide so sorry I didn't notice it
earlier uh so consider using vectors for
MP college would that have been viable
yes it it would have been
um so it's kind of the EMP colge is
created in a way where using either
arrays or or vectors would be probably
the
easiest uh way to do it
okay also add to
that the also
suggest uh using
what the standard Library Vector yeah
yeah yeah STD Vector yeah yeah I assume
when somebody's asking about vectors
they mean standard
Library
Vector um
okay now let's look
at lab
GDP oh I think I
still I think I still have the solutions
here I need to like
um get rid of the solutions so I can
show it
properly okay let's just go over
here oh I did already have that in the
desktop at least
[Music]
okay now it should be all good okay
so uh I'm of course not going to go over
like all the
explanations uh here I'll just kind of
uh cut to the cut to the chase here a
little bit there uh
the most important com commands we wrote
down
here
uh and I'll also
I show some of that myself but let's uh
first look
at just look at the tasks that we have
here uh let's uh find the
there we
go okay so
first
oh I already had
it
make front lab GDB
front and then what we get is this so so
size
zero so that's say incorrect size
um what we need here is fix the clear
function and fix the insert front uh
function and we should start with
the uh insert front function so for
right now there's nothing there so so of
course uh it was not able to uh put
anything
there uh and then what is also mentioned
there is that you
should or at least you can use
the insert from function from the MP
list as a
basis so in in the lab 3db we have a
singly linked list and this is a doubly
linked list so you could kind of start
like this if if you feel like you don't
Tru know how to get started
here but there's a lot of things here
that are not actually relevant uh
to
us so I don't I don't think we have any
kind of tail that we keep track
of in this case it's going to be called
just
head uh we don't have any
previews so then we kind of want to get
rid of that anyway
um okay so I guess here we have kind of
the basic components that we need to
work with so so if it's insert
front uh
then
uh what that means is that let me just
kind of um visualize this quickly so
let's say if we already have like
a couple boxes and and here's the head
and and the head is pointing to
this next one over here and then we need
to insert at the front so then what
needs to happen is
that we add a new one here that's going
to point to the current
head and
then we're going
to define the head to be this new thing
that we just added
um okay so we have this new
one and the new ones the new nodes next
should be the print
head and then the head should be
the new
node does that make sense
uh the compiler is kind of helpful
because it it can tell you here like if
you copied it from there it's like okay
there's no such variable but there is
something called just length without
underscore
so that makes it easier okay this seems
to work just
fine and then we can see when we insert
this way then of course the most latest
number is is at the front so then we
kind of end up having this reverse order
here
um okay and we can put that in there and
it's going to be
correct okay and then before fixing the
clear
function let's just try running our
program with ALR
and then we can
see this
definitely definitely lost bites and
some indirectly lost
bites sorry um so we can see the
16 definitely lost bites that's what
it's asking for so SP in
16 that's correct
okay then we kind of get to the uh
GDB part
you
uh well actually first I should fix the
clear
function
um okay actually let me kind of go back
to
this I back to this drawing so if we now
have this
situation we have these so so what we
want to do is we want
to delete this and then move on to the
next one then delete that and then move
on to the next
one and then delete that as well
so so we kind of want to
um let's make this
temp
um we store the
uh way to the next
one and then as long as the next is not
null we want
to uh kind
of keep moving
forward actually hold on just go
correctly now
so so let's say we we want
to
delete head right it's always like a
little bit tricky your crap your head
around so
[Music]
um so we delete head then we already
have access to the next
one uh and then we would
want then temp to
be or that then we would want head to be
Temp and temp to
be head next right and then we would
kind of
repeat this
right okay go correctly
is this gonna be
correct the live coding is always
so hard
um I don't think that's going to be
quite correct
right like I I just did this again
like yesterday which is just like the
last thing I did yesterday and and now
it's already like I don't know what I'm
doing
anymore yeah that's not
[Music]
correct okay maybe I'll just not not
worry about it and and just
uh just move on that's not really the
point anyway
you also need to assign LS
Z oh yeah
true that's
definitely yeah I this is more about
learning the GDB than like the actual
like how do
you implement these
exactly I
mean sorry that I'm a little bit like
sloppy with like going through this but
like I say always difficult to do live
coding stuff I should probably have like
Solutions next to me so I don't like
blank out on
things
um but hopefully you get the idea even
if even if I kind of
like mess this up
um okay but but now let's look at like
the way uh GDB
Works um okay
so we've run our program with uh GDB I
think that should
actually that doesn't have the like Dot
and slash there but but you
should
um okay so now GDB is
running and then we want to insert some
kind of
breako
um so we can insert
the uh break points by typing the the
function yeah that should be fine and
then if we run
front then we find that okay okay the
program ran up to this point and then it
stopped and it's seeing like okay now
we're at the break point and and now we
can also access some uh information
Let's uh see so it's in list
given actually I do think I have these
Solutions here that I
can kind of use to help sort this
out
U let's just let's just put
this um
this
here um okay so it's telling us that
we're in list given
79 yeah okay that looks just about right
so we can see it's like printing out the
line that we're currently in and we can
see it matches with
that okay okay what does it want us to
do
um okay so we can see that there's this
uh
current and then we we kind of want to
see what the value of that is
so then we
can
display for
data we
can display the the pointer
itself and now that we set those
displays
there we can type in next and then every
time we like going of go go to the next
line it's going to keep displaying these
values that we
defined
um okay so this looks like what it wants
from
us so let's put that
there um okay and the next thing
uh we can kind of get out of this by
using the kill command for example and
let's also delete break
points so those are also some commands
you can use if you if you're wondering
like what what are all the commands the
you can type
help and then you get all of
these and then you can also like okay
help
break points and then you get more
information about break
points so there's a lot of stuff you you
can find by doing
that okay let's
um break at
the Traverse function so here it's
asking for something like this but now
it's giving us RGB a
pixel and that's basically because we're
using like a template function
and then when it's compiled now it's
actually seeing it as like rgba
pixel um but that's going to be
fine okay and then get let's give a
condition it says here condition one but
but in this case the breako is number
two so condition
two
um current data
Alpha 42
and then if we type continue the program
is going to keep running until it runs
into something that stops
IT uh oh first I need to run the
program uh oh I think I need to
let do this
again bre list
reverse R reverse
condition all right then we
continue okay and
we get up to here and then now that we
are
here back
trace and now we can see all the
function calls that happened uh up to
this
point and since this reverse function is
recursive we can see that keeps calling
itself here you can see the Len argument
is like changing
a lot here if we had this entire back
trace of uh the entire thing then it' be
really lengthy but we had the breakpoint
condition so it didn't go quite that
far
um okay and then we want to find the
first call to the reverse helper
function which
is which is
this right because this is actually the
uh this is not the helper function this
is like the function for the interface
where you just call like okay reverse
this but this is the precursive helper
function so just type the number of that
so in the back phrase It's the 40
second uh function
call okay and
then we have a few
different uh functions to fix I'll just
kind of show the answers because like I
noticed lab coding isn't isn't going
going that well for me
so
um let me just kind of see what the what
the issue was with each of
these
um okay with with this one issue is
that it doesn't increase the length in
this
case and then the other thing is
um let's see said kind of just in
different
order this like couple different ways
you you can like uh kind of do this
exactly but
uh oh right the yeah the
[Music]
problem right yeah yeah you need to
actually uh put the new one in the in
the next of the temp not not in the temp
directly that this way it just ends up
kind of being
stuck um
and that's like where with using GDP you
can kind of notice like okay now it's
supposed to move on the next one but
then you see like okay this pointer
didn't really move
anywhere um
okay next reverse
function uh over here
so that here uh the the the way um
the way you want to kind to approach
this since it's
precursive um so you can see when it
first calls
this um well okay let let me actually
just show this so let's put
um make sure I don't have any break
points and let's break at
uh see if we can do it by line
number
um very like that
um okay okay so now we get
here and then the operation is that we
get the next of the current but then we
can see that the current is actually
zero at this
point um and and so so the reason I
wanted to put a break point here is that
because it's a recursive function we can
notice that like it's just going to like
go here like 70,000 times in this case
so there's nothing interesting happening
until the length increases zero then we
get here and then we can notice when we
get
here as a current is all readyy zero so
we actually went too far in this case so
we actually just changed that to one
okay that's
fine and then for
Shuffle
uh yeah this is when I originally did
this it was really helpful for me to
like draw on on on paper but basically
what the
uh problem here is is that this
um like one never
really moves
anywhere so we always get like one next
that's the temp but one is always the
same so it's just kind of stuck in place
so uh then we can just update one
at the end every
time and I think that should be all of
it
um oh test answer is wrong
s maybe I forgot
something oh right in
the insert back I didn't
do that
yet okay and now everything should be
correct okay yeah this was a little bit
as the labs get more complicated gets
more difficult to show them uh in
lectures um it might be easier for the
next one to create separate recording or
something I'll see how I handle it
um if if this was still like a little
bit unclear then be sure to ask on
Discord or
somewhere um for clarification on the
assignment um but yeah hopefully
hopefully you'll find find GDB
useful uh I find it especially when you
run into like segmentation FS or
something like that it's really useful
because it can just kind of let you
inspect the situation at the moment of
segmentation
fault and then another thing is when
you're like kind of dealing with these
pointers and
traversing then it's useful for kind of
understanding what everything is
pointing
to at all
times um but yeah uh
that would be the lecture for today and
indeed
um this Thursday Villas lecture
in
uh s
112 at uh
2:15 a lot of it is going to be about
like uh modern C++ practices and and uh
espe memory
management related
things I'm personally personally looking
forward to his lecture and I hope to see
a lot of people there but uh yeah that's
that's it for
today's lecture so see you there