you don't
need ah sorry so you don't you don't
need to do any
particular op in like in uh in C you
need to inherit from a disposable
interface to be able to use the scope
cleanup
mechanism
so this is emphasiz by the
actual supposed or like a
the uh the uh syntax by which you
actually invoke a Destructor is just a
closing brace because that will invoke
the destructors of of the local
objects and it's it's gener and generic
in the sense that this works for every
kind of block so if you exit a function
you get the destructors Run for the
things that were created in that
function if you exit a loop it works the
same way if you have block statements in
the branches of U conditional statements
like if
else or if you have a block statement in
a in a case of a switch case you always
exit a block and you get the destructors
run you can also have BL plain block
statements that are not attached to any
Loop
construct or a conditional so if you
just write a pair of phases and code
between that
that does introduce a new
scope and then when you exit that scope
you get
distructor run when when you do the
exit so there's a some slideware
examples of this so in this first
example uh we create a unique pointer
there and we just fall off the end of
the
function that will destroy the unit
pointer and that leads into deallocating
the memory stored for the actual object
of Type
X which will then of course invoke the
destructor of that X object as
well so the slightly different example
there
below is that we we have an explicit
return
statement and that just works the same
way um of course in addition to this uh
you can you can exit a function by
throwing an exception that does exactly
the same thing it runs the distractors
of all all scope local
objects if we look at various ways of
exiting a loop it does exactly the same
thing so we have there that conditional
break if it so happens that uh the
uh I equals
the index that was passed as a
parameter the break will exit the loop
completely of course that will result in
the uh unique pointer named V being
destroyed and then continue of course
jumps out of that block
statement by jumping to its end it will
exit that block
statement and that will run the
destructors again
so all kinds of ways to to exit Loops
will always uniformly run the uh scope
local
distructor uh it's it's mentioned in the
in the slide slides bullet points that
you could also go to out of this
Loop uh whether that's recommended is of
course a philosophical
discussion but uh for the PO purposes of
this exam explanation that we the same
way if you go to out of a block
statement it will still run the
destructors for the object in in that
block
statement so yeah all forms of block
exit work the same way you can fall off
the end of of a block you can return out
of it you can use break or continue you
can throw an exception or call a
function that throws an
exception and you can go to out of it
and in all of these cases is the cleanup
world
one I you perhaps mentioned for
completeness sake that if you use a
legacy C function called long jump that
will not run your local destructors
because
it's it's not using facilities that are
C++
aware but uh if you use long jump in a
C+ plus program where you have
non-trivial cleanups in
scope that is undefined Behavior
so it is not statically determinable so
the compiler can't always tell you that
you're doing wrong
things but um the standard specifies it
as undefined Behavior which is a very
strong license against doing
that now then generally about Resource
Management about scope Resource
Management scope Resource Management
types are types that release a resource
in their
Destructor they are used as local
variables variables with automatic
storage duration I mean objects of
resource management
types and what that does is that it
binds a
resource with a storage duration that is
longer than automatic usually
Dynamic to a scope to a block of code
so when you have like a dynamic
allocation you bind it to a particular
scope and the distructor will handle it
so that when the scope is exited the
cleanup of the dynamic allocation
happens as if it were were a
uh a variable of automatic storage
duration so it it ties the lifetimes of
uh
of automatic
objects Resource Management types come
in all kinds of fa flavors so they may
or may not own a resource some do and
some just find an
existing resource to a
scope so not all resource management is
about
lifetimes uh just because a particular
resources release doesn't always mean
the allocating memory
it is relatively common that this kind
of resource Handles in local Scopes are
bound to a single scope so you can't
even transfer them outside of a scope
but sometimes you can and that's
actually
useful so the motivational bit of course
is that why is this important
well this was something that I
pretty much uh dogmatically adopted as a
programming technique and
Stu 20ish years ago earlier in my career
when you use this kind of resource
management rappers consistently you'll
never have a memory
Le due
[Music]
to really
okay are you observing the chat if
there's
question U there's two questions in the
chat it but I'm scared
okay