this
okay
okay so let's see today um we're going
to work on pointers we're going to
figure out we're going to go through all
of the cases of things that can go bad
with pointers and with handling memory
and we'll talk about the good practice
of working with
pointers um
so that's the goal of this lecture and
then as I said elmary will go through
lab
intro um and all of the um other stuff
that we didn't ask you to work with that
the structure of the code which might be
useful for you in future assignments but
the lecture is useful for your lab DB
debug where you'll have to work with
pointers Chase pointers and figure out
where memory where where there is a bug
with some with memory in some
way so let's start with Let Me Go full
screen
here okay so we're going to go through
definitions and this is just going to be
a warmup so I'll ask you to use your
phone and
answer uh this simple warm-up quiz
questions so we're going to go through
all of these definitions when a variable
is declared on stack on the stack on the
Heap when variables get values when
stack memory or heat memory is cleared
or when a null pointer is deleted all of
these are nice operations they don't
cause any problem this is something that
we'll have to write in our code so this
is something that is welcome in the code
and as a programmers we will be doing
this all the time so let's go through
this the first question is a variable is
declared on the
stack so pick all of the lines that
correspond to
that so we go through these exercises
first and then we'll um just write down
all of the answers in the
end so pick all of the lines that
declare a variable on the
stack
so declaration is we tell the system hey
we're going to use this variable we
didn't give a value to it yet we're just
declaring it we're telling the system
hey there's an intention that we have to
use this variable and that's its name no
value yet so which are the variables
that are declared on the stack
here so Z equals new int does not
declare a variable on the stack
okay that's incorrect because Z is
already declared and new int will take a
chunk of memory from the
Heap
okay now a variable is declared on the
Heap which lines are the the ones that
would declare a variable on the Heap
so we tell the system yeah only this one
we tell the system we are going to
intent we we have an intent to use some
memory on the Heap but we don't give it
value
yet xals 10 no this one is no this one
is no this is already definition of the
variable so those variables already
declared before
right so these are no but this is yes
okay
good um the next question is a variable
gets a new value now this could be any
variable Heap variable or or stack
variable so pick all of the lines that
correspond to the situation that a
variable gets a new
value yeah very good
yeah yeah very good so all of
this and this one very important that
you got this one Z will get a new value
Z will get the address of this
initialized but declared variable on the
Heap very good we'll draw a picture of
that for
that
later okay so you P all of the good
lines
in all of those instances a variable
will get a new value now a a stack
variable gets a new value or stack
memory has is changed what are the lines
that correspond to that Lo a situation
that a stack is changed a memory on the
stack is changed or a variable that is
declared on the stack gets a new
value
very
good Delete p
no delete Z so very good because we'll
talk about this delete p and delete Z
will not change the values of the
pointers p and Z they will stay
unchanged it'll only clear the Heap
memory but the stack will not be changed
with this and that's what opens the door
to what's called dling pointers so this
is very bad situation you will have to
clean PMZ because delete pnz does not
change the stack values but everything
else so this is correct this is correct
the stack value is going to change the
stack uh memory is going to change
integer p no that doesn't do that but
this this is correct this is correct
this is correct this is correct good
we'll write the answers later so don't
worry if you are not writing it yet a
variable gets a new value on the
Heap so when is the
Heat
changed when is the Heap changed yeah
very good
good the Heap will not get value here
it'll reuse whatever is there
so it's not a the the variable is
declared but not get it doesn't get its
value this is stack variable so no stack
variable no so this is
correct delete p and delete
Z so it's kind of like yes the Heap
values the Heap um will change here or
may not it's kind of more undefined
Behavior so I would say maybe maybe not
but definitely I wouldn't say that it's
guaranteed that the variable on the Heap
gets um a new value so it's incorrect to
say so however Heap might be changed
upon that uh um upon that line so there
are only three lines
but this is the correct answer I jumped
it jumped too bad fast so this is the
correct answer everything else is
incorrect everything else is incorrect
but there's some discussion that can
happen with deletes okay next question
stack memory is cleared out by the
system so what is the line where stack
memory is going to be cleared out by the
system the system will take that stack
memory and say okay this these variables
do not have control over it I will use
it for some other variables I will use
it for something else I I am taking the
control back so what are the
lines if you can see that I added line
13 what
is what is the correct answer no no no
line 13 line 13 is is the only correct
answer everything know the the stack is
not
touched the system does not take that
memory back with
this
okay okay let's go back let's go to the
next Slide the last question heat memory
is cleared out is it the last question
no pre last Heat memory is cleared out
by the system so when is that the case
so with Heap with persistent memory
which is the
Heap the we have to tell the system when
to take the memory back right so we
announce it the specific statements and
what are those
statements delete Z delete P that's when
the system takes the Heap memory back
when we assign null to pnz we are
operating with the stack only right
we're changing the value of p on the
stack not on the Heap we are not
changing the Heap memory there okay and
one last and now pointer is deleted so
where is that happening in this
code the deleting a null pointer is a no
op there's no problem with that so it
happens here because Z is null so delete
Z is deleting null pointer and the
system just goes looks at the address
started Z sees that it's a null space
the space for null pointer so deleting
it is a no op you don't have to delete a
null pointer nothing happens so it's
okay um and you can do that in your code
nothing really happens okay so these are
the
answers but I want to populate the
answer I want to draw the picture
because there were some
problems um that we en encountered right
so let's see what happens let's go
through this code line by line when I
say integer main the moment I write let
me start writing the moment I
write this curly I open the curly
bracket that's when the Heap for that
function is initiated or the the stack
for this function sorry stat stack stack
for this function is initiated so all of
the variables that are going to be
declared in the scope of this curly
brackets Will Go On The Stack for this
function and when I close the curly
bracket that's when all of those
variables all of that memory within this
function allocated for declared
variables will be cleared taken back by
the system or cleared out so let's see
how it happens so let's go through then
the lines of this function one by one
first integer X so variable of type
integer with the name X is declared on
the stat so it's in some location let's
say
A1 no value yet type integer right so
that's where a variable is declared on
the
stack so at line two right the next line
is declaring two pointers p and Z they
are stack
variable
so maybe at some location A2 a variable
p is declared on the stack of type
integer pointer and then at location A3
variable Z is declared off type integer
pointer there are no values there these
are just declaration
so this are just declarations I didn't
assign any value therefore this values
here maybe just whatever system re uses
or maybe it puts some default values it
will depend on your execution on your
compiler on all of those things so you
don't know you don't have control of it
the system will have control of it and
most likely it's just going to be reused
values whatever was there because that's
the most efficient thing to do now line
four so there are two steps happening
happen in here whatever is on the right
hand side that's asking for Heap memory
whenever you say new you ask the system
to give you a new variable on the Heap
which will never have the
name it'll have location B one so this
is Heap say B1 location no value you
didn't ask for Value you didn't
initialize you didn't Define this value
you just declare you didn't Define this
variable you just declared it and you
said that the type of it is
integer so this is a declaration of a
new variable on the Heap here just line
four and it's the right hand side of
this expression that accomplishes
it now the left hand side and and this
assignment statement that's what
initializes your variable
Z which is on the stack because
assigning this gives the value B1 to the
pointer Z so now your pointer Z points
to that memory location in the heat okay
therefore line four also
accomplishes this a variable gets a new
value and a variable gets a new value on
the step not on the Heap on the stack
right so Z value Z variable gets a new
value on the stack
okay so the next line I think this was
easier oh yeah this was easier so we do
reference Z that is we ask for a
variable at Z's value location right so
we ask for this variable with no name we
follow the pointer with an asterisk so
we ask for that variable and we give it
a new value one so line five is the only
line which really accomplishes
of changing the
Heap uh memory right and giving a new
value to a variable on the Heap that has
no
name okay now line six line seven and
line eight essentially accomplish the
same thing they take these variables on
the stack and they give them new values
so let's see what happens first we give
x value 10 second we give P the address
of X which is
what so what will be the value of P
after this
operation what should I put
here A1 A1 very good thank you because
this EMP % will take will strip memory
address off that variable s so it will
be A1 okay and then the line 8 will
assign value Q to Value P so what will
become essentially I'm overwriting the
value A1 now with
what let me use different different
color because we just assigned A1 to P
but now we're saying no no no we want P
to have a different value which is Q's
value what is Q's
value oh I don't have a Q probably I
meant Z
right all right right this is yeah what
this would be a compilation Arrow okay
let's try Z then of course maybe Q would
be defined somewhere but what if it's
C then B1 yeah so weting it with B1 and
again we just working this is just
stack stack operations stack variables
right that get new new values so six
seven and eight just stack variables
getting new
values now I'm going to say delete P hm
delete p
what does it
mean what is p now p is B1 so it's
pointing to the same location as Z right
and if I say delete P the system will
just take its value and clears out or
takes back the memory located in that
place in that address in that value so
this VAR this memory is gone we not have
access over it anymore the system will
be using it for other pointers or for
other uses
right
that's good that's a good thing we we
should be doing it we should be clearing
out Heap memory so now we have the
pointer p and pointer Z pointing
to the same location but that location
is not ours anymore to use so it's a
little bit diff difficulty or dangerous
situation that we need to make sure we
we clean kind of so we we need to use
good practices because bad things can
happen that we'll talk about on the next
slide but what I'm doing here I'm just
saying pnz equals to null uh right
here but um let's go back to line nine
so does line nine correspond to any of
these questions yeah Heap memory is
cleared out by the system so that's good
good also Hep memory may be changed here
maybe some other variables will in the
meantime will get this memory and maybe
the values there will be changed but I
wouldn't say that it's guaranteed so you
cannot really claim that that happens
here
okay so you cannot really say oh a
variable will get new value if you say
delete P because that's not incorrect it
may or may not
happen now uh line 10 P equals to null
and line 11 Z equals to null so we are
going
to assign new values for variables on
the stack and they're going to be
zero addresses or n addresses of
null which means that lines 10 and 11
correspond to a variable getting a new
value on the step
right delete Z
so now we're going to delete Z so we'll
take the value of Z which is null and
delete it it's a no op it's allowed by
the system because there's nothing to
free at
0.0 so the system will
allowed okay any questions about it
anything weird so let's go uh the next
slide
is um questions any questions about it
so this is a warmup we want went through
the definitions that we learned last
time now let's go what can go bad we
didn't talk about it but it's
exactly your lab
debug and I'll show you how we will take
good code but then remove a couple of
lines from it and give it to you in lab
love dag to find a bug because
removing some important lines from good
code will lead to some kind of bad
behavior so let's look at all of the
possible bad behaviors that can
happen undefined Behavior have you met
that yet when you were debugging your
lab intro did you see that undefined
Behavior can happen so what is undef
undefined Behavior sometimes systems C
the system May crash and sometimes it
runs
okay sometimes it may have some runtime
errors like it's
slow but others it just seemed to work
fine so that's what's called undefined
Behavior Insidious bug is related to
undefined Behavior so it's when it's
really difficult to find where exactly
your program is not working so that's
what insidious bug is keep corruption is
another type so all of these I'm talking
about runtime errors not compilation
errors so the compiler is not on your
side the compiler will compile your
program and say everything is fine maybe
there's a warning somewhere but maybe no
not at all
so these are all runtime errors so you
compile your program and then you run it
and then you see that something is
happening and again once in a while
you'll actually see that there's a SE
fold message or some kind of message
that the system says when upon the crush
but it may be that your program doesn't
even crash it just doesn't work properly
so um undefined behavior is one such
situation Insidious bug is another such
situation Heap corruption that's when
that's why in undefined Behavior may
happen so if you're overriding a heap
the Heap with something in a place that
you are not
authorized then undefined Behavior may
happen because you're may be overriding
the value of some other variable that
you think you're not
touching and that will lead to undefined
Behavior un initialized pointer so
that's when you declared your
pointer and the pointer has some value
which is may look like an address that
you're not authorized to touch and then
you der reference and put some value in
that address on the Heap that may lead
to undefined Behavior or the system May
crash or it it may work properly dling
pointer is when you delete a pointer but
you don't assign null to it so bad in
because then if you D reference it you
will access unauthorized heat memory
again a memory leak is when you don't
delete a pointer at all so you just
assign null to a pointer or some other
value to a pointer some other memory
location uh which means that your HEAP
memory was not freed and if you do it
sufficiently enough many
times you will run out of heat memory
and your system will just your your
program will slow slow
down double free so what if you delete
your pointer twice so you say delete
that location Twice first time is fine
but second time this memory may belong
to some other variable you attempt to
free
it it leads to un again undefined
Behavior many strange things can happen
can happen so the only good runtime
error here is the reference in an all
pointer because that's always a sec
fault so that's kind of good so let's I
give you next slide is I gave you a
bunch of situations so do you have any
questions if you don't have any
questions let's go to the next
slide so this is all of the bad things
that can
happen and once again we're going to go
through each one of these codes and you
tell me which of these runtime
arrows that is that code is so we'll go
through a b c d e f g and you'll have to
pick all of the one through 10 which
would correspond to that situation
right okay so let's see number
one I declare a v two variables and then
I give that
assignment what kind of error is
that this is kind of a sentex question
huh yeah why is that it's a compilation
error correct why is
that yeah so this is more an exercise of
what does it mean when I say integer
pointer P comma
X and the the this asterisk belongs to P
not to integer so this declaration
declares a pointer P but just an integer
X so if I wanted X to be a pointer to I
would have to put sis to it here as well
okay just a syntax question so once I
know that P is an integer pointer but X
is just an integer this assignment just
does not make sense to the compiler
because it's a mismatch of types so not
good so it's just a compilation error
there's no uh other problem here that's
the easiest because the compiler will be
on your side and it will just tell you
exactly hey you cannot assign an integer
value to a pointer right because the
pointer will want an address not an
integer
value the next question is what if I
declare an integer pointer and I give
it the the location where it points to
20 Val 20 what which one is this
problem
unfortunately it's not a compilation
eror the compiler will say sure fine
whatever undefined Behavior
good uninitialized pointer so the main
the the core problem here initialized
uninitialized pointer your memory looks
like
p is on the stack and it has garbage
value and you're trying to dreference
that garbage value maybe it will lead
you to some Heap memory maybe it'll
crash great so it's undefined Behavior
also as well uninitialized pointer leads
to undefined Behavior but if it if that
garbage makes sense to the system and it
looks like a memory address on Heap
it'll go to that memory it'll put 20
there but that memory maybe Le to to
some other fun other variable right so
it's a very very bad practice to do
something like this because you
assessing unauthorized memory
potentially and you're lucky if it's a
SE
fault okay so we would uh I have answers
later you'll see all of the answers but
I would say that the core here is UN
initialized poter but it leads to
undefined Behavior a runtime error
that's definitely a runtime error there
could be SE fault it could crash but it
could all all of these undefined all of
these are runtime errors right it's also
an Insidious bug because you're actually
manage you will manage to change that
unauthorized heat memory then you will
be chasing that bug for a long time
because some other memory suddenly will
be getting a different value 20 when you
don't know which one I don't know is it
me or not but who is oh yeah let me try
to maybe okay
here okay so very good we'll go through
answers later now
um I am declaring a pointer P here I'm
asking for a for for memory on the Heap
nicely and I'm putting a value three
there right there so I'm essentially I
decare two values there on Heap and on
stack p and that unnamed variable and I
gave values to both of
them but then I say p equals to
no yeah this is a
dangling no it's not a dangling pointer
so no because the pointer is not going
to be dling it's going to get null value
it's going to be fine but you just had
poter P pointing to that nice allocated
memory in the Heap with value three
and then you assign it to point to null
what happened to that memory do you have
a handle of it if you don't if that's
all your code has then it's lost so it's
a Memory link so it's a runtime Arrow as
well and it's a Memory Le it can cause
all sorts of problems later on like um
bad performance you you may run out of
memory if you do that uh sufficiently
many times and I'll show you an example
later I have a code which runs out of
memory e up all of the heat memory
because I do it in a
loop okay now um another code so I
declared p as a pointer X as an integer
I gave x a value it's on the stack so X
has five value five
p is a pointer on the stat but it also
got the address the stack address right
and then I delete P so then what
happens
[Music]
yeah yeah I delete I tell the system
look at that value of the pointer which
in this case is the
stack delete that please delete that
what do you think will
happen so actually in this case this is
will be on your side and it will warn
you hey you know you are trying to
delete a stack memory and that's not
allowed so uh you'll get a message here
so thank goodness right because we will
not mess up with the stack will be
warned so it's going to be a uh
um so it's going to be a compilation
error in the comp in the compiler but
it's it's really stressful because in on
my compiler it's just a warning so the
compilation gives you warning and then
when you run it
crashes so I don't know what's going to
happen on every possible system you're
welcome to run this code and see what
happens but essentially make sure that
you never delete stack memory because on
my system the compiler is on my my uh my
side but maybe it's not everywhere I
don't know what happens in all possible
situations but you're not allowed to to
delete a stack memory so this is
bad um I have this code somewhere but I
don't try it at home and you see what
happens in your
case uh so this is not a dangling
pointer in this case although it may be
eventually deleting P without assigning
to null is a bad practice but I think
the program will crash before that
because it will attempt to clear stack
memory okay
um now if you have a pointer P you got
the nice memory on the Heap for it you
initialized both you have three on the
Heap you have the address of this
variable on on the stack for p now you
delete that
memory
twice what happens yeah you left ding
pointer that's true you never actually
REM you clear that memory but P still
points to it right P still has that
address unless you assign it to null or
to something else so very good but you
do it twice so double free leads to
undefined
Behavior you're clearing that memory
that already belongs to this to the
system so that's not good so essentially
you can say it's actually danging point
I guess because you deleted it you
didn't reassign it to null you're trying
to delete it you're assessing another
heat memory which is
unauthorized and you're dealing with it
messing with the heat memory that you
should not be
doing okay very good now the is it the
last no next to
last so you again have this nice
situation you deleted P so you clear
that memory on the Hep but now you
trying to access it and assign P to it
that's the classic example of dangling
pointer you deleted P but if you didn't
reassign its value you're trying to
access that memory again just like you
did with delete so that's a classic
example of dangling pointer which is a
runtime error as well which may lead to
undefined Behavior it it is an Insidious
bug it is Heap corruption so corruption
so all of those
thingss and the last example so now it
seems like you're doing everything fine
you have p and three on the Heap p on
the stat Del lead P you clear that
memory you read you don't have a
dangling pointer you put null into the p
and then you're trying to
access null memory and put three in
there right so what happens
here it's the reference in an N pointer
it's always set F here at least it's
very clear SE fault means you try to Der
reference now pointer so there's no
undefined fine behavior in this case it
will always give you SE fault which is
the best of all of the running runtime
errors okay so here are all of the
answers which is good so I have a
question for you is anything here not
clear should we go through any of these
examples um and draw should we pick one
so tell me which one and we'll draw a
picture of what's going on
so which one was the least clear to
you A B C D E F or
G anything or everything is
clear pick one and tell
me
[Music]
no should continue
or or something was not clear so I put
every all of the possible errors here
right it's kind of like the last one is
the
actual example of what went wrong so
eight is a memory Le but it's always a
runtime error so eight a memory leak it
is a runtime error or like here seven is
dangling pointer but a d green pointer
May is may lead to Heap corruption
Insidious bug undefined behavior and
runtime error right again uninitialized
pointer where did we have uninitialized
pointer this one I guess but it's also
kind of a dangling
pointer uh but it's also in shiz pointer
so it has all of those right and double
free which is this case double free
that was because we had uninitialized
pointer or angling pointer actually I
should add seven here as well this PO is
dangling there so we're trying to delete
it if we put P equals to
null then no bad problems would happen
because deleting P would be a no off
right
so there should be seven should be there
as well and then do reference in N
pointer that's also a runtime error by
the way which again put two there um but
it's the easiest of all of the runtime
errors because it's just SE
false okay so all good right
no we don't need to go through drawing
this so now this brings us to the your
next
Lab in
C++ you can do many bad things by by
working with
memory
and just making some tiny mistakes like
forgetting some lines forgetting some
steps and you run into this runtime
errors so I give you I give you here a
nice order of working with pointers if I
want to have a pointer p
I first ask for heat memory for it right
so let's draw what happens I initialize
P I declare p and first it's a d green
pointer so right after I need to
initialize it otherwise I'll have not an
initialized pointer so at line two I
initialize it so I get some heat
memory with no value yet but I
initialized my pointer that's nice so
this two steps should go
together if you don't do it if you don't
initialize pointer you have an
uninitialized pointer that could lead to
runtime error then you can do reference
P you can work with P so you can put
value three here uh that's great then at
some when you're done with P you delete
this memory you clear it out you give it
back to the system but if you don't put
this to step together if you immediately
don't give some other value to P you'll
have a dangling pointer which can again
lead to sorts all sorts of problems
therefore it's a good practice to assign
it to null right away so give it that
special area address value of null
pointer okay so these two should be
paired these two should be paired then
it's one of the right orders or right
one of the right ways or sequ of doing
things so what we did in lab
debug we just you know forgot some lines
in our code inserted some bugs so what
and this is going to be questions for
you what happens if I just
forget line
two so I do that what if I just forget
line four what if I swap lines four and
five what if I swap lines five and two
so I think we already in our Discord
discussion you saw that we had swapped
lines here so what does it mean what
happens let's go these are exercises as
well so I have this and you pick what
happens I think again here you only can
pick one but pick the worst like the the
most the the biggest reason I guess uh
for what will happen
if you forget to write line two you have
uninitialized pointer and then we know
already from previous exercises what
that leads to very
good very good so that's an initialized
pointer
problem okay what happens if I forget
line
four
I forget to
delete yeah I memory right already saw
that so you have your pointer and you
just immediately assign n to it what
happened to that heat memory it's there
system cannot reuse it nobody can reuse
it okay now what happens if both lines
in
two
are removed again compiler will say it's
fine program is fine you'll get a
runtime
arrow and uh which one is the worst I
guess uninitialized or it's both
essentially it's both memory leak and
uninitialized
pointer that you get yeah which one is
worse I guess uninitialized pointer is
worse than the memory Le but in any case
it's a the runtime
Arrow okay very
good
yeah and it's a runtime error obviously
yes what happens if you swap lines four
and
five so you have your nicely initialized
Heap and stack in
Heap but you're Reign P to null before
deleting
it the biggest problem here is memory Le
so it's as if you just forgot line four
right because after that again compiler
will not tell you
anything but you'll try to delete null
which is a no op but you lost that
memory in the Heap so the biggest
problem here is memory
leak uh and
number last last one is whopping five
and
two yeah the referencing L pointer so
this is the nicest of all of the bad
problems because you get SE fault that's
easy to
diagnose right so these are the answers
I put them
here
and this is one of the good orders then
so you'll have to find where we
implanted a bug in that lab and fix
it using this
order um
now this it's the same slide I just
wanted to kind of point out that if we
keep these two lines together so we have
to remember that these two steps have to
happen together in that order no
swapping orders then
once I'm done with this pointer I used
it I cleaned it up what if I still want
to reuse it so the question is where can
I go from Step six can I repeat any of
the lines so is line two okay to repeat
is line three okay to repeat so let's
see is it
safe
atline sets to start
over where is it
save I think you can only answer one lot
but pick all if it's not picked yet pick
all that
apply so from Step say it's safe to
delete the pointer it's good so line
four is safe line
three is not safe because you get SE
fold right line two is safe right so
that's cool so what I'm trying to get
here is that when you write big big code
so this is the answers very good when
you write big code you might be using
pointers and then maybe some other F
functions will be reusing them so you
want to clean your pointers in you want
to leave your pointers in a clean state
so that's why you follow this order and
keep them always at all times you keep
your pointers
clean and this is a nice order because
again once you're done with the
pointer other users can start at line
too but even a better order even another
right order which might be even
better is this so let's try erase this
code so always keep line one and two
together sorry I need to
um charge
my I lose it so you look at this code
for a little bit and then we discuss it
that's what's happening
there Outlet some more clothes
okay good okay
so I initialize pointer to now but I
could initialize I could declare an
initialize pointer to something else I
could also ask for p equals
new whatever
or just initialize it in any way I want
assign it some other pointer that's
just this is initialization step but the
idea is that when you initialize your
pointer always initialize it either to
null or to some
value now when you delete your pointer
again initialize it to null then it's
always safe for whoever uses this
pointer net to return to line to step
three and when they use this pointer
they'll first check if it's null because
it could be and if it's null then
they'll initialize it to something valid
but otherwise they'll use it and der
reference it so that's kind of like good
atate right that's how you handle your
pointers to other software Engineers who
write the code that's a good way so
always at all times your pointer should
be either null or proper properly in the
properly
defined
okay so here this
is good uh the rules of good software
engineering with handling
pointers any questions about
that now I want to jump a little bit
ahead we actually talking about arrays
next lecture that damic
arrays um there are many ways of holding
array defining arrays in
C++ there is this classical way of where
you deal with Dynamic arrays on Heap
memory but there's also standard Library
arrays that you can use that are much
safer because as you can see we're
talking now about C style memory memory
handling that is unsafe way of handling
memory in C++ that was was inherited
from C after that
C++ became or adopted much safer
structures that uh software Engineers
can use however there's still a lot of
code out there that has this unsafe
practices um that's why we have to cover
both and next time we'll talk about
arrays more but now I just want to um if
you jump ahead with your labs and start
working with arrays I just want to point
out that the same good rules apply to
arrays and the syn of defining arrays is
very similar so when you declare a
pointer just a pointer like in our case
to declare an array Dynamic array it's
the same declaration it's going to be a
pointer but then asking for memory here
your pointer P will ask only for one
integer variable on the he while here
with this declaration new Square integer
square bracket three you're asking for
three values on the Heap so your in your
pointer X here is p here's X will
actually point to the beginning of a
block of three integer variable on the
Heap that's how arrays are you find
stack Hep stack Hep and then you have to
Loop them through those values over here
by der referencing X and the syntax is
really nice you can der reference X just
by saying square bracket I so the zero
element at s square bracket zero will be
the
first variable on the Heap then X1 will
be second and S2 is going to be third in
this case of array of size
three so you do reference your ARR array
or pointer to the array and work with it
you first of course declared it and
defined it and ask for memory for it
then you do reference and initialize it
and then you delete your array and the
syntax again is similar to The Pointer
except that you ask for three variables
so you need to use the syntax that is
for arrays that is you use square
brackets there to say that delete all
three not just
s did I forget something now you know
the rules of good behavior what did we
forget I forgot one more
line no yeah the same way so don't
forget that you should also set X to no
otherwise you have a ding pointer to
this beginning of the array the same
problem right fine what could be the
bugs that we plant in there for
you we could forget the square
bracket what do I do then then I just
delete the first
element instead of the whole chunk right
so that's one thing again we could swap
the lines we could do all the same
things because as you can see syntax is
very similar for one pointer versus the
whole array of pointers so again the
same problems could happen if you swap
the lines forget one line all of those
things right just the sentence is
slightly
different so I hope this helps you with
love lab
debug uh debugging these things
debugging
pointers so that's good what else I
wanted to say any questions from people
online now I have
just more a little more fun with
pointers let me ask um el el mar how
many minutes do you need because we
still have half an hour do you need half
an hour because I can leave this as a uh
quiz questions for next
time uh well you can you can still go if
you want
to let's see I hope they're not muted
they're not muted so uh can you hear
me okay let me write him a message
El just let me know
you are
ready and we can stop
anytime no I can't hear you
yep oh yeah because I muted now what
about
now say it again hello yeah yeah I was I
had my windows
muted uh okay so I I can I can do my it
so should be fine try talking again
hello uh is he
okay El is talking but we cannot hear
him
ah let me see what kind of output I have
here wait
here uhhuh yeah let's try this hello try
speaking again
hello
output device is changed maybe now it's
on
the
hello um let me check
zoom zoom um sound settings
if you see sound settings tell me where
they
are
here speaker should be
fine okay now it's really weird oh why
is it muted again right try again hello
yes okay somehow it got muted again
okay so you think 30 minutes is good for
you
uh yeah it's fine I mean it's up to you
uh if you want to stop here or like I
can do with less or more time I think
let's let's uh let's stop
here I have some examples of functions
but let's see if you run out of time
then I'll show uh some cool uh examples
of memory leak but otherwise let's go
with lab intro I think that's quite
important to go through that because
there's some funny syntax things that we
were discussing yesterday so let's
um let's do that okay you guys hear well
when he talks okay go ahead El and if
you run out of time if you if you have
extra time if you if we have extra time
I'll have something to
show uh yeah okay so so the audio is
good in the classroom yep hear you
you guys here
yeah uh okay let me just uh share my
entire screen here
um okay you should be able to see can
can you see the like screen clearly in
class as well yes yes yes okay um so the
first askas for lab intro is basically
to Define this rgba pixel class so
that's something we already talked about
in the first lecture how to how to
define
these classes in in
C++
and uh we have these two files here or
already in this lab we have the header
file we have the uh CPP file and there
already like this kind of um little
framework or like yeah it's it's already
the class is already defined here and we
even have this uh the Double inclusion
CS already uh set up here but what we're
missing then of course are
the
um the the properties of the class so so
first thing we we
need the RGB and a values and we wanted
them to be public in this case and what
we wanted was the U in 8 so so what this
means is unsigned integer 8
bit so so it's a 8bit value so so that
and it's unsigned so that means it
doesn't get any negative values it goes
from zero to 255 which is commonly used
for uh describing rgba values
uh okay so then we
can do this definition
for all of
these uh right uh the alpha as
well okay so then what what happens if
we if we want to
compile right
now
uh oh okay okay we actually run into
that issue let's um let's define our
Constructors first as well uh so we
need right we we did this with in
values so so we have the Constructor
with no arguments and then we have the
Constructor with the uh values that
initialize the red green and blue
channels
already and we could name
them like
this uh okay so so right now now now we
have already declared the constructors
so so then
it's yeah yeah oh nice I can actually
make this bigger that's
[Music]
nice
um okay so so nether declared that they
don't actually we didn't actually Define
what these Constructors do yet but but
at least we can compile but now we also
find this
issue uh what is this
8core T the compiler doesn't know but it
has conveniently a suggestion here maybe
you didn't uh
include include this um
Library uh so so we can include that
cstd D
in so so this Library basically includes
this uh type that we like to
use let's try
again
um okay now it's a little better but uh
now we should
also uh
Define our actual Constructors so
let's uh look at the CPP file
then so then here you can see that uh we
have just this line include RGB pixel. H
so that you can essentially think that
that's what like connects these two
files uh to each other so that's already
set up and then
to uh Define these uh
functions so so that's first we
have this
to uh
Define like
the what what what what are we talking
about so so we're talking about like
something that's inside this
rgba uh pixel class and then uh then
this is the name of the Constructor and
of course Constructors don't have uh any
return type so so it just looks like
this no return tag but the same name as
class uh okay so then
for the default Constructor for
us uh well if we didn't declare any like
Constructor in in the first place then
we would have some kind of default
Constructor but like this is our
Constructor of of no arguments and we
want to Define what the
default value should be so so this is
the this is the kind of like simplest
way to uh do things and to like
understand there there is also the
option of using
initializer list which looks a little
bit different but
uh now that we're dealing with like some
like trivial data types and not like
other classes it's not really a big deal
which way you do it and then of
course but but sorry elmary I I actually
forgot to mention in lecture that it's
slightly more
efficient to do it in the initialization
line rather than within the function
within the block of the function because
then less stack is used and yeah and
that's important to remember like if you
really want to optimize everything then
putting in a line is more efficient
because then you don't have to put those
variables on the stack within this curly
bracket at all so much less stack is
used and you can even show the code
where it's signant slow if you do it
many many
times sorry I just forgot to mention it
in lecture so I wanted to put it out
there yeah uh so so it is more optimal
the difference is significantly
larger uh when you're dealing with like
classes as as member uh variables like
like if if all of these were like some
kind of classes or like objects of like
some user defined class for
example uh then it would be much more
efficient to like just directly
initialize it here because otherwise you
would need to like first call the
default Constructor and then start
changing the values uh so so in the CL
in the case of like class objects it's
it's much more important to use the
initializer list but with with like this
kind of trivial data types it's not
really uh that big of a deal and
sometimes you do need like some kind of
logic to it like uh depending on some
kind of
factors um
maybe like you you could have I if
statements here
like if uh if
true uh well that's not really uh a good
example but but that the point is that
you have more control this way but but
when you can do things with initializer
list then then it's a good way to do
things so I can actually just remove all
of that and just keep
these and that's
a good
Constructor okay let's define the other
one as
well the one where
we initialize it with user given values
and and this one you can actually also
do uh the same way right
yep uh so we're going to end up having
like kind of a long line but I guess we
can also split it into
Parts see if the users are going to send
800 instead of 225 you know then uh you
don't check no Checker in the
initialization line right you can yeah
that's true if if we if we use like ins
here yeah yeah then they they might have
like U they might give us bad values um
so I guess I could
also it's fine for now it's okay we just
we're explaining what can go
wrong
yeah
um but that's example of where the
outter grader right El in the outter
grader you could check for good behavior
like this if we were to ask that it
should behave well so that's where they
are when you when you sent your
submissions through love La we actually
going to run this code like wrap it
around with in different test cases and
that's where you could test whether your
Constructors actually do the right thing
right whether you use uh good you know
good rules for writing
code so if you compile and run your code
and it all is fine on your side it
doesn't mean that you run it on all test
cases that we
have but just be warned because
sometimes you may still not pass out a
greater for these kind of
reasons okay yeah very cool yeah so so
in C++ also it's good to note that we we
can we can do line breaks without having
to worry about anything because
uh because because this is not Python
and we always have like some kind of uh
symbols to determine what part of the
code we're dealing with so so if you end
up getting like a really long line then
then generally it's pretty easy to like
split things into multiple
lines uh okay so so now now it
compiles
um and now before even touching the
main function we
can um look at the result also if you're
using the Linux
subsystem and like you're kind of
looking at the files directly here then
it's not going to like automatically
refresh at least it doesn't for me so
then I'm I hitting F5 when I'm expecting
like some new files to be here before I
actually see
them uh okay
so the result is that that we're able to
draw these cross here so so that's
something where you need to have
those uh need to have the rgba pixel
class working with uh good Constructors
but then
there's some things in
the oh go on then
update uh it'll update before I have to
use it again um okay
so so in the main function
then if we look at the structure
here uh so so when we run the program
this is where it's going to actually
like first go in the main function start
executing things so so we load the
sample
image
um and Sample image is this that's kind
of what we already saw except we had the
crosshairs on top of
it uh okay
um and then then we have
overlay which is this text on a black
background and then the first thing we
do is we brighten the
overlay with this uh value
128 okay so let's look at the brighten
function uh so as arguments we have the
original
PNG and we have the amount to uh in
increase the brightness by and you
already have this Loop
here so it's looping through all the
pixels uh in the
image and then we can kind of look uh as
example the this function here how we
can uh how we can kind of access these
pixels so so we can see that this way uh
that there's this
um operator overload load for like using
these brackets where where you can put
the X and Y
coordinates uh to access a pixel there
so so in this case uh you're just kind
of um in inserting
these rgba
pixel objects in into these uh different
pixel coordinates but in this case we
want to modify uh each Channel
uh
separately uh
okay so if we take the original
XI y i uh actually let me let me also
like kind of show where this is coming
from yeah where is the overload is yeah
so if if you look at the
you have all the files here so you can
open the
PNG uh PNG
Doh and and here you start seeing this
uh this operator keyword and then there
always something I promise we'll go in
lectures through operator overloads and
we'll go in details but now is just like
if you had a job in software engineering
company you're just given this code and
like you're surviving right and later
we'll we'll have many Le to cover this
but let's uh let's start now okay go
ahead sorry
El yes so we can find it from here uh so
so this operator and then uh these
arguments are are defined and then what
it returns is pointer to rgba
pixel uh and we don't really need to
look at the definition here we can just
look at the header file and see that
okay this is what it does
this is something that I can do uh I use
this operator with this coordinates and
and does some kind of comment here to
describe uh what it does and and then I
know what I'm going to get out of
it
uh okay so then this should
be uh this should give us a
pointer
uh and
then
hopefully hopefully I'm doing doing this
right now but uh so it should be like
this right so so when it's a pointer and
we want to
access like um property of the object
that the pointer is pointing to then we
can actually use this operator uh so in
this case uh this is used to D reference
the pointer and like that's kind of an
approach that that we can use but then
this is kind of a a shortcut also a
shortcut yes we didn't we didn't teach
it yet yeah that's interesting I should
put it earlier um I'm following what has
been done at University of Illinois but
yeah it's kind of like you have to
figure it out yourself here and then
teach it many things are like that
unfortunately because you can't teach
everything like in the first lecture
there has to be some order but
yeah yeah yeah you can also like do it
by D referencing but uh I'll I'll show
this anyway um but just to like test
that yeah it compiles this way so this
is like a valid way to do things so so
this way we could just like Define
values here but but we don't want to
Define this we want to build our like
brightening logic here so then we can
kind
of uh take this value again and then add
the amount to
it
um okay so so some of you probably know
that that there's going to be like a
little problem with this and I'm going
to show what the the problem looks like
before I fix
it uh
okay it's going to only brighten the
overlay and
then yeah that's actually not going to
show up but I'm going
to brighten
the I'm going to brighten the image
instead so so you can see the uh effect
uh hold
on okay now I'm a little bit confused
why nothing actually changed
make yeah maybe I should do
that
it's still the same
okay
um maybe I'll just
proceed further and I think the issue is
going to come up in a moment anyway uh
okay let's let's leave it like that for
now and then do the uh
Blend images
function uh okay
so we're going to have kind of a
similar logic here where we Loop through
all the pixels this time we
have uh two different pngs as arguments
and we the function is going to return
the first image so that's going to be
the output so so then we modify the
first
image okay so once
again
we can kind of start with this basis
that we're going
to uh modify all of these pixels
individually
so so so one one student uh brought it
up before that like like isn't isn't
this kind of complicated like like we
have to do all of these separately um so
so the thing is if you wanted to have a
simpler way to do things your main
function uh then you would need to edit
your classes to add some kind of
functionality
like like in
the in the rgba pixel class for example
we could Define overloads
for uh
like addition for example like what does
it mean if we have rgba pixel plus
another one uh
the uh comp piler C++ doesn't know
automatically what that's supposed to do
but you could Define it that okay what
that means is that we uh add each of the
like rgba
channels uh like with each
other and then you could kind of make it
easier maybe in your in your main
function so you're going to have to do
everything yourself is the
idea okay so quite simply we can uh do
[Music]
something like
this uh add those two together and
divide by two and something that was
also brought
up um before
is I I've seen some students uh want to
like cast these two different types or
or round the
result uh
but it's not like the
results might turn to like a decimal
number here that that doesn't that
doesn't happen it's going to uh stick to
the same type I mean there can be like
kind of type conversions happening
between uh like our U ins and and ins
for example or like
if
um like we're doing addition here for
example so so if this was limited to uh
255 then then we might have some trouble
so so I think what's happening here is
that it's actually like
using uh like in or something to do this
addition and then it's going to divide
but then the end result is always going
to be u in anyway and and you don't
really have to worry about the uh type
conversions at least in this case I mean
some cases you of course have to
but but it's going to be just fine it's
going to be whole numbers all the way
through let me
call good
all okay and let's remember to have the
correct uh channel for each of these
because that's a like a bug that can
easily happen here where it's like you
you forget this as like cred because you
were copy pasting and then you're
wondering what the result doesn't quite
match
uh okay so now te technically we've done
everything so let's look at the output I
think it wraps around with the B Spain
you should check for yeah yeah yeah I
wanted to show uh this problem
here so so depending a little bit how
how you do things uh you might get this
issue where it's like like why why is
this text so bad or maybe if you're
trying to brighten the background image
then uh you might get some like really
funky colors in the in the sky or
something and and the reason for that is
because because we're using this
uint uh that are 8 Bits
And here what can happen is that if
this value for example is the the value
for Fred in one of the pixels is let's
say 200 and then the amount by which
we're adding is
128 uh then that would be like
328 and we're trying to put that number
into this 8bit
type so what's going to happen then like
that's not going to fit so then what
happens is is that it wraps around uh
and then we start getting like uh low
values all of a sudden so so that's kind
of why the text is
disappearing is
because the text is supposed to be white
but then it's wrapping around and then
it's like
actually just going to kind of
disappear or or if we were applying this
to the background
image then you'll see funky colors
because like everything's kind of going
to be unbalanced because like some of
the colors are going to wrap around and
some are not and and it's going to get
really
weird but how we want this to
behave is that at most this will
increase the value to
255 so again if if this is 200 and this
is
128 then we want the end result to be
mhm and the easiest way to do that is to
use the Min function
which in this case is already going to
be included and we're already using the
namespace
STD uh it's included in the
algorithm yeah library in the standard
Library yeah uh so we can just
use uh use this function
now uh okay
so if we do
this then again if if if here we end up
getting
328 but
then the other argument for the Min
function is
255 then the function is going to return
255 because that's the smaller number
out of these two so then you use the Min
function actually to define the maximum
that you want to get out of this
operation uh it can feel a bit like
reverse thinking maybe that I used the
Min function to define a maximum but uh
that's kind of how it ends up
working so this way you can do all of
this in just three lines you don't need
any uh if statements you don't need
to
uh declare and Define any any other
variables in
between uh you can do everything in in
just three
lines okay and there we go that looks
just about
correct and then if we
also run diff then it doesn't produce
any output which means that the
uh images match
perfectly okay I guess uh
any questions about the question in the
chat there's a question in the
chat yeah I saw that question and then I
was thinking that
honestly I don't think I can provide a
good
answer
no me think that's a good question to
ask on Discord and maybe one of the Cy
guys can yeah I answer that
one okay okay but we are out of time
thank you El was this useful was this
useful so I think it would be a good
practice to do that every Monday for a
lab so that at least we're all clear on
what's going on in the labs
right and it will help uh you have MPS
that are individual so you have to work
on that yourself but if we make sure
that you follow Labs then you get a lot
out of this class because lecture
materials is much more basic it's
important to cover basic stuff it's
important to understand those
definitions
but um then we still cover the labs this
was great El thank you so much okay so
we'll see you um on
Thursday thank you El bye all right see
you bye