this computer okay we're ready to
roll so we will start a little bit with
uh warming up with pointers like last
time and then we'll go into arrays so we
want to understand how to not only store
one element on a heap but chunks of
elements on a heap and how to access
that how to safely ask for memory there
like that and how to safely uh free that
memory okay but we'll start with warmup
and I have announcements first so let's
see announcements we have well you know
what are the deadlines for the deadlines
I hope are very clear we have another
there is a lab due on every Monday night
and then every two weeks there is some
kind of MP machine problem which is
individual
so um very rough
schedule uh I want to make another
announcement so we are learning raw
pointers in these
lectures and they're useful they're also
not safe as you probably noticed from
last time how many uh run how many
different kinds of runtime errors you
can achieve using raw pointers if you
don't have follow the safety rules right
um that doesn't mean that they're not
used in industry they're still
used um it just you have to be very
careful uh when dealing with them
however the with new standards of uh C++
distributions starting with C++ 11 there
are safer pointers that you can use I'm
not going to cover them in lectures but
um we will have an invited uh principal
software engineer from cute who will
come here on 18th of uh April so please
come to that lecture we really want to
have a full room for sure to greet him
because I think he's worried that we
don't have very good attendance anymore
culturally in this University so it's
really important that you guys
come um he is a C++ standards Committee
Member and he's also on your Discord so
he answers your questions if you noticed
he's there I
think I think they look it for the
best you know
why so um It's kind a win-win situation
they help us because um this is the
first pilot run I'm not fresh in C++
it's very good to have people who
actually work on C++ every day and V has
been working with it every day for 30
years so he really knows ins and outs of
everything there and um so please come
don't forget I'll be reminding every
lecture because it's very important to
not miss on that lecture okay so there's
also safer ways of handling arrays than
what I'm going to be doing today and Via
vectors however raw pointers are
important because that's what allows you
to really Access Memory
fast and there's still code in cute and
other companies out there that uses raw
pointers that's why we're learning them
too okay cool so let's do a warmup uh
we'll go through these questions it's
just a warmup so uh I'll start with the
first one it's easy for you guys so what
type of what is the type of Q in this
declaration is it integer pointer is it
integer is it integer pointer
pointer or something else uh these kind
of questions also help you figure uh
kind of have be prepared for the exam
because that's the type of question you
do have in the exam but there will just
very many of them and will give you
limited
time to
answer so
okay Q what's the type of Q we we went
through this last lecture very quickly
but I just wanted to have it what's the
Q it's just a syntax question so Q
is integer not integer pointer a pointer
here or this Asis belongs to the
variable not to the type Okay so p is
integer pointer but Q is just an integer
so this is the correct answer cool the
compiler would catch you here though so
this would be something that compiler
would be on your side and you would not
you would figure it out it's not one of
those Insidious bugs okay what's the
output here to the standard out of this
little
program so this is just for you guys to
to figure out chase the pointers we'll
be chasing lots of pointers today so
that's just a
one 6
six 6
six any
other options the first line is correct
the second line is not you're printing
out six here which is okay so what do we
have an integer pointer an integer
you give P the value of x's stack
variable address that's fine so whenever
you follow the pointer you're actually
changing the value of x now so X will
become six but what is p what is p
what's its
type pointer yes what its value some
gibberish address an address so you'll
have six and then you're right that
there will be no end of line
here so there will be no end of line
there will be six followed by some heex
number which is a an address okay
cool
fine uh okay which of the following
statements will print the value of x we
know that this prints the value of x
that's
great
let's s so that's s for sure so you can
pick that
right this is an address so Mo what's
this good do reference P so take the
value of P which is X's address and
print what is that address which is X so
X and s p is x value good what about
this one that's an interesting thing so
what you do here you take X he takes its
address and then follow that address
with s which is X so the value is X good
what is this well this is X and it's the
same so good p is an
address this is an address of P not of
an
S here this is the the value of P which
is address of X but this is the address
of P the address of p is different from
address of X good so anything else that
uh so this one is address of P follow
that it's P's value which is X's address
but not x what about this one follow P
which is s take its address which is
address of s and then print out the
value that address X that's
X
okay uh I maybe one of this is what is
this an address of P follow it P
no is this one no that you
can can I do that uh is this one no this
is p so yeah I think we followed all of
them um yeah I think that's it so this
is address of s value address so this is
good this is not correct right so the
all of the above are okay and this one
is not and bow not
okay maybe I missed some but I'll look
at it carefully then uh oh are you
curious about any of those because I
have a program for
that would you like to really see what's
going on
here I think that's interesting which
one bugs you is there something that
bugs you there you
go were you not sure about any of these
you think one of them that I said is not
an address is an address I mean is a
value of P of X that let's put it
there so clearly X is fine right what
about an address of s and you follow the
reference that address and print out the
value that should be S right so we're
going
to uh g++ my zero
program
there and run it good right now you see
this is X or the address and then follow
it and this is the we printed out G
which is the uh address the address of X
the value of p is the address of X can
you take address two times
[Music]
then because the address has to be with
the variable so you can do that do you
want to see what
happens it will it will yell at
you can do that so it expects a variable
it cannot take the
address okay so that's cool anything
else you want to try here so do you see
I could have done it many times like
this
now
right kind of operation that kind of
undoes itself right and then look since
this is an address of P of X I could
just put P there and then again like
fold it
over okay so that's cool um so let's do
that yeah okay good warm up good let's
go back to our
slides if you have any questions please
post them here what is the result of
compelling running this code so that's
the warm up last time again look I have
declared pointers two of them are
Pointers I have asked for memory for one
of them and that's on the Heap and then
another one got the same value so they
both point to the same Heap variable
that doesn't have a value yet but I
reference one of the pointers and put
value there and then I delete that free
memory I free that memory the heat
memory but I have dangling pointers
number pointers fine I still want to see
what's there I shouldn't be able to but
I told you that C++ will not hold your
hand you can still do it it just can
lead to undefined Behavior because that
memory is freed and you're accessing it
so let's see what's going to be
undefined behavior on my particular
system so I'm going to show you that
code I think it's in one is that the
same code right I'm going to dreference
it and see what's there although I freed
that memory but then moreover I'm going
to Der reference and put nine in there
and then print it out
again what do you think might happen do
you have any like intuition what's going
to
happen some random numbers and then
nines yep that's it very good let's do
that
d++ one okay
there you go very good so ah what am I
going to do about it right what am I
going to do about it so we actually in
lab debug please correct me because I
can say some other I think in lab Lab
debug we teach you how to catch these
memories with a special tool that is
called uh address
sanitizer and I'm not going to go
through that in lectures but I'm just
going to show you that it's not that
difficult to use it so I'm going to
compile now the same program but with
address sanitizer so I'm going to give a
flag I think it's F
sanitize equals
address and then do that and I want to
show you that although if you just
compile and run the program nobody yells
at you here if you run sanitizer that
guy will check all of the memory and it
will
say did I say it
right oh yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah sure
okay okay that's fine yeah okay look
what it
says it says the
delete here I think what's it he use
after free you freed your memory and
you're going to use it so there you go
you got your slap there you go you can
do that you can now Trace where is the
problem and the entire lab debug is on
this so we'll plant a bunch of the bad
behavior kind of problems in the
code if you remember the rules safety
rules you'll immediately spot where you
have to put delete or assign null to the
pointer but if you kind of forget you
still can use sanitizer and Trace where
you you did something that's wrong okay
I cre lot memory
very good yeah yeah it's not lab we
doing lab debug now right it's La the
lab debug is now we have you're doing
now you don't need that yeah we give you
many tools and we don't talk much about
memory yet so but soon so next Lab is
that and you'll if you read the lab it
explains you how to use this Tools in
details uh but here is just just like a
a
teaser okay so now last one on look
again I did something wrong what did I
do wrong in this
code I'm doing it in the loop
now I am doing 20,000 loops and I'm
asking for a string on the heat 20,000
times and that string has a million of
characters and what do I forget to
do fre Theory free the memory yeah so
what's going to happen what is the
result of running and compiling this
code what do we call it what's the term
what's a good term for that memory leak
you want to see what happens when you
have a memory leak so we need to do g++
Loop and here is my let me just double
sure that yeah see I don't delete string
right so I want to
run
nothing happens it just slow you think
oh yeah because I have such you know so
many uh iterations in the loop maybe
that's why it's
slow but no it's not because of that
it's because you know you have a problem
there so let's fix it and we know the
rules of good behavior so I need to I
have my somewh yeah here let me just
open uh what is two Loop yeah
we I know that I need to delete
s right what else should I do it's
better to assign s to null but in this
particular case I know that it goes out
of scope so I'm not going to do that but
we will talk about scope very soon so
let's see so
now if I do g++ 2 Loop it
compiles and if it if I run
it it's not slow just a little bit so so
that's what memory Le is you saw it it
just it hands there you know you can run
it may help you during execution time
and just say hey you're out of memory
but sometimes it will not it will just
be slow it may even say done if you did
it less times and you wouldn't even know
that there is a memory leak unless you
use the sanitizer so our friend
sanitizer let's do that again so let me
um let me compile it with uh
sanitizer and run
it oh it's
looping but I have
some or maybe you can just make the
number smaller so yes yes yes but I did
have an output at home which is weird
maybe after a while it'll tell you but
yeah let's do then less iterations
that's interesting that I don't see
anything here but you know your your
program is hanging for sure so um
there yeah so thank goodness right there
are some tools where you can tell that
there's detected memory leaks and you
can count them
and so fine that's warm up so we kind of
we went over what we already talked
about last time
and now we are switching to the new
lecture and we will be talking about
arrays but let me start first talking
about just different ways the um so
please remember that we have a different
um slideer for this
now yeah
so I want you to look at this two pieces
of code and tell me what is difference
functionally and now yes now you can go
to your slides you're out you can write
on your um print outs because that's
what we will be working with we're done
with the warm up so tell
me what is the functional differences
what are the functional differences if
there any between these two pieces of
code when I compile and run
it so here's the question for you too
you can try to yeah the user memories
different executions and the output to
the terminal will be different right
that's very good both of them will
comine compile just fine so it seems
like when we run this program on the
terminal one will print
out hello with an exclamation mark and
another one will print hello with a
question
mark okay so let's Trace what these
codes do because they also so what what
is also correct as you rightfully
pointed out is that the use of memory is
going to be different so behind the
scenes they also handle memory
differently right so what's going on
here well let's start tracing the
program to really see what's going hap
what's going on with the program control
so what is going on in terms of
execution line by line so when the main
function starts
first the control is given to this line
and that line calls to
function fun function fun right so then
the program control is switched to
function fun and that's where it starts
with this curly brace here and the first
line is executed and that
initializes the variable s of type
strain on this stack so it declares it
and initialize it in one line right so
we have the stack here and somewhere
there a variable with name S Type string
is given value hello with an exclamation
point that's
good and
then uh that is printed out right so on
the stream on the cender out we'll see
hello
uh the next line is the end of the
function the curly braces are closed and
that's when something important happens
so the system thinks aha I know exactly
what to
do this function ended therefore all of
the stack variables in this scope I'm
going to take
back so s is released back to the use by
the system s is gone and it's all
determined by this curly braces so s
goes out of scope and out of Stack
system takes it takes that memory back
and then it gives the control back to
main right after that
line and uh the main ends okay so that's
really nice because you don't have to do
worry about anything there is no new or
delete inside it's all happening on the
stack and me and memory-wise the system
handles stack so let's look at another
function at the second function that um
is not too much different except that
how it handles memory so again M main
starts first line the function the
programmatic control program control is
given to function fun it starts with the
first line the first line declares
variable
s of typ string pointer so it's a
pointer
and also initializes it to this memory
address that is on the Heap so there is
stack there is Heap so some memory
address memory of size
strain is allocated at some memory
address no value is given so whatever is
there we call it garbage is there but
that memory address is given to S as the
value 2.2 right then
you excuse me we reference
S and give that variable on the
stack value hello with a question mark
then we print
out the point T of
s and then we delete s so we do all the
right things we say okay we know we ask
for that memory and a heat with new so
we responsible we're going to give it
back to the system so the system can
reuse that heat memory responsibly
everything is fine
right so then the system goes to this
last line which is the curly
braces which means that it does the same
thing it says okay I know exactly what
to do the fun has ended all of the local
variables in that scope I'm going to
take back that stack memory so what are
those
variables what are the variables on the
stack in this situation address so this
variable s that value is that address so
yes this memory on the stack goes back
to the system the system takes it back
right here and then we go we exit
function fun so fun is over function fun
is over and we here in main does that
make sense so do you see that there is
much more work going on here because
there's one variable on the heat that
you need to manually give back to the
system after asking for that memory
manually as well while as the system
handles it as is on the stack the system
gives that memory and takes it back upon
Declaration of the variable and upon the
it exi in the scope of function
yeah so can we assign the pointer as to
no or yeah that's very good question you
walk right into something that I wanted
to ask do we have to do it here we know
that's the right thing to do that's an
extra operation though because instead
of this memory address at that point
you'll put another
zero but s goes out of scope right
immediately after that so s is gone no
there will be no handling dangling
pointer because it's gone system will
take it
so that's where problem comes because
the good rules tell you you should do it
but if you're a very experienced
programmer and you know what you're
doing you know that this is an extra
line of code and an extra operation so
that takes time that's your call so
that's something that now that's that's
out of my scope of how I know C++ you
should ask you like okay what do they do
are there situations where they really
would need to save time even on
something like this or do they always
follow the good rules I don't know I
know that definitely in my experience we
had situations where we would count
everyone everything matters
[Music]
how can I find the hello
again you you can't so it's gone there
oh hello is gone so hello is given back
to the system right
here but guess what if you put as s
there again maybe there will be still
hello maybe some garbage you don't know
but you shouldn't so you should
and that's why s equals null would be
good good rule of
behavior and and and that's why C++ is
not a safe language because this kind of
things may lead to many problems if you
don't know what you're doing okay I
think I have a couple of questions for
you what are the advantages then of
using heat at all like in this situation
versus sta like do you see an advantage
here or maybe disadvantage like just
just speculate you can of course
speculate here in class as
well just raise your
hand do you see any advantage should we
what should we do in this situation
what's
better like in this particular code
what's more
efficient none what did do we just do it
all in
vain yeah so in this particular code
this is more efficient if you have to
compare to this is more efficient you
there are less operations you just do it
on stack the system takes it back over
there you do one variable is on stack
and another one on the keep and you have
to do more operations to just clean it
all up right so it's less efficient
stack is easier to write yeah so
um when you can use stack use stack
that's the that's kind of the point of
this code that if you do not have too
much to store too much to ask then you
stack that's
fine however if this was I don't know
encyclopedia of some sort maybe you
would consider putting on the heat just
because and maybe you wouldn't want to
remove it out of the Heap right away
either you would want to pass that
pointer somewhere to reuse it then you
need to use uh Heap so there are many
different situations but the main idea
is that if it's small amount of memory
you
stack if it's large objects then you
will consider only then you will
consider using the
heat stack is easier and stack is better
if you can get away with that yeah
that's very good but the Heap is larger
so you can put larger objects there yeah
so very good very good
answers um oh yeah that's see we yes
that okay we answered that why didn't I
put it it doesn't matter in the
situation but um and yet it's bad
behavior on my
side okay yeah so what about the uh
execution time is the execution of the
stock or keep memory code the
same it'll be a little slower for the he
just because there are two more
operations yeah yeah a little slower but
again if you had it depends on the size
though and how many times you do it so
in this particular situation that code
on the he is little but very little very
little um
okay now now we'll look
at different kinds of objects not just
primitive types but objects and what
happens with them when we assign one to
another so what happens to larger kind
of objects across this assignment
operation okay let's do
that okay so I'm going to set this all
up with this type now it's not primitive
type it's userdefined type that is class
space and you can see that it has only
three member variables one is bull
primitive type done so we're talking
about students they have names so
another private member is name of type
string not quite primitive type but
defined in centered Library so you can
think of it as a primitive type kind of
so it behaves really nicely was
distributed with every distribution of
C++ out there so pretty good and then we
have this picture of the student which
is PNG
and as you can see it's not a pointer
it's a PNG so maybe all of it is on the
stack we don't know quite but maybe I
mean we only see this we don't see how
they implemented because we only see
what's provided in ph. right so this is
the interface of our class so we're not
exactly sure what's going on here but it
wouldn't be wrong to assume that it's
all on the step that the whole image all
pixel by pixel stuff is on the step
so not really well set up but it's on
purpose because let's see what happens
to it so then I declare
two objects A and B on the
stack and the next line calls
for initialization of B so I have a
question for you does anybody have a
name starting with b
here what is a finish name that starts
with B is there a finish name that
starts with
B ber yeah good okay baa is it Double T
or one Bera I love it okay so that's
student Berta right there so we're going
to initialize B Berta she assumes she's
happy because fins are the happiest
people on Earth
so and she's not done she's still a
student okay cool so I initialized B and
as you can see it's all on stack here
now I'm going to say a equals to be and
here where the rule comes by default in
C++ assignments
are
assignments so that's very important
assignments
are
memberwise I mean I'm writing it and it
takes time on purpose because it's
member Wise by value you which means
it's going to take time so a strain is
going to copy itself and you know this
is not a long stren so that that's not
bad but this member memberwise by value
so me this member is going to be
copied by
value the phas PNG is going to be copied
by value and
booleans they also know how to copy
themselves by value so the question is
is how do they know how to copy
themselves this objects because this is
a string so hopefully STD is implemented
the way that strings know how to copy
themselves bullan probably too but PNG
how do we know it's going to copy
Faithfully the
image hopefully right because we are not
writing PNG we are using PNG here so we
should assume that whoever wrote PNG
will write perfect fin finally defined
operation for copying okay so we have to
assume that if you take a class it's
well implemented okay cool but as you
can see this may take time
right and then if we go to the next line
we say a set name to n now so what does
that mean we take object
a and we rewrite the name to
n and then
and probably not difficult to imagine
that if you say B get name what
happens what gets printed
out or whatever like what's the value of
that get
name it's still Bera right it's not an
it's Bera because B will print out
its uh name okay any questions so far so
good right seems fine so we can think
now that A and B are independent copies
of each other but we of course change
the name these are maybe two students
they have different names but they still
look alike right because we didn't
really change how they look like the P&S
are the same okay so now let's contrast
this Behavior with this Behavior instead
of declaring faces face objects I'm
going to declare face
pointers so C is a face pointer
I declare it that means on the stack C
is given a place an address and an
uninitialized pointer right so so far
it's uninitialized pointer we better
initialize pointers because we know it
can lead to bad behavior D is the same
it's on the stack with not like not good
uh value yet but we're going to
initialize and let's put let let me make
sure that it's clear I should have put
this initial both the pointer and where
it's pointing so let's initialize
pointer to get this
memory and let's initialize whatever is
the reference D is so whatever that
memory is whatever that face is so let's
come up with a good finish name that
starts with
d d David David okay cool David is he
happy he's a fin right so happy and not
done no cool so we initializes both the
pointer and the um the value the the
face it's pointing to cool now I'm going
to look what's going to happen through
across this assignment statement it's
member Wise by value so what are the
values and members of c and
d just the other they're just pointers
so they're just one block in the memory
that holds an address so it's going to
get copy it from D to C which means C is
just going to point to the same face
right cool so then if I say C set name
I'm effectively de referencing C and
removing David and putting Carlos in
there and then if I do ref refence D and
ask for name of D now what is
that it's Carlos now right so do you
like
it
h yeah so this is the reason why in
Python one you just compare to arrays
between each other and change one of the
arrays the other ARS arrays changing in
I know that in Java this is Java
Behavior I don't know about python is
that python Behavior by by default too
yeah I think
so it's
like it can be a bit unclear like if
you're dealing with pointers or not
because it's not really like visible to
the user but in some cases like
especially with strings it's very common
that s languages only St the string in
one place yeah or or array I mean
strength
areic yeah so but in Java that's the
Java Behavior so it seems like python
behavior and
pointers in C++ but not objects in
C++ so that's the distinction it's very
important to know what you're doing of
course because clearly this is
completely two different behaviors right
two different functionalities and
sometimes you'll want to make copies
sometime it's it's sometimes you can say
deep copy but deep copy is not in this
case it's deep copy but sometimes
they're are different levels like what
if the is a pointer then you get the
memory address copy but not the actual
PNG but then so then the Deep copy would
mean that you vot down the the next step
and copy that as
well uh anyways that's the
picture now what's with the syntax do
you see the difference do you see that
syntax is slightly I just want to point
out that
c and an arrow is exactly the same as
saying the reference C and take a member
a sub member that's equivalent just
syntax so you can use one or another
that's why I use it
here anyway so any questions about it
questions firstly are the brackets
necessary brackets where in C in C plus
see here uh so I always have to look up
you know what I should have looked it up
this time now I forgot this um press
like you have to learn what goes first
which operation and here for clarity I
put this maybe you don't need to but
please double check I don't remember you
need to in this case you need to
right it's like round brackets and no
other brackets no no no no other
brackets yeah if you're talking about
square brackets that's next slide we're
going to be talking
about arrays yeah okay good thank you
and the second question is about this
bully and done what's the point of
this
general just an example of like you use
some code there will be some private
members sometimes you don't know why
they are there just like that just to
have something I think here it's the
case of a primitive type and almost
primitive type and not primitive type at
all so
yeah I don't think so right is it it the
same yeah I don't know uh so this is
like sometimes post it on on SL on uh
Discord I don't know I think
it's we can do real quick run and
see I don't think what it even compile
let's
see ahuh no it doesn't compile sorry
it's it's something that's different
langage I think but you you cannot do
that yeah yeah yeah yeah
so
no but yeah oh right right right is that
what oh yeah oh there's a bug on my
slide right is that what you're
saying that has been there for years for
decades you found a bug on my slide that
has been there for decades and nobody
ever asked
it okay cool uh however you know what I
could have done something like this I
could have defined Ty Boolean to name it
in C++ you can redefine any type and
name it anything which I'll be using in
like here I think four flower right here
see type Define I will call flower in to
kind of pretend that I have a fancy
class flower but they just in so
technically you should have called it
you know somewhere maybe that it was
would be
redefined okay that's why C++ code
sometimes it's so difficult to read
because you don't know like some fancy
name could be just an integer that was
redefined you know any anything can be
renamed okay
cool
now okay which code is slow didn't we
already talk about yeah no we didn't
okay which code is faster here I we kind
of already we kind of
know oh no sorry the question is there
or did I jump the question hold on yeah
let's answer this and then there was a f
question about faster SL uh but let's
answer this okay where are the variables
a b c d so I'm talking about this
variable this variable this variable and
this variable where are they looking at
their
declarations on the
stack C and D is also on the stack right
you you see that C and D are on the
stack the point of variables it's where
they point to they their point T is not
right but C and D are on the stack
they're not in the keep so this is not
correct okay and this this is not
correct so all on the stack very good I
think I have to go to previous slide
because I had which code is faster let's
look at
that yeah because here we just copying
that hex number from one variable to
another we this here we might be copying
strings and even pixel by pixel pngs
okay so Cals d
uh one last question where is the point
T of c and d located so where is
this the thing is it could be either
okay it could be either on the Heap or
on the stack I didn't say that I like
there is D equals new face I didn't say
that maybe I would say d equals the
address of
a and then this whole thing would be
just a on the stack okay so could be
either so the correct answers could be
either
okay okay now we are going to
erase still have some good time because
I have something interesting in the end
so let's talk about first static aray so
static arrays let me make sure I don't
forget anything I wanted to point out
okay guess so let's see I'm going to
make this new declaration now you see
there's some new syntax square brackets
so once the uh system will see this line
it'll say okay you're asking you're
declaring a variable with name X Type
integer but you just don't you don't
want just one check of memory you want
to have size of five elements chunk and
how do does it know that it's size five
between the square brackets right so
you'll say okay I know what to do the
system will say yeah I can do it I will
give you a whole chunk of Stack memory
so we're talking about static arrays
that's how you define a stat declare a
static array so it's going to be on the
stack so it's going to give you the
whole chunk of five elements all of them
type integer so these are
s what's subsequent or successful one
after another addresses in
memory and they are they're all named X
but the first element is called
X plus zero
steps so the first Chunk in memory the
second one is the second or x + one step
in memory X x + 2 steps x + 3 steps and
x + 4
steps so it's five elements okay
everything is fine all of them are
integers right so now that's what the
system will do and it's all in stack
okay and so now you can see that I can
maybe set up a four Loop i = 0 I less
than 5 the size I ++ and and I can
initialize all of these values s i
equals say 2 * I is that okay and then
the values so we essentially we are D
referencing X you can think of it as a
pointer although you shouldn't maybe but
or you can say that I'm just stepping
through all of the elements in this Chun
of memory in this array and I'm setting
up two times those steps two * I
values okay
do you like
it so what
else I have a question for you so that's
it so what's good about it if you were
to set up some kind of function or there
was some kind of scope with the um curly
braces over there that upon seeing this
end of the um scope for X the system
would take it back and you wouldn't have
to so it will just be taken back for the
system you maybe set up a different
array or whatever on the stack so that's
very nice
questions I have a question for
you the question is can we change the
size of static
arrays and if you ask like which one is
correct and that gives that describes
the worst dis the mo the biggest
disadvantage of using static arrays yes
you're right so the size of the static
array cannot be determined during
execution so you cannot say oh I'll just
ask the user to tell me what's the size
or I'll ask a sensor the sensor will
tell me something and I'll initialize
the array based on that value no you
can't you have to know in
advance you you wrote that program
you'll know the size of the array will
be five right at compilation time you
should know the the number so this is
correct answer and that's the
disadvantage okay fine so that's why uh
Dynamic arrays are much more uh useful
yeah so can we rewrite the values inside
the array yeah yeah yeah yeah you just
say s square brackets whatever put
it okay but I'll show you what can go
wrong of course but uh let's talk about
then Dynamic aray so one thing to point
out is static sounds kind of like stack
so so it's easy to remember that those
are arrays on stack and this is dynamic
array which is on the Heap so you don't
have to know the size ahead of time you
can ask you can get that information
during the run of the program you can
even ask the user to input the the
number during the execution and then the
size the array will be set up so then in
order to set up this array you just
declare a pointer and we talked about it
last time you just declare a pointer so
just a regular pointer but the way you
ask for memory is different so if you
know some size or ask for size then you
ask for memory for this pointer in a
different way so not just new int
because that would be just one variable
you're asking for a chunk of memory of
size of size
size because there's the square brackets
and then the system will say oh fine
okay so you have this uh X already
declared with some uninitialized pointer
so then new
will um the system will say okay I'll
give you the size of three elements on
the Heap memory
each of type
integer values so far garbage but this
beginning this first block of this Heap
memory will be given as the value to
this pointer right so that memory
address on the Heap will be given as the
value for x through this
assignment and then the names of this
Heap variables of course they don't have
names but we can do reference X to
access them and you can say the first
one is at zero that is zero steps away
from the beginning or the first variable
over there in the uh
block the second one is s + one step and
the third one is s plus two steps then
you could initialize them using some
kind of loop like this so then each SI
is is given the value I + 3 so you put
three four five in
here but this is heat memory right so
that means if you ask for it with a new
you should release it free it using
delete the only thing is that you have
to also say that it's not just s that
you're freeing but the entire block so
you use square brackets here
because if you don't put square brackets
what
happens only the first element will be
freed and this will cause memory leak
right so you really have to tell the
system no the whole block that I asked
for pleas
freedback okay any questions so now
we'll have a lot of yeah so first thing
are the addresses of the all elements
like sequential yes and also can you
access one one of the elements without
holding the X so just using the
address if you know it it'll be
different on each architecture or
whatever yeah but sure but you usually
don't know it
yeah is there any
um Pro of using C style arrays like this
Dynamic instead of vectors array not
vectors because vectors are slow they
allate memory dynamically but
array C C++ array it should be exactly
the same
performance right so what about
um it yes use that whenever you can but
uh you'll see that you can create much
more complex data structures using ra uh
raw uh arrays so for example
what if you have an array of
arrays make it
array all of them different
sizes so when we are talking about
double yeah so this is a raw access to
the memory and it's it may be useful but
yes by no means and I think that's the
question that you should ask to v as
well when
is it safe and why are these still used
because I'll show you how many problems
we can have with this um and that's
something the scope of this I don't know
really but I think it all depends on the
projects and I just don't have that
experience like when is one more
important when is it crucial to have
this kind of assess to
memory okay I would love to have that
discussion Discord but I think what we
list said all also that he wants you to
learn the bad ways because then he'll
come and say these are the good ways and
he'll be like feeling Victorious about
it um well it's also not that these are
bad but more fundamental like is that
iover
yeah but let me show you some examples
of what kind of structures we can create
with this and then you can uh see but uh
first I wanted to really run into
problems
of static versus dynamic or sorry in in
all sorts of problems okay so please
look at this code do I have a uh yeah
please look at this code and tell
me what will happen what is the result
of compiling and running this
code okay
I don't think I did I still print it out
oh
[Music]
yeah yeah there's an error in D memory
you only delete the first very good so
what do you call
that yeah time eror it's a Memory leak
for sure right yeah it's a runtime error
so that's good um will it crash though
sure
no it will not it will not be helpful uh
the address sanitizer will be helpful
but um if you don't do that just memory
L now so you're already here so we
didn't delete the right we just deleted
the first element then I still do
reference it which you know is no
surprise for you that I still can go and
access all of those but now I'm doing
the static
array and look at what I'm doing I'm
treating it as if it's a d
right I'm going
to so what's going to happen there what
do you think it doesn't
compile oh no it
compiles brush oh no it
want because of two things yeah it's a
runtime error so I have this code you
would think right that something would
be
bad more four I think it's four four no
it's three three three okay so let's
see yeah oh of course I didn't set to
null pointer because if I set this stain
to the null pointer right here I
wouldn't have a problem
of if I deleted it properly and set as
to null then this would only this was C
this would cause a segmentation fault
which is what we want kind of that's
better we shouldn't you reference the
the array or go to the array once You'
read it uh
here it's a stack array so you cannot
delete it it's just going to U misbehave
so let's see do you want to see what
happened and here I just say even in
this program like this shouldn't be
allowed right you shouldn't
be your referencing why but let's see
what happens so we need to do
g++ actually let's yeah let's not do
sanitizer yet because we know there's a
problem so is it three right
three let me put it side by side with
the code so what is happening
here this is the first array
right
do I have different
code two *
I strange why is it one two
three so it just garbage
right because it should be uh 0 2 6
right I'm initializing it to
that right so I don't know why it's one
2 three but who cares
right okay what is interesting is
this wait uh let me get I'm not
following my
my my
um so the
first oh and let me really make sure
that we have the same code oh right
right see because I I I was playing with
it at home that's why so I'm not
printing out this so let's see what's
there I'm only printing out the five
elements of the static array so let's
Rec compile
rerun aha so that's what happens to the
memory after it's been freed and we are
trying to access it the first element is
this the second is this third four third
that's it so that's what happens and uh
address sanitizer would catch it so if
we run address sanitizer it would say
hey you didn't delete the whole thing
and if you put it to null pointer we
would get second so that's cool so now
let's fix it we deleted all whole thing
and we don't want this anymore we don't
want a print out we already know that
dangling pointers can cause all sorts of
problems so now let's just concentrate
on the static array I'm going to
recompile I'm going to
run so I am just showing you that the
referencing and using square brackets is
the same thing here so I'm going to
print out all five elements the first
three are fine because they're just I +
one of the static array and here is a
part of Stack that you're not supposed
to touch but this will let you it just
will let
you how could you catch it do you think
uh address sanitizer would help
you it will say maybe that will warn you
right it will so that's why I'm going to
um
sanitize equals address let's
see ah see so it'll catch you and what
do you think is the warning
there stack buffer overflow you're
touching the stack that you're not
supposed to so thankfully these tools
will be on your side uh when to to catch
any kind of memory problems thank
goodness right
so there's some tools to to let you know
that this is not allowed however
syntactically there's no
problem
okay yeah but it will compile and run
just fine yeah it what it seems like
right but but it's
around so now we have still half an hour
we're going to do something crazy and
that's when
um
that's where we can do crazy things with
this
um arrays so of course if you can have a
single array why not have double array
you know have a more dimensional arrays
and then if I look at my guardian. so if
I look at the interface of some
class let me go back um it can tell you
that one of the
private variables is a double array the
name is plot the type is flower so maybe
some kind of class that was nicely
implemented some flower so they want to
plot or plant a plot of flowers right
and it's a double array so you have no
idea how it's implemented but you can
guess right what exactly is going on so
I have a question for you what do you
think how how do you think it's
implemented so when there's some kind of
Constructor we didn't talk about
Constructors yet but when
this me memory is
arranged in which one of these ways is
it arranged so that's a question for you
on the next
slide which one of this is a uh valid
option for
initializing the
memory for the
plot
question
say where does it say in plot oh yeah
sorry flower plant I forgot yeah first I
had integers I'm like oh no I should
just use flowers because it's yeah I I
apologize over here it's flower plot so
this the same thing yeah yeah yeah good
good
catch but you know that for me flower is
just in because I Ty de like that okay
any any option four
takers well it turns out all four are
valid it just may not be really
necessarily
clever but they're all valid all four
are possible options for this for the
implementation or for
memory uh handling Arrangement
Arrangement so let's start with plot
with option one so if I said that plot
is double pointer and then I say okay
for plot give me a new memory address
but just one variable of type flower
pointer
that's okay I'm not asking for an array
I'm just asking for one so then I got
that with this first
assignment that's on the heat that new
flower pointer is on the heat and then
for that flower pointer I can just do
reference it with plot through plot and
ask for just another block which is T
flower totally valid I don't know why
would I ever have a pointer to a pointer
like that why would I need it but it's
valid and
therefore um oh I think the question
here is how many flowers would be there
in this
plot or this kind of way of initializing
it and how would we
access uh
that that
flower
M so in that in this kind of way it
would be just one object but we would
access it through this kind of strange
sentence of getting the first element in
the first the first pointer and the
second
pointer or you could just call it
asteris asteris plot as well either way
it's fine because we know that asterisk
dot is the same as square
brackets okay pretty
cool now uh
oh yeah I think I didn't mention it I
didn't really say what is the
equivalence
but so what I wanted to I did want to
mention that
plot um it was it would be better to go
back to the arrays oh yeah I can show it
right here I think in
my yeah so so B please remember that
square brackets accessing some element
of the array is the same thing as de
referencing that name but like this many
steps away so the synta syntax is the
same right you just say okay take that
memory address and go this many steps
down the array and then um you reference
it give the value there so this syntax
is the same I forgot to mention
okay so do you like
this no but nevertheless it's it's valid
right so let's draw the picture of this
situation essentially the plot
here is a
pointer to a flower
pointer so this is plot you referenced
once and only this is flower
now where I can put value I put a rose
there see and this is either plot 0
0 or you could say asteris asteris
plot but that's the picture and here the
plot is on the stack but everything else
is on the
Heap okay you can see that it's going to
get crazy
right
now second option how many flowers are
in this second option and how to assign
a value value to
each and then we'll draw a picture for
this
scenario b or c b or c clearly it's
seven elements you can see that so what
happens is that I for plot pointer I ask
for an array
right and each element of that array is
going to be plot
I but all of those are going to be just
pointers to one flower because I didn't
ask for an array here I just asked for
one flower right which means that there
are seven elements and
all but all of them have
just
one one flower pointer but so in order
to access them you can do reference
plots with I steps but then only take
one first step you could also say
asterisk plot
eye okay so they the answer is
C let's draw a picture for this
situation
it is a valid situation though
so I don't remember which one we have I
think we have just double array in U one
of the MPS I think so all of this is
useful for one of the MPS I just don't
remember one of which one is them Comon
MP okay so we will say that here
plot asks for an array
of size seven all of them are flower
pointers so we'll need to initialize
them and ask for memory for them which
we do in a loop and each of them is not
an array it's just a flower so just one
point one one
flower uh
variable which then we could access like
this as you can see in a loop we could
say the I plot
element do reference that you can say
zero then to Der reference the first
element and put a values whatever you
want
there so that's the picture do you like
this
yeah it's it's possible that you would
need something like that
right okay cool
next okay now we have case three or
option
three that's just a normal regular kind
of
um double array
right so this is pretty useful to what
to hold in like matrices I know what are
applications for these pgs could be like
that right with pixels so okay okay so
which one is that that's a d That's
pretty straightforward much more
straightforward right B is not the case
in this because we will have oh my God
and I swear to God I wanted to put 49
here and it's the number of elements is
49 in this case
right do you see
that and I don't know how it didn't get
updated so the slide is mess stop but
let's go to the answer so that we fix it
okay so the answer let's see let me fix
it so the possible option should have
been 49 here
49 and the correct answer is D and let's
see what happens here plot is given an
array and they they address to the
array of size seven right through this
first line and all of them are flower
pointers which is fine because flower
pointer can be either a flower itself or
a pointer to a flower or a pointer to an
array of flowers and in this case it's
not just one flower like in the last
case but it's an array of flowers so
each of them in the loop are given
through new an array of size seven as
well
which means that we have 49 flowers and
each and single one of them can be
accessed by first calling the row I and
then
the colum J so you can imagine that I
could set up another loop for J equal 0
J less than 7
j++ and I then I could initialize
plot the E column
the J sorry the I row jth column to rows
again and I would put R there in every
single one of them okay so that's
um that's useful right this is quite
useful and um now the last
one this is I think the weirdest
one so now what if I say that if I
initialize it like
that which one is left yeah B that's the
only one left right anyway so that's
kind of easy but let's see what happens
with this initialization so I have
flot
plot and I ask for
just one variable I'm not asking for an
array I just just want an address of
flower pointer which the system will say
okay I'll give you this is a new
variable of type flower
pointer it's not initialized yet but
I'll give you the address to plot to
hold it so the PT is created but doesn't
have value yet so now I'm going to give
value to the point T the reference plot
and say oh that should be a pointer so
far as an initialized so give me with
new a chunk of memory of size
seven of flowers right okay why would I
ever do
that I don't know I don't know but then
um the thing is that plot zero is this
guy or equivalently you could just say
plot but then you would have to um keep
here you have to put parenthesis it's
important because otherwise by default
the other one will be taken so
um then you say I equals to row so
that's
equivalent okay H you like
it any of them are
useful okay so the bad thing is that you
have to free
memory and that's where we have a bug in
one of the MPS because we'll create this
array for you and you'll have to free it
and you'll have to appropriately go
through the loop of free because you
could see that asking for a memory we
had some Loop set up sometimes sometimes
we did sometimes we didn't which means
that freeing you also will have to do it
through the loop of some sort maybe but
let's start with
this okay so for the first case where it
was just pointer to pointer is there any
proper way of deletion in any of
[Music]
this well can you please
reconsider there's one good way for this
one there is place there's
one mean remember for for the option one
we had
plot holding a flower pointer folding a
a flower so this is the reference plot
so how do we delete this memory can you
tell me the order where should we start
what if I say delete
PL then what
this memory gets freed and lost so we l
lose this
forever and we we we have a d pointer if
we don't assign to know so that's not
good so first we should the reference
plot and say oh we ask a new there was a
new statement for the this element the
reference plot so therefore there should
be delete of that too so you call delete
plot
and then this memory is
free then you can say oh now it's safe
to delete plad and this one is free so
you kind of the way in which you ask for
memory you should go in the backward
order you first ask for plot memory and
then for the reference plot so then you
have to delete first this set free this
one first and then this one okay so a is
actually totally
fine
now I gave you the Snippets of
code how to do it for all of the other
options which one was the most useless
option four right where we had a flower
so this was a pointer to the pointer to
the array
so to delete that you should first the
reference plot so look at this variable
and delete with square brackets that
whole thing and then delete
plot so we are done with this and this
in both of these
cases plot was pointing to an array so
there will be delete array plot in both
but then we have to be careful so do you
want to look at the code I have the code
for all of these
options uh let's see I have met
someone it's four flowers plot look at
that so I have my
plot option
one I asked for that memory pointer to
pointer then I print it out what I print
out is the value and the values are
should be flowers but what I how I set
up I set up the number of elements so
you'll see the number of elements in
those array and then I delete it and say
plot to null which means that hopefully
I cleared the memory responsibly and I
set the plot to null so I can ask for
another kind of memory completely in
option two and there should be no memory
leak no
unsafe uh grabbing of any kind of memory
right so therefore if I did everything
fine if I asked for new kind of memory
Arrangement print out the number of
elements and deleted it
responsibly then address sanitizer will
not see any problems and will'll let me
do it and let me continue I assign plot
to null and then ask for another memory
Arrangement and this is a regular array
two dimensional array uh it has 49
elements so if I print out one element
it will be 49 for option three and I
delete it
responsibly so I can ask for option four
and should be fine so do you want to see
if uh sanitizer will be okay with my
memory with my
program like
this no problem right which means we did
everything fine
F and everything is clean and
safe and this this code is this this is
the code I just put it uh
sequentially in my
program any
questions let me see I'll go to some if
if anybody from the
class has any I'm going to go to Q&A
maybe anybody has questions because I
don't have any questions anymore let me
see where is my Q&A long time
ago but think of good questions you
should have questions right any
questions where is
my there no questions in
this no there is a way to ask questions
where well at Le uh if you
one um go to the one here okay you can
put your questions here
no but I can read
them Al there's some questions somewhere
oh I know if I go to on slack with this
on slider.com
although are quite
old9 minutes ago and the other one is 30
minutes but we can go here let's go to
this part any questions we can jump back
and
forth this is the
where we started yeah
iot is this all
okay yeah
useful yeah when we have a pointer and
we say
like and then we say like pointer equals
null yeah what's the difference between
these two
[Music]
operations good question what is what is
actually going on oh there's a question
here by the way you got a
question the class have yeah yeah this
is right away we can I'll go back to
your question but yes this is correct
classes have to implement copy
functionality manually otherwise a
default is provided which is member Wise
by value so if you have any pointers you
will not have deep
copies okay
uh so we can draw on some of the here
you are asking what's the difference
between two operators so if I have a
pointer
p and I said integer say pointer
p and then I initialized it so it say it
has some Val let me put this hexagon
value say
0.123 something like that so that's my
pointer it has an address of its
own it has its value which is an address
and that's the Heap say Heap memory uh
with that address right here so and
let's say we put value three
there at this memory address 1 three
whatever okay that's the situation so
now if I say delete
P then operation is not touching the
Heap at all it just says oh okay delete
P that means take the value of P which
is this memory and free it back to the
system it doesn't really change P it
just takes the value of p goes to that
memory address and tries and frees
it so now it can allocate it to
something else so you can so the thing
is that you can still access it
possibly I mean you can still access it
by the referencing because the value of
p is still the same memory
address but it will do it but it will
it's not it's it's not it doesn't belong
to P it belongs to the system now the
system might um allocate it to something
else and start putting values through
those pointers there so that's dangerous
so delete P does not change P it changes
the the address that is found in p as
its value uh but P equals null now this
one operates directly on P it removes
the value and changes it to null
value yes it's very important right
because we again switch these two lines
and you get completely different
Behavior right because then you lose
this value you cannot free
anymore yeah any other questions we had
some uh Q&A
somewhere where was
Q&A I lost Q&A where's our Q&A the last
SL last slide yeah let's go last slide
was
Q where is my Q&A question there it's
this
one oh I'm operating with a completely
different yeah there last slide is
K there yes no no questions okay but
that was a really good question
yeah yeah when we have like fais objects
um the right answer was that we can do
of
St either of them
so how's that decided by the compiler or
no by the way your fa PNG is implemented
uh well depends let me look exactly um
depends what do
you let's go there it's a very good
question depends which one of which do
you mean well there was one like
question and the answer was like they
can be e sub or right right right this
one this one so this is on stack this is
UN stack this is UN stack this is UN
stack this PNG not clear we don't know
because maybe p& is actually a
pointer but this one is very not clear
here so how would we ask for it to be on
stack versus on Hep depends if I said D
equals new
face that it would be clear that this
face is on Hep but I could say d equals
an address of
a and then the it would say pointer to
here and then C equals D would assign
the value which is the address to the
same address that D stores which is this
thing
ination yeah initialization is what
decide would figure it out
yeah okay okay all good questions so
good luck with your
assignments I think we're doing good I
think we
keeping on that's very good I didn't say
goodbye to those
guys let me
see go
back hey
everybody on
Zoom uh goodbye and let me close it
properly
oh yeah stop
recording