okay now for lab memory uh we have four
different files that we may may or may
not have to
edit and and then we also have some
other files in the project that that you
you probably want to want to look at but
um let's let's start
by compiling and and running uh and
seeing
uh where that gets us
so if we front this
then then it's like okay this looks
pretty bad
um so then let's
run with as and and look uh what kind of
problems are we actually getting
here so
requested allocation
size exceeds maximum supported size uh
so let's see what's going on
allocator
uh
58 seems to be doing
something something
wrong so it's it's pointing to this that
that something is going wrong
here exceeds maximum supported size so
so then I suppose PR count must be some
incredibly high value
now the thing that's going on here is
that
um if you look around you'll see that
room count is not actually getting
initialized
anywhere it's it's part of the uh uh
allocator uh
class but nothing is actually ini izing
it right now so that means that this is
some kind of undefined
value now it's very likely that it's
going to be
zero but also in this case it seems like
it's some incredibly high value instead
but uh either way the problem is that
it's undefined and we need to Define it
somehow
um so then we can see that we're using
this file
class some kind of static function in
that in that
class uh well
actually rather than a class it's more
like just a name space where where we uh
Define some
functions okay so we're using the load
rooms but of course this doesn't do
anything to actually it doesn't return
anything but in order to get the number
of rooms well we'll see that there is
actually a function for that so so let's
just uh grab this we don't really need
to worry about the implementation well
we'll see from the header file that
that's what the function does and uh
we'll just grab that from there we we
can trust that this is
a a well defined uh
function okay so so we get the room
count now so this part should be
fine uh oh of course it's part of the
file IO name
space there okay now we run into
something else aloc d aloc
mismatch operator new brackets versus
operator delete so so that implies that
uh we are allocating like an array and
then by the time we're deleting it uh we
don't see it as an array anymore or I
should say the program doesn't see it
that
way uh so we can see that we run into
this error in the in the clear function
well that makes sense like because it
was about the point where we are trying
to delete it that it it's not working
as it should but that doesn't really
help us find the issue like why why was
it not correct there instead we should
look here where it says where that
memory was
allocated uh
room
uh okay so so it's saying that it's it's
creating these these letters
well okay so so then if we also check
room uh 86 yeah yeah we see
that this is about deleting those
letters
um now actually actually in this case in
this case it was good to look at the
delete because it actually was uh oh not
that way this way the time this issue
was actually here uh so okay uh but now
that's
sorted but of course it was good to look
at the allocation as well so we have a
full picture of what's going on um okay
so what next so we still have an issue
with
the point when we're trying to delete
keep buffer
overflow
uh so
then
that then there's something else that's
that's going wrong here so so this is
actually more more so the situation that
that I explained earlier where uh it's
like what it's trying to delete doesn't
really match what it was what it was
created and that's why that's why it's
crashing here uh okay so now yeah I was
a little ahead of myself so now let's
look at the so so allocator
59 kind of okay okay that's where we
create these
rooms
um okay okay what else can
we find
here
um okay okay in this
case in in this case we can really
directly from here it's it's it's not
really showing
us quite where where the problem
is so we can see that that when we're
trying to delete like like something's
going wrong we're allocating the memory
here and by the time we're deleting it
something's going wrong so so somewhere
in between things are going wrong that
that's all the information we can truly
get uh at this
point so so then let's just see what
happens here next so so this is where we
are kind of actually putting the data uh
in here
and what we can notice is
that we're actually incrementing I
before we're even putting anything there
so so then zero ends up being empty and
then by the time we get to the end we're
going to actually be out of bounds so uh
see hold on let let's let's get that
sorted out uh now let's see if that
actually solved the
issue
or if there are more problems to deal
with it seems like there's
still more
problems
now we're kind of seeing that this is
specifically about like
uh the the
letters something's wrong where with
with the letters here
uh okay let's
uh let's see
so here we're we're
copying uh the shroom that we're getting
from file
IO uh so we can
also look here and uh next
room yeah yeah it's returning a copy of
a
room and putting it
there so then let's see let see what the
copying looks like
here uh
so
then we can notice the letters is
actually it's it's supposed to be uh
like a pointer pointer to an array in
the
Heap so now we're just copying the the
pointer
here so we're copying the pointer
to uh this like local copy that we're
creating
here which then gets uh
destroyed at the end so so then we end
up not having the the
memory anymore so so that's a problem so
so we don't actually we don't actually
want to do that we we want to instead
allocate some new memory and copy the
actual data here
um let's see we can we can kind
of we kind of copy from here if we want
to
um max letter so so max letter should
still
be uh the the
same
um so let's make sure that the previous
data is getting cleared first
so
uh yeah yeah when we're doing this that
then we're
calling uh clear first and then
copying okay so so then uh then it
should be fine and and the where we are
copying
to
uh that that should anyway like be
initialized as as empty so uh okay then
let's just fill fill in the data
here um
letter
count something like this right would
that be good
okay now we're actually getting forward
the only problem we we have anymore some
kind of memory
leak and and when you're running into
into memory leaks then uh of
course first the first step is to look
at the destructors that we
have uh
so let's see
here Destructor
Destructor uh I don't I don't see any
Destructor
here what about the room okay there
there a Destructor for the
room uh yeah yeah the destructor for
this room here is it's calling clear but
for
allocator uh I don't I don't see any
disruptor that would be a b big
problem let's
get let's get to work with with fixing
that so let's first uh Define it in the
in the header
file then uh let's see there's the
Constructor
let's um
let's put the
uh Destructor next to
it okay so what do we need to delete
here well well we need to delete
everything that we are allocating so so
Alpha seems to be uh an
array of of
letters so let's delete it as an
array and then rooms is an array of
rooms so let's
also delete
that okay so it seems like everything
that we're initializing now we should
also be
deleting let's see if that
works yeah that actually fixed all all
of it so we actually
we didn't really have to worry too much
about okay what what is this actually
pointing to in this case we just uh
needed
to needed to look at the destructors and
notice that there wasn't any and then uh
get get that sorted out and uh okay if
we
now
um all
right we can
we
can forward this output
to
there compare the outputs and we'll see
that it matches so so everything's
fine uh okay in this case it should
probably
look uh Your solution should probably
look like pretty much the
same uh as what I did that there's like
some things you could do a a little bit
differently
but
um yeah that this should pretty much be
the the the way you want to want to fix
this